<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Person"><frontmatter><addr>favonia</addr>  <route>favonia.xml</route>   <title>Kuen-Bang Hou (Favonia)</title> <meta name="external">https://www.favonia.org/</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> <backmatter><contributions><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><addr>angiuli-favonia-harper-2018</addr>  <route>angiuli-favonia-harper-2018.xml</route> <date>August 29, 2018</date> <authors><author><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local">Carlo Angiuli</link></author><author><link href="favonia.xml" type="local">Kuen-Bang Hou (Favonia)</link></author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>Cartesian Cubical Computational Type Theory: Constructive Reasoning With Paths and Equalities</title> <meta name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.CSL.2018.6</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a dependent type theory organized around a Cartesian notion of cubes (with faces, degeneracies, and diagonals), supporting both fibrant and non-fibrant types. The fibrant fragment validates Voevodsky’s univalence axiom and includes a circle type, while the non-fibrant fragment includes exact (strict) equality types satisfying equality reflection. Our type theory is defined by a semantics in cubical partial equivalence relations, and is the first two-level type theory to satisfy the canonicity property: all closed terms of boolean type evaluate to either true or false.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><addr>abchfl-2021</addr>  <route>abchfl-2021.xml</route> <date>April 1, 2021</date> <authors><author><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local">Carlo Angiuli</link></author><author>Guillaume Brunerie</author><author>Thierry Coquand</author><author>Robert Harper</author><author><link href="favonia.xml" type="local">Kuen-Bang Hou (Favonia)</link></author><author>Daniel R. Licata</author> </authors> <title>Syntax and Models of Cartesian Cubical Type Theory</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a cubical type theory based on the Cartesian cube category (faces, degeneracies, symmetries, diagonals, but no connections or reversal) with univalent universes, each containing <tex>\Pi</tex>, <tex>\Sigma</tex>, path, identity, natural number, boolean, suspension, and glue (equivalence extension) types. The type theory includes a syntactic description of a uniform Kan operation, along with judgmental equality rules defining the Kan operation on each type. The Kan operation uses both a different set of generating trivial cofibrations and a different set of generating cofibrations than the Cohen, Coquand, Huber, and Mörtberg (CCHM) model. Next, we describe a constructive model of this type theory in Cartesian cubical sets. We give a mechanized proof, using Agda as the internal language of cubical sets in the style introduced by Orton and Pitts, that glue, <tex>\Pi</tex>, <tex>\Sigma</tex>, path, identity, boolean, natural number, suspension types, and the universe itself are Kan in this model, and that the universe is univalent. An advantage of this formal approach is that our construction can also be interpreted in a range of other models, including cubical sets on the connections cube category and the De Morgan cube category, as used in the CCHM model, and bicubical sets, as used in directed type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree></contributions> <context/> <related/> <backlinks/> <references/></backmatter></tree>