<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml" root="false">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:addr>//forester/OYOR</fr:addr>
    <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOR.xml</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity › a plan for global identity in Forester"><fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOJ.xml" title="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity" addr="//forester/OYOJ" type="local">Towards <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011P.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA]" addr="//forester/jms-011P" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link>: a design for global identity</fr:link> › a plan for global identity in Forester</fr:title>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <fr:p>Building on my <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOQ.xml" title="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity › analysis of global identity in Forester" addr="//forester/OYOQ" type="local">analysis</fr:link>, I propose that Forester allow any tree to declare that it “describes” a given global identity in the form of a URI. At a first cut this can be done via datalog (but we would probably hide this behind something):</fr:p>
    <fr:pre><![CDATA[\execute\datalog{
  -: {\rel/describes \current-tree @{https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0585-5564}}
}]]></fr:pre>
    <fr:p>Now it remains to explain how we shall surface the fact that a given entity is described by some tree.</fr:p>
    <fr:ol><fr:li>For any identity in this relation, we should automatically create a “disambiguation page” that transcludes all the attached trees.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>When a hyperlink points to a URI that lies in this relation, it should be directed to the disambiguation page.</fr:li></fr:ol>
    <fr:p>There are further implications for such a feature—for instance, in the future we might automatically populate bibliographic information, etc. (But we have to be careful due to the near-universal unusably low quality of bibliographic databases keyed by DOIs, etc.)</fr:p>
    <fr:p>We will need to provide guidance as to how identities should be assigned to (e.g.) people who don’t control an online identity, etc. The rule of thumb should be that we always defer to the preferences of the described person, and to the version of record in the case of an artefact. When there is no canonical choice, users of Forester should do what they like, but they should be willing to update their references in the future should a canonical global entity emerge.</fr:p>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>3</fr:month>
              <fr:day>8</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:addr>//forester/OYOJ</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOJ.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity">Towards <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011P.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA]" addr="//forester/jms-011P" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link>: a design for global identity</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>As we move closer to <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011P.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA]" addr="//forester/jms-011P" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link>, which <fr:link href="foreign-forester-30FN.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA] › publishing and implanting forests" addr="//forester/30FN" type="local">introduces</fr:link> rudimentary federation capabilities, we must address new problems that did not arise in the days when no two <fr:link href="foreign-forester-tfmt-000R.xml" title="Forests and trees of evergreen notes" addr="//forester/tfmt-000R" type="local">forests</fr:link> interacted or linked to each other. The most immediate issue is that trees describing entities with “global” identity (including actual people as well as bibliographic references) will naturally be duplicated across many forests. For example, this happens when one person authors trees in multiple forests, and it happens even more often with bibliographic entries (both for the entries themselves and their author attributions). It is very important to handle this problem properly <fr:em>now</fr:em> in a way that (1) minimises friction and (2) enables us to quietly evolve toward <fr:link href="foreign-forester-klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024.xml" title="Bluesky and the AT Protocol: Usable Decentralized Social Media" addr="//forester/klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024" type="local">more Web-centric approaches to identity as they emerge</fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Below, I survey some existing approaches to identity that we would hope to be compatible with at some level. If you want to skip to my concrete proposal, see <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOR.xml" title="A plan for global identity in Forester" addr="//forester/OYOR" type="local">§ <fr:contextual-number addr="//forester/OYOR" /></fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOL</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOL.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Survey of global identification schemes">Survey of global identification schemes</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>There are several extant schemes for identifying individuals, organisations, and artefacts. Some are centralised, and others are decentralised. Centralisation of identity is not necessarily a bad thing, but it is most viable when nearly everyone agrees on the central authority; on the other hand, decentralisation can help in situations where a single central authority has not accumulated enough trust or prestige to be viable.</fr:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:addr>//forester/OYOM</fr:addr>
                    <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOM.xml</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Centralised identification via DOIs and ORCIDs">Centralised identification via DOIs and ORCIDs</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <fr:p>Nearly every scholarly paper and book published has a <fr:em>Digital Object Identifier</fr:em> (DOI) assigned to it, which are managed by a single authority (<fr:link href="https://www.doi.org/" type="external">The DOI Foundation</fr:link>); this applies to both traditional publishers and eprint servers like the arXiv. Services like <fr:link href="https://zenodo.org/" type="external">Zenodo</fr:link> allow individuals to mint their own DOIs and pin resources and artefacts to them. Due to their widespread adoption, DOIs are a completely viable way to identify published papers and books—and I would argue that any attempt to replace DOIs with a decentralised identifier is likely to be counterproductive as the goal should not not be decentralisation <fr:em>per se</fr:em> but rather to have a reliable, universal way to refer to scholarly content and artefacts.</fr:p>
                    <fr:p>What DOIs do for artefacts, the <fr:em>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</fr:em> (ORCID) aims to do for <fr:em>people</fr:em> acting within the framework of open science. ORCIDs seem to do their job well, but not everyone has or should have an ORCID—nor would every person who does have one voluntarily choose to pin their entire identity to it. Therefore, although I happily use them, I think ORCIDs are likely to face more of an uphill battle than the DOI—which needed buy-in only from major publishers and eprint servers to reach hegemony.</fr:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:addr>//forester/OYOK</fr:addr>
                    <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOK.xml</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Informal decentralised identification via web addresses">Informal decentralised identification via web addresses</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <fr:p>A particularly simple way to identify a single person or organisation is by means of a web domain or an email address. Although not everyone has a domain name, many people have email addresses. On the other hand, people often have many domain names and their email address may change over time; and when people die, their presence on the web is often erased or lost. Therefore, although widespread, this approach may create difficulties with longevity and stability.</fr:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:addr>//forester/OYON</fr:addr>
                    <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYON.xml</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="General-purpose decentralised identification via DIDs">General-purpose decentralised identification via DIDs</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <fr:p>When reading about the paper of <fr:link href="foreign-forester-klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024.xml" title="Bluesky and the AT Protocol: Usable Decentralized Social Media" addr="//forester/klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024" type="local">Klepmann et al.</fr:link> outlining Bluesky’s AT Protocol, I learned of <fr:link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/did-1.0/" type="external"><fr:em>Decentralised Identifiers</fr:em> (DIDs)</fr:link>. In essence, DIDs are URIs of the form <fr:code>did:method:path</fr:code> where <fr:code>method</fr:code> identifies <fr:em>how</fr:em> the DID is intended to be resolved and <fr:code>path</fr:code> is a colon-separated path that should be resolved by means of that method. In either case, a DID is intended to be resolved to a JSON document that contains information about the resource or entity being described, as well as various methods (like public keys) for verifying the integrity of that information. The <fr:em>methods</fr:em> are somewhat open-ended, but two important methods have emerged.</fr:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:addr>//forester/OYOO</fr:addr>
                        <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOO.xml</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="W3C’s did:web method">W3C’s <fr:code>did:web</fr:code> method</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <fr:p><fr:link href="https://w3c-ccg.github.io/did-method-web/" type="external">W3C have specified the <fr:code>did:web</fr:code> method</fr:link>, which in which the <fr:code>path</fr:code> is intended to be a web domain. Simplifying somewhat, a DID like <fr:code>did:web:jonmsterling.com</fr:code> would be substantiated by responding to the HTTPS request <fr:code>https://jonmsterling.com/.well-known/did.json</fr:code> with a document in the appropriate format. The upside is that the owner of a web domain is <fr:em>their own</fr:em> identity authority; in this sense <fr:code>did:web</fr:code> is a truly decentralised identification scheme. The downside is that you have to have a web domain, and you also can never change it ever—the <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOK.xml" title="Survey of global identification schemes › informal decentralised identification via web addresses" addr="//forester/OYOK" type="local">same disadvantage of informal decentralised identification which we have discussed</fr:link>.</fr:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:addr>//forester/OYOP</fr:addr>
                        <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOP.xml</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Bluesky’s did:plc method">Bluesky’s <fr:code>did:plc</fr:code> method</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <fr:p>For a social network like Bluesky, it is critical that users be able to migrate their identity from one domain to another. Obviously users may change or lose their domain over time, but it is important to keep in mind that the vast majority of users will <fr:em>never</fr:em> have their own domain and so they will over the course of their lives jump from one subsidiary domain that they don’t control to the next—just as Mastodon users are constantly migrating from instance to instance, driven to wander endlessly by either the petty tyranny of instance maintainers who think they know best, or by the natural quiescence of instances caused by lack of funds or time, or (in many cases) a combination of the two.</fr:p>
                        <fr:p>It seems that there is no way to address this problem without introducing some central authority—a <fr:em>directory</fr:em> of permanent identifiers that are then resolved to documents that establish cryptographically verified bidirectional links with more ephemeral and human-readable forms of identification (such as web domains). This is essentially the design of Bluesky’s <fr:code>did:plc</fr:code> method, as explained by <fr:link href="foreign-forester-klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024.xml" title="Bluesky and the AT Protocol: Usable Decentralized Social Media" addr="//forester/klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024" type="local">Klepmann et al.</fr:link>:</fr:p>
                        <fr:ol><fr:li>On your own domain, which serves as your (ephemeral) handle, you place a DNS TXT record or file that contains a DID like <fr:code>did:plc:asdlkfh9q8034baliufhbcailurb</fr:code>.</fr:li>
      <fr:li>Someone resolves this DID to a document by querying a central <fr:em>directory server</fr:em> (such as <fr:link href="https://web.plc.directory/" type="external">Bluesky’s own</fr:link>). This document contains a link back to the domain; signatures are used to ensure that every update to the document has been authorised by whoever signed it when it was first minted.</fr:li></fr:ol>
                        <fr:p>Although some centralisation is required here, the use of cryptographic proof ensures that the central authority does not need to be trusted (to a certain extent).</fr:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOQ</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOQ.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Analysis of global identity in Forester">Analysis of global identity in Forester</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>Although Forester aims to become a better citizen of the Web and integrate with emerging protocols, it is a non-negotiable design constraint that Forester still remain usable by people who don’t control a domain  name, cannot run software on their web host, cannot set DNS records, and could not care less what a <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYON.xml" title="Survey of global identification schemes › general-purpose decentralised identification via DIDs" addr="//forester/OYON" type="local">DID</fr:link> is. I also have a feeling that there will not be a single protocol that fits all use cases; what I am noticing, however, is that there are commonalities to all the protocols, and that we ought to be informed by these commonalities. For example, in every case an identity is resolved from a URI of some kind—for example, DIDs and DOIs and ORCIDs all have canonical URIs.</fr:p>
                <fr:p>Therefore, it strikes me that Forester’s approach to global identity must rest on the axiom that an identity is nothing more or less than a URI; we can place no constraints whatsoever on what form this URI takes, and we should also remain flexible as to compatibility with future replacements of URIs (whether in the form of IRIs, or the <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011R.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA] › a URL scheme for tree addresses › what do we mean by “URL”?" addr="//forester/jms-011R" type="local">URL non-“standard”</fr:link>, etc.).</fr:p>
                <fr:p>If we start from that point of view, there some problems to address:</fr:p>
                <fr:ol><fr:li>Even if an identity is not canonically addressed by a tree in a forest, an identity still often needs to <fr:em>have</fr:em> a tree in the forest. One wants to store biographical and bibliographic information, and maybe even personal notes, etc., and at the very least it is very important to be able to browse backlinks on a biographical page even if the page itself has no content of its own.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>Not only must we be able to attach a tree to an identity: we must be able to attach <fr:em>many</fr:em> trees to an identity. This is a requirement of federation.</fr:li></fr:ol>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOR</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOR.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="A plan for global identity in Forester">A plan for global identity in Forester</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>Building on my <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOQ.xml" title="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity › analysis of global identity in Forester" addr="//forester/OYOQ" type="local">analysis</fr:link>, I propose that Forester allow any tree to declare that it “describes” a given global identity in the form of a URI. At a first cut this can be done via datalog (but we would probably hide this behind something):</fr:p>
                <fr:pre><![CDATA[\execute\datalog{
  -: {\rel/describes \current-tree @{https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0585-5564}}
}]]></fr:pre>
                <fr:p>Now it remains to explain how we shall surface the fact that a given entity is described by some tree.</fr:p>
                <fr:ol><fr:li>For any identity in this relation, we should automatically create a “disambiguation page” that transcludes all the attached trees.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>When a hyperlink points to a URI that lies in this relation, it should be directed to the disambiguation page.</fr:li></fr:ol>
                <fr:p>There are further implications for such a feature—for instance, in the future we might automatically populate bibliographic information, etc. (But we have to be careful due to the near-universal unusably low quality of bibliographic databases keyed by DOIs, etc.)</fr:p>
                <fr:p>We will need to provide guidance as to how identities should be assigned to (e.g.) people who don’t control an online identity, etc. The rule of thumb should be that we always defer to the preferences of the described person, and to the version of record in the case of an artefact. When there is no canonical choice, users of Forester should do what they like, but they should be willing to update their references in the future should a canonical global entity emerge.</fr:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOS</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOS.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Request for comment">Request for comment</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>I am hoping to hear other people’s thoughts on this proposal, including any constructive criticisms or suggestions for how we might go about implementing it. You can write to me or the <fr:link href="mailto:~jonsterling/forester-discuss@lists.sr.ht" type="external">mailing list</fr:link> with your feedback.</fr:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>3</fr:month>
              <fr:day>8</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:addr>//forester/OYOJ</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOJ.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity">Towards <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011P.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA]" addr="//forester/jms-011P" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link>: a design for global identity</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>As we move closer to <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011P.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA]" addr="//forester/jms-011P" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link>, which <fr:link href="foreign-forester-30FN.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA] › publishing and implanting forests" addr="//forester/30FN" type="local">introduces</fr:link> rudimentary federation capabilities, we must address new problems that did not arise in the days when no two <fr:link href="foreign-forester-tfmt-000R.xml" title="Forests and trees of evergreen notes" addr="//forester/tfmt-000R" type="local">forests</fr:link> interacted or linked to each other. The most immediate issue is that trees describing entities with “global” identity (including actual people as well as bibliographic references) will naturally be duplicated across many forests. For example, this happens when one person authors trees in multiple forests, and it happens even more often with bibliographic entries (both for the entries themselves and their author attributions). It is very important to handle this problem properly <fr:em>now</fr:em> in a way that (1) minimises friction and (2) enables us to quietly evolve toward <fr:link href="foreign-forester-klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024.xml" title="Bluesky and the AT Protocol: Usable Decentralized Social Media" addr="//forester/klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024" type="local">more Web-centric approaches to identity as they emerge</fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Below, I survey some existing approaches to identity that we would hope to be compatible with at some level. If you want to skip to my concrete proposal, see <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOR.xml" title="A plan for global identity in Forester" addr="//forester/OYOR" type="local">§ <fr:contextual-number addr="//forester/OYOR" /></fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOL</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOL.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Survey of global identification schemes">Survey of global identification schemes</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>There are several extant schemes for identifying individuals, organisations, and artefacts. Some are centralised, and others are decentralised. Centralisation of identity is not necessarily a bad thing, but it is most viable when nearly everyone agrees on the central authority; on the other hand, decentralisation can help in situations where a single central authority has not accumulated enough trust or prestige to be viable.</fr:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:addr>//forester/OYOM</fr:addr>
                    <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOM.xml</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Centralised identification via DOIs and ORCIDs">Centralised identification via DOIs and ORCIDs</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <fr:p>Nearly every scholarly paper and book published has a <fr:em>Digital Object Identifier</fr:em> (DOI) assigned to it, which are managed by a single authority (<fr:link href="https://www.doi.org/" type="external">The DOI Foundation</fr:link>); this applies to both traditional publishers and eprint servers like the arXiv. Services like <fr:link href="https://zenodo.org/" type="external">Zenodo</fr:link> allow individuals to mint their own DOIs and pin resources and artefacts to them. Due to their widespread adoption, DOIs are a completely viable way to identify published papers and books—and I would argue that any attempt to replace DOIs with a decentralised identifier is likely to be counterproductive as the goal should not not be decentralisation <fr:em>per se</fr:em> but rather to have a reliable, universal way to refer to scholarly content and artefacts.</fr:p>
                    <fr:p>What DOIs do for artefacts, the <fr:em>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</fr:em> (ORCID) aims to do for <fr:em>people</fr:em> acting within the framework of open science. ORCIDs seem to do their job well, but not everyone has or should have an ORCID—nor would every person who does have one voluntarily choose to pin their entire identity to it. Therefore, although I happily use them, I think ORCIDs are likely to face more of an uphill battle than the DOI—which needed buy-in only from major publishers and eprint servers to reach hegemony.</fr:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:addr>//forester/OYOK</fr:addr>
                    <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOK.xml</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Informal decentralised identification via web addresses">Informal decentralised identification via web addresses</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <fr:p>A particularly simple way to identify a single person or organisation is by means of a web domain or an email address. Although not everyone has a domain name, many people have email addresses. On the other hand, people often have many domain names and their email address may change over time; and when people die, their presence on the web is often erased or lost. Therefore, although widespread, this approach may create difficulties with longevity and stability.</fr:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:addr>//forester/OYON</fr:addr>
                    <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYON.xml</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="General-purpose decentralised identification via DIDs">General-purpose decentralised identification via DIDs</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <fr:p>When reading about the paper of <fr:link href="foreign-forester-klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024.xml" title="Bluesky and the AT Protocol: Usable Decentralized Social Media" addr="//forester/klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024" type="local">Klepmann et al.</fr:link> outlining Bluesky’s AT Protocol, I learned of <fr:link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/did-1.0/" type="external"><fr:em>Decentralised Identifiers</fr:em> (DIDs)</fr:link>. In essence, DIDs are URIs of the form <fr:code>did:method:path</fr:code> where <fr:code>method</fr:code> identifies <fr:em>how</fr:em> the DID is intended to be resolved and <fr:code>path</fr:code> is a colon-separated path that should be resolved by means of that method. In either case, a DID is intended to be resolved to a JSON document that contains information about the resource or entity being described, as well as various methods (like public keys) for verifying the integrity of that information. The <fr:em>methods</fr:em> are somewhat open-ended, but two important methods have emerged.</fr:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:addr>//forester/OYOO</fr:addr>
                        <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOO.xml</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="W3C’s did:web method">W3C’s <fr:code>did:web</fr:code> method</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <fr:p><fr:link href="https://w3c-ccg.github.io/did-method-web/" type="external">W3C have specified the <fr:code>did:web</fr:code> method</fr:link>, which in which the <fr:code>path</fr:code> is intended to be a web domain. Simplifying somewhat, a DID like <fr:code>did:web:jonmsterling.com</fr:code> would be substantiated by responding to the HTTPS request <fr:code>https://jonmsterling.com/.well-known/did.json</fr:code> with a document in the appropriate format. The upside is that the owner of a web domain is <fr:em>their own</fr:em> identity authority; in this sense <fr:code>did:web</fr:code> is a truly decentralised identification scheme. The downside is that you have to have a web domain, and you also can never change it ever—the <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOK.xml" title="Survey of global identification schemes › informal decentralised identification via web addresses" addr="//forester/OYOK" type="local">same disadvantage of informal decentralised identification which we have discussed</fr:link>.</fr:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:addr>//forester/OYOP</fr:addr>
                        <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOP.xml</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Bluesky’s did:plc method">Bluesky’s <fr:code>did:plc</fr:code> method</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <fr:p>For a social network like Bluesky, it is critical that users be able to migrate their identity from one domain to another. Obviously users may change or lose their domain over time, but it is important to keep in mind that the vast majority of users will <fr:em>never</fr:em> have their own domain and so they will over the course of their lives jump from one subsidiary domain that they don’t control to the next—just as Mastodon users are constantly migrating from instance to instance, driven to wander endlessly by either the petty tyranny of instance maintainers who think they know best, or by the natural quiescence of instances caused by lack of funds or time, or (in many cases) a combination of the two.</fr:p>
                        <fr:p>It seems that there is no way to address this problem without introducing some central authority—a <fr:em>directory</fr:em> of permanent identifiers that are then resolved to documents that establish cryptographically verified bidirectional links with more ephemeral and human-readable forms of identification (such as web domains). This is essentially the design of Bluesky’s <fr:code>did:plc</fr:code> method, as explained by <fr:link href="foreign-forester-klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024.xml" title="Bluesky and the AT Protocol: Usable Decentralized Social Media" addr="//forester/klepmann-et-al-atproto-2024" type="local">Klepmann et al.</fr:link>:</fr:p>
                        <fr:ol><fr:li>On your own domain, which serves as your (ephemeral) handle, you place a DNS TXT record or file that contains a DID like <fr:code>did:plc:asdlkfh9q8034baliufhbcailurb</fr:code>.</fr:li>
      <fr:li>Someone resolves this DID to a document by querying a central <fr:em>directory server</fr:em> (such as <fr:link href="https://web.plc.directory/" type="external">Bluesky’s own</fr:link>). This document contains a link back to the domain; signatures are used to ensure that every update to the document has been authorised by whoever signed it when it was first minted.</fr:li></fr:ol>
                        <fr:p>Although some centralisation is required here, the use of cryptographic proof ensures that the central authority does not need to be trusted (to a certain extent).</fr:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOQ</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOQ.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Analysis of global identity in Forester">Analysis of global identity in Forester</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>Although Forester aims to become a better citizen of the Web and integrate with emerging protocols, it is a non-negotiable design constraint that Forester still remain usable by people who don’t control a domain  name, cannot run software on their web host, cannot set DNS records, and could not care less what a <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYON.xml" title="Survey of global identification schemes › general-purpose decentralised identification via DIDs" addr="//forester/OYON" type="local">DID</fr:link> is. I also have a feeling that there will not be a single protocol that fits all use cases; what I am noticing, however, is that there are commonalities to all the protocols, and that we ought to be informed by these commonalities. For example, in every case an identity is resolved from a URI of some kind—for example, DIDs and DOIs and ORCIDs all have canonical URIs.</fr:p>
                <fr:p>Therefore, it strikes me that Forester’s approach to global identity must rest on the axiom that an identity is nothing more or less than a URI; we can place no constraints whatsoever on what form this URI takes, and we should also remain flexible as to compatibility with future replacements of URIs (whether in the form of IRIs, or the <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011R.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA] › a URL scheme for tree addresses › what do we mean by “URL”?" addr="//forester/jms-011R" type="local">URL non-“standard”</fr:link>, etc.).</fr:p>
                <fr:p>If we start from that point of view, there some problems to address:</fr:p>
                <fr:ol><fr:li>Even if an identity is not canonically addressed by a tree in a forest, an identity still often needs to <fr:em>have</fr:em> a tree in the forest. One wants to store biographical and bibliographic information, and maybe even personal notes, etc., and at the very least it is very important to be able to browse backlinks on a biographical page even if the page itself has no content of its own.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>Not only must we be able to attach a tree to an identity: we must be able to attach <fr:em>many</fr:em> trees to an identity. This is a requirement of federation.</fr:li></fr:ol>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOR</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOR.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="A plan for global identity in Forester">A plan for global identity in Forester</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>Building on my <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOQ.xml" title="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity › analysis of global identity in Forester" addr="//forester/OYOQ" type="local">analysis</fr:link>, I propose that Forester allow any tree to declare that it “describes” a given global identity in the form of a URI. At a first cut this can be done via datalog (but we would probably hide this behind something):</fr:p>
                <fr:pre><![CDATA[\execute\datalog{
  -: {\rel/describes \current-tree @{https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0585-5564}}
}]]></fr:pre>
                <fr:p>Now it remains to explain how we shall surface the fact that a given entity is described by some tree.</fr:p>
                <fr:ol><fr:li>For any identity in this relation, we should automatically create a “disambiguation page” that transcludes all the attached trees.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>When a hyperlink points to a URI that lies in this relation, it should be directed to the disambiguation page.</fr:li></fr:ol>
                <fr:p>There are further implications for such a feature—for instance, in the future we might automatically populate bibliographic information, etc. (But we have to be careful due to the near-universal unusably low quality of bibliographic databases keyed by DOIs, etc.)</fr:p>
                <fr:p>We will need to provide guidance as to how identities should be assigned to (e.g.) people who don’t control an online identity, etc. The rule of thumb should be that we always defer to the preferences of the described person, and to the version of record in the case of an artefact. When there is no canonical choice, users of Forester should do what they like, but they should be willing to update their references in the future should a canonical global entity emerge.</fr:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:addr>//forester/OYOS</fr:addr>
                <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOS.xml</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Request for comment">Request for comment</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:p>I am hoping to hear other people’s thoughts on this proposal, including any constructive criticisms or suggestions for how we might go about implementing it. You can write to me or the <fr:link href="mailto:~jonsterling/forester-discuss@lists.sr.ht" type="external">mailing list</fr:link> with your feedback.</fr:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="//forester/jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>3</fr:month>
              <fr:day>8</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:addr>//forester/OYOQ</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>foreign-forester-OYOQ.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity › analysis of global identity in Forester"><fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYOJ.xml" title="Towards Forester 5.0: a design for global identity" addr="//forester/OYOJ" type="local">Towards <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011P.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA]" addr="//forester/jms-011P" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link>: a design for global identity</fr:link> › analysis of global identity in Forester</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>Although Forester aims to become a better citizen of the Web and integrate with emerging protocols, it is a non-negotiable design constraint that Forester still remain usable by people who don’t control a domain  name, cannot run software on their web host, cannot set DNS records, and could not care less what a <fr:link href="foreign-forester-OYON.xml" title="Survey of global identification schemes › general-purpose decentralised identification via DIDs" addr="//forester/OYON" type="local">DID</fr:link> is. I also have a feeling that there will not be a single protocol that fits all use cases; what I am noticing, however, is that there are commonalities to all the protocols, and that we ought to be informed by these commonalities. For example, in every case an identity is resolved from a URI of some kind—for example, DIDs and DOIs and ORCIDs all have canonical URIs.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Therefore, it strikes me that Forester’s approach to global identity must rest on the axiom that an identity is nothing more or less than a URI; we can place no constraints whatsoever on what form this URI takes, and we should also remain flexible as to compatibility with future replacements of URIs (whether in the form of IRIs, or the <fr:link href="foreign-forester-jms-011R.xml" title="Forester 5.0 [TBA] › a URL scheme for tree addresses › what do we mean by “URL”?" addr="//forester/jms-011R" type="local">URL non-“standard”</fr:link>, etc.).</fr:p>
            <fr:p>If we start from that point of view, there some problems to address:</fr:p>
            <fr:ol><fr:li>Even if an identity is not canonically addressed by a tree in a forest, an identity still often needs to <fr:em>have</fr:em> a tree in the forest. One wants to store biographical and bibliographic information, and maybe even personal notes, etc., and at the very least it is very important to be able to browse backlinks on a biographical page even if the page itself has no content of its own.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>Not only must we be able to attach a tree to an identity: we must be able to attach <fr:em>many</fr:em> trees to an identity. This is a requirement of federation.</fr:li></fr:ol>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
