<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>6963</fr:anchor><fr:addr>grodin-niu-sterling-harper-2024</fr:addr><fr:route>grodin-niu-sterling-harper-2024.xml</fr:route><fr:title><![CDATA[ decalf]]>: a directed, effectful cost-aware logical framework</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2024</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>5</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="popl-2024.xml"
addr="popl-2024"
title="POPL ’24: 51st ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages"><fr:em>POPL ’24</fr:em>: 51st ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3632852</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05938</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@article{grodin-niu-sterling-harper-2024,
  author = {Grodin, Harrison and Niu, Yue and Sterling, Jonathan and Harper, Robert},
  title = {Decalf: A Directed, Effectful Cost-Aware Logical Framework},
  year = {2024},
  publisher = {Association for Computing Machinery},
  address = {New York, NY, USA},
  volume = {8},
  number = {POPL},
  doi = {10.1145/3632852},
  journal = {Proc. ACM Program. Lang.},
  month = {jan},
  articleno = {10},
  numpages = {29},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We present <fr:strong>decalf</fr:strong>, a <fr:strong>d</fr:strong>irected, <fr:strong>e</fr:strong>ffectful <fr:strong>c</fr:strong>ost-<fr:strong>a</fr:strong>ware <fr:strong>l</fr:strong>ogical <fr:strong>f</fr:strong>ramework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs with effects.  Like <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework"><fr:strong>calf</fr:strong></fr:link>, the language is based on a formal <fr:em>phase distinction</fr:em> between the <fr:em>extension</fr:em> and the <fr:em>intension</fr:em> of a program, its pure <fr:em>behavior</fr:em> as distinct from its <fr:em>cost</fr:em> measured by an effectful step-counting primitive. The type theory ensures that the behavior is unaffected by the cost accounting.  Unlike <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework"><fr:strong>calf</fr:strong></fr:link>, the present language takes account of <fr:em>effects</fr:em>, such as probabilistic choice and mutable state; this extension requires a reformulation of <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework"><fr:strong>calf</fr:strong></fr:link>’s approach to cost accounting: rather than rely on a “separable” notion of cost, here <fr:em>a cost bound is simply another program</fr:em>. To make this formal, we equip every type with an intrinsic preorder, relaxing the precise cost accounting intrinsic to a program to a looser but nevertheless informative estimate.  For example, the cost bound of a probabilistic program is itself a probabilistic program that specifies the distribution of costs.  This approach serves as a streamlined alternative to the standard method of isolating a recurrence that bounds the cost in a manner that readily extends to higher-order, effectful programs.</fr:p><fr:p>The development proceeds by first introducing the <fr:strong>decalf</fr:strong> type system, which is based on an intrinsic ordering among terms that restricts in the extensional phase to extensional equality, but in the intensional phase reflects an approximation of the cost of a program of interest.  This formulation is then applied to a number of illustrative examples, including pure and effectful sorting algorithms, simple probabilistic programs, and higher-order functions.  Finally, we justify <fr:strong>decalf</fr:strong> via a model in the topos of augmented simplicial sets.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title>References</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>6968</fr:anchor><fr:addr>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title>A cost-aware logical framework</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="pacmpl.xml"
addr="pacmpl"
title="Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages">Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages</fr:link>, Volume 6, Issue POPL</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3498670</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We present calf, a cost-aware logical framework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs. Taking inspiration from recent work that reconstructs traditional aspects of programming languages in terms of a modal account of phase distinctions, we argue that the cost structure of programs motivates a phase distinction between intension and extension. Armed with this technology, we contribute a synthetic account of cost structure as a computational effect in which cost-aware programs enjoy an internal noninterference property: input/output behavior cannot depend on cost. As a full-spectrum dependent type theory, calf presents a unified language for programming and specification of both cost and behavior that can be integrated smoothly with existing mathematical libraries available in type theoretic proof assistants.</fr:p><fr:p>We evaluate calf as a general framework for cost analysis by implementing two fundamental techniques for algorithm analysis: the method of recurrence relations and physicist’s method for amortized analysis. We deploy these techniques on a variety of case studies: we prove a tight, closed bound for Euclid’s algorithm, verify the amortized complexity of batched queues, and derive tight, closed bounds for the sequential and parallel complexity of merge sort, all fully mechanized in the Agda proof assistant. Lastly we substantiate the soundness of quantitative reasoning in calf by means of a model construction.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title>Related</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>6973</fr:anchor><fr:addr>popl-2024</fr:addr><fr:route>popl-2024.xml</fr:route><fr:title><fr:em>POPL ’24</fr:em>: 51st ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages</fr:title><fr:taxon>Conference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2024</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">https://popl24.sigplan.org/</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The annual Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages is a forum for the discussion of all aspects of programming languages and programming systems. Both theoretical and experimental papers are welcome on topics ranging from formal frameworks to experience reports. We seek submissions that make principled, enduring contributions to the theory, design, understanding, implementation, or application of programming languages.</fr:p><fr:ul><fr:li>Conditional Acceptance Notification: <fr:link
type="external"
href="2023-10-02">2023-10-02</fr:link></fr:li>
  <fr:li>Revised Submission Deadline: 2023-10-26</fr:li></fr:ul></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>