<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12958</fr:anchor><fr:addr>harper-2023-calco-mfps</fr:addr><fr:route>harper-2023-calco-mfps.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Integrating cost and behavior in type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>21</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~rwh/talks/calco-mfps-2023.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"> Plenary invited lecture for CALCO/MFPS 2023</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Joint work with <fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:link> (Carnegie Mellon), <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link> (Carnegie Mellon), and <fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link> (Cambridge).</fr:p><fr:p>The computational view of intuitionistic dependent type theory is as an intrinsic logic of (functional) programs in which types are viewed as specifications of their behavior. Equational reasoning is particularly relevant in the functional case, where correctness can be formulated as equality between two implementations of the same behavior. Besides behavior, it is also important to specify and verify the cost of programs, measured in terms of their resource usage, with respect to both sequential and parallel evaluation. Although program cost can—and has been—verified in type theory using an extrinsic formulation of programs as data objects, what we seek here is, instead, an intrinsic account within type theory itself.</fr:p><fr:p>In this talk we discuss Calf, the <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework">Cost-Aware Logical Framework</fr:link>, which is an extension of dependent call-by-push-value type theory that provides an intrinsic account of both parallel and sequential resource usage for a variety of problem-specific measures of cost. Thus, for example, it is possible to prove that insertion sort and merge sort are equal as regards behavior, but differ in terms of the number of comparisons required to achieve the same results. But how can equal functions have different cost? To provide an intrinsic account of both intensional and extensional properties of programs, we make use of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">Sterling's notion of Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:link>, a generalization of Tait's method originally developed for the study of higher type theory. In STC the concept of a “phase” plays a central role: originally as the distinction between the syntactic and semantic aspects of a computability structure, but more recently applied to the formulation of type theories for program modules and for information flow properties of programs. In Calf we distinguish two phases, the intensional and extensional, which differ as regards the significance of cost accounting—extensionally it is neglected, intensionally it is of paramount importance. Thus, in the extensional phase insertion sort and merge sort are equal, but in the intensional phase they are distinct, and indeed one is proved to have optimal behavior as regards comparisons, and the other not. Importantly, both phases are needed in a cost verification—the proof of the complexity of an algorithm usually relies on aspects of its correctness.</fr:p><fr:p>We will provide an overview of Calf itself, and of its application in the verification of the cost and behavior of a variety of programs. So far we have been able to verify cost bounds on Euclid's Algorithm, amortized bounds on batched queues, parallel cost bounds on a joinable form of red-black trees, and the equivalence and cost of the aforementioned sorting methods. In a <fr:link
type="local"
href="grodin-harper-2023-calco.xml"
addr="grodin-harper-2023-calco"
title="Amortized analysis via coinduction">companion paper</fr:link> at this meeting <fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Grodin</fr:link> and I develop an account of amortization that relates the standard inductive view of instruction sequences with the coinductive view of data structures characterized by the same operations. In ongoing work we are extending the base of verified deterministic algorithms to those taught in the undergraduate parallel algorithms course at Carnegie Mellon, and are extending Calf itself to account for probabilistic methods, which are also used in that course. </fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title>Related</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12960</fr:anchor><fr:addr>harrisongrodin</fr:addr><fr:route>harrisongrodin.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Harrison Grodin</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">https://www.harrisongrodin.com/</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">PhD Student</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0002-0947-3520</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12961</fr:anchor><fr:addr>jonmsterling</fr:addr><fr:route>jonmsterling.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Jon Sterling</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="camcl.xml"
addr="camcl"
title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory">Cambridge Computer Laboratory</fr:link>; <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GP.xml"
addr="jms-00GP"
title="Clare College">Clare College</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0002-0585-5564</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">Associate Professor</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="postdoc-advisor">larsbirkedal</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Associate Professor in Logical Foundations and Formal Methods at University of Cambridge. Formerly a <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">Marie Skłodowska-Curie Postdoctoral Fellow</fr:link> hosted at <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GC.xml"
addr="jms-00GC"
title="Aarhus University">Aarhus University</fr:link> by <fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link>, and before this a PhD student of <fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link>.</fr:p><fr:p>I am a Bye-Fellow of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GP.xml"
addr="jms-00GP"
title="Clare College">Clare College</fr:link> from February 2024, and have been elected a Fellow for the coming year.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12962</fr:anchor><fr:addr>yueniu</fr:addr><fr:route>yueniu.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Yue Niu</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="position">PhD Student</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0003-4888-6042</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>PhD student of <fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>