<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>19036</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">hegel-sol</fr:addr><fr:route>hegel-sol.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Wissenschaft der Logik">Wissenschaft der Logik</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1812</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>19038</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000Y</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000Y.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 1: objective syntax of dependent types">Chapter 1: objective syntax of dependent types</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>To state and prove theorems like <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000S.xml"
addr="jms-000S"
title="Cubical canonicity">canonicity</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000T.xml"
addr="jms-000T"
title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability</fr:link> for a type theory, we must have a mathematical definition of the <fr:em>syntax</fr:em> of type theory. Conventionally, the syntax of type theory has been studied in several layers: one starts with a definition of “raw” syntax as trees labeled by the names of the generating operations, quotients these trees under permutation of bound variables, and then layers on top of this an additional inductively defined formalism expressing the well-formedness of types, well-formedness of terms, definitional equality of types, and definitional equality of terms. After this, one verifies that definitional equivalence classes of well-formed types and terms can be used as the raw materials to construct a universal model of the type theory that has a universal property: any other model of type theory can be equipped with a unique structure-preserving homomorphism from the universal model. The described universal property determines the universal model up to unique isomorphism, if such a model exists.</fr:p><fr:p>We refer to the painstaking process described above as the subjective metatheory, building on the <fr:link
type="local"
href="hegel-sol.xml"
addr="hegel-sol"
title="Wissenschaft der Logik">Hegel</fr:link>–<fr:link
type="local"
href="lawvere-1994.xml"
addr="lawvere-1994"
title="Tools for the advancement of objective logic: closed categories and toposes">Lawvere</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="lawvere-schanuel-2009.xml"
addr="lawvere-schanuel-2009"
title="Conceptual mathematics: a first introduction to categories">distinction</fr:link> between objective and subjective approaches to logic. The objective metatheory, in contrast, involves stating and proving results about type theories and programming languages relying only on the universal property of the universal model and not on any specifics of its presentation; the advantage of the objective metatheory is that it is simpler, more direct, more modular, and more composable.</fr:p><fr:p>Chapter 1 argues that the subjective metatheory in the sense described is redundant: the decidability conjecture can be stated with respect to any representative of the universal model and does not depend in any way on the raw syntax of type theory, and moreover, for all the type theories considered in this dissertation the existence of at least one representative of the universal model is guaranteed for somewhat trivial reasons that have nothing to do with the specifics of type theory. In this chapter, we develop a logical framework for specifying type theories modularly and working with their universal models in an objective fashion.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>