<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>8513</anchor> <addr>hottbook</addr>  <route>hottbook.xml</route> <date>2013</date> <authors><author>The Univalent Foundations Program</author> </authors> <title>Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics</title> <meta name="external">https://homotopytypetheory.org/book</meta><meta name="venue"><link href="ias-special-year.xml" type="local" title="IAS Special Year on Univalent Foundations">IAS Special Year on Univalent Foundations</link></meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Homotopy type theory is a new branch of mathematics that combines aspects of several different fields in a surprising way. It is based on a recently discovered connection between homotopy theory and type theory. It touches on topics as seemingly distant as the homotopy groups of spheres, the algorithms for type checking, and the definition of weak <tex>\infty</tex>-groupoids. Homotopy type theory offers a new “univalent” foundation of mathematics, in which a central role is played by <link href="vladimirvoevodsky.xml" type="local" title="Vladimir Voevodsky">Voevodsky</link>’s univalence axiom and higher inductive types. The present book is intended as a first systematic exposition of the basics of univalent foundations, and a collection of examples of this new style of reasoning — but without requiring the reader to know or learn any formal logic, or to use any computer proof assistant. We believe that univalent foundations will eventually become a viable alternative to set theory as the “implicit foundation” for the unformalized mathematics done by most mathematicians.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Meeting"><frontmatter> <anchor>8515</anchor> <addr>ias-special-year</addr>  <route>ias-special-year.xml</route> <date>2012</date> <authors><author><link href="steveawodey.xml" type="local">Steve Awodey</link></author><author><link href="thierrycoquand.xml" type="local">Thierry Coquand</link></author><author><link href="vladimirvoevodsky.xml" type="local">Vladimir Voevodsky</link></author> </authors> <title>IAS Special Year on Univalent Foundations</title> <meta name="venue">Institute for Advanced Study</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A Special Year on Univalent Foundations of Mathematics was held in 2012-13 at the Institute for Advanced Study, School of Mathematics, organized by <link href="steveawodey.xml" type="local" title="Steve Awodey">Steve Awodey</link>, <link href="thierrycoquand.xml" type="local" title="Thierry Coquand">Thierry Coquand</link>, and <link href="vladimirvoevodsky.xml" type="local" title="Vladimir Voevodsky">Vladimir Voevodsky</link>. The following people were the official participants:</p><ul>  <li>Peter Aczel</li>  <li>Benedikt Ahrens</li>  <li>Thorsten Altenkirch</li>  <li><link href="steveawodey.xml" type="local" title="Steve Awodey">Steve Awodey</link></li>  <li>Bruno Barras</li>  <li><link href="andrejbauer.xml" type="local" title="Andrej Bauer">Andrej Bauer</link></li>  <li>Yves Bertot</li>  <li>Marc Bezem</li>  <li><link href="thierrycoquand.xml" type="local" title="Thierry Coquand">Thierry Coquand</link></li>  <li>Eric Finster</li>  <li>Daniel Grayson</li>  <li>Hugo Herbelin</li>  <li>André Joyal</li>  <li><link href="danlicata.xml" type="local" title="Daniel R. Licata">Dan Licata</link></li>  <li>Peter Lumsdaine</li>  <li>Assia Mahboubi</li>  <li><link href="permartinlöf.xml" type="local" title="Per Martin-Löf">Per Martin-Löf</link></li>  <li>Sergey Melikhov</li>  <li>Alvaro Pelayo</li>  <li>Andrew Polonsky</li>  <li><link href="mikeshulman.xml" type="local" title="Michael Shulman">Michael Shulman</link></li>  <li>Matthieu Sozeau</li>  <li>Bas Spitters</li>  <li>Benno van den Berg</li>  <li><link href="vladimirvoevodsky.xml" type="local" title="Vladimir Voevodsky">Vladimir Voevodsky</link></li>  <li>Michael Warren</li>  <li>Noam Zeilberger</li></ul><p>There were also the following students, whose participation was no less valuable.</p><ul>  <li><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local" title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</link></li>  <li>Anthony Bordg</li>  <li>Guillaume Brunerie</li>  <li>Chris Kapulkin</li>  <li><link href="egbertrijke.xml" type="local" title="Egbert Rijke">Egbert Rijke</link></li>  <li>Kristina Sojakova</li></ul><p>In addition, there were the following short- and long-term visitors, including student visitors, whose contributions to the Special Year were also essential.</p><ul>  <li>Jeremy Avigad</li>  <li>Cyril Cohen</li>  <li>Robert Constable</li>  <li>Pierre-Louis Curien</li>  <li>Peter Dybjer</li>  <li><link href="martinescardo.xml" type="local" title="Martín Hötzel Escardó">Martín Escardó</link></li>  <li><link href="favonia.xml" type="local" title="Kuen-Bang Hou (Favonia)">Kuen-Bang Hou</link></li>  <li>Nicola Gambino</li>  <li>Richard Garner</li>  <li>Georges Gonthier</li>  <li>Thomas Hales</li>  <li><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local" title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</link></li>  <li>Martin Hofmann</li>  <li>Pieter Hofstra</li>  <li>Joachim Kock</li>  <li>Nicolai Kraus</li>  <li>Nuo Li</li>  <li>Zhaohui Luo</li>  <li>Michael Nahas</li>  <li>Erik Palmgren</li>  <li>Emily Riehl</li>  <li>Dana Scott</li>  <li>Philip Scott</li>  <li>Sergei Soloviev</li></ul></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Person"><frontmatter> <anchor>8517</anchor> <addr>vladimirvoevodsky</addr>  <route>vladimirvoevodsky.xml</route>   <title>Vladimir Voevodsky</title> <meta name="external">https://www.math.ias.edu/vladimir/home</meta><meta name="position">Professor</meta><meta name="institution">Institute for Advanced Study</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree></related> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>8519</anchor> <addr>jms-0076</addr>  <route>jms-0076.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Context and overall objectives</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Software systems mediate a growing proportion of human activity, e.g. communication, transport, medicine, industrial and agricultural production, etc. As a result, it is urgent to understand and better control both the correctness and security properties of these increasingly complex software systems. The diversity of verification requirements speaks to a need for models of program execution that smoothly interpolate between many different levels of abstraction. Models of program execution vary in expressiveness along the spectrum of possible programming languages and specification logics. At one extreme, dependent type theory is a language for mathematically-inspired functional programming that is sufficiently expressive to serve as its own specification logic. Dependent type theory has struggled, however, to incorporate several computational effects that are common in every-day programming languages, such as state and concurrency. One of the most extreme forms of computational effect is “higher-order mutable state”, which is when programs can read and write data as well as entire subroutines to the computer’s memory during execution.  Programming languages that support these features require very sophisticated specification logics due to the myriad details that must be surfaced in their semantic models.</p><p>Recently there have been several significant technical advances in mathematical semantics for programming languages that have been ripe for exploitation. For instance, in my doctoral thesis I developed a new technique called <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</link> or “STC” that smoothly combines multiple levels of abstraction into a single language. Inspired by sophisticated mathematical techniques invented in topos theory and category theory for entirely different purposes, STC enables low-level details (even down to execution steps) to be manipulated in a simpler and more abstract way than ever before, making them easier to control mathematically. Perhaps more importantly, the STC method makes it possible to import ideas and techniques from other mathematical fields that are comparatively more developed than programming languages. Another related advance is the use of <link href="bmss-2011.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">Synthetic Guarded Domain Theory</link> or “SGDT” as a mathematical language in which to describe and reason about the behavior of computer programs, potentially exhibiting complex interactions with their environment and with other programs. A third advance setting the stage for this project is the development of <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">Univalent Foundations and Homotopy Type Theory</link>, a new and backwards-compatible foundation of mathematics that places symmetries and reversible transformations of mathematical structures in the forefront.</p><p>The goal of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project has been to combine these three ideas to break a long-standing logjam in the mathematical understanding of computer programming: the denotational semantics and equational separation logic of higher-order mutable state.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>8521</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml</route> <date>July 23, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Free theorems from univalent reference types</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.16608</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We develop a denotational semantics for general reference types in an <link href="awodey-frey-speight-2018.xml" type="local" title="Impredicative encodings of (higher) inductive types">impredicative version</link> of <link href="bbcgsv-2019.xml" type="local" title="Guarded cubical type theory"><b><em>guarded homotopy type theory</em></b></link>, an adaptation of <link href="bmss-2011.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">synthetic guarded domain theory</link> to Voevodsky’s <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">univalent foundations</link>. We observe for the first time the profound impact of univalence on the <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational semantics of mutable state</link>. Univalence automatically ensures that all computations are invariant under symmetries of the heap—a bountiful source of <link href="wadler-1989.xml" type="local" title="Theorems for free!">free theorems</link>. In particular, even the most simplistic univalent model enjoys many new program equivalences that do not hold when the same constructions are carried out in the universes of traditional set-level (extensional) type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>8523</anchor> <addr>jms-000R</addr>  <route>jms-000R.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Background on homotopy and cubical type theory</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>For more than four decades, dependent type theory has been positioned as the “common language” that can finally <link href="martin-loef-1982.xml" type="local" title="Constructive mathematics and computer programming">unify mathematics and computer programming</link>: while it has never been controversial that a computer program is a form of mathematical construction, the running hypothesis of the type theoretic community has been the converse to this claim, namely that mathematical constructions should be viewed as programs that can in principle be executed by a physical machine — roughly, <strong>sets</strong> = <strong>types</strong> and <strong>elements</strong> = <strong>programs</strong>. Thus the struggle to realize this type theoretic hypothesis has been a two-way process, punctuated by moments at which the mathematical meaning of a programming construct is elucidated, or at which the computational content of a mathematical construct is uncovered.</p><p>In the current millennium, a new identification has been taking shape in which <strong>types</strong> = <strong><tex>\infty</tex>-groupoids</strong> (homotopy types), which are an infinite-dimensional generalization of sets; the origins of this new perspective on type theory lie with <link href="hofmann-streicher-1998.xml" type="local" title="The groupoid interpretation of type theory">Hofmann and Streicher’s 1998 groupoid interpretation of type theory</link>, combined with the revolutionary contributions of <link href="voevodsky-2006.xml" type="local" title="A very short note on the homotopy λ-calculus">Voevodsky</link> and <link href="awodey-warren-2009.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy theoretic models of identity types">Awodey and Warren</link> respectively. The main feature of the new language, dubbed <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics"><strong>homotopy type theory</strong></link> or <strong>HoTT</strong>, is that isomorphisms between types are equipped with a new induction rule called univalence stating that all type theoretic constructs respect isomorphisms: to a first approximation, if <tex>A  \cong  B</tex> then <tex>P(A)  \cong  P(B)</tex> for any <tex>P</tex>. The univalence principle is motivated by the phenomenon of homotopy invariance that pervades the large-scale structure of modern-day mathematics, from algebraic topology to algebraic geometry to mathematical physics; as a programming construct, univalence suggests <link href="acmz-2021.xml" type="local" title="Internalizing representation independence with univalence">new approaches</link> to both generic and modular programming.</p><p>Thus one of the main projects for the first decade of homotopy type theory was to substantiate the relationship between HoTT and mathematics on the one hand, and between HoTT and computer programming on the other hand. The question of whether homotopy type theoretic language can be interpreted in sheaves on arbitrary infinite-dimensional spaces (<tex>\infty</tex>-topoi) has finally been resolved satisfactorily by <link href="shulman-2019.xml" type="local" title="All (∞,1)-toposes have strict univalent universes">Shulman</link> in 2019. On the other hand, the computational interpretation of homotopy type theory has involved a reformulation of HoTT called <strong><link href="abchfl-2021.xml" type="local" title="Syntax and models of Cartesian cubical type theory">cubical</link> <link href="angiuli-favonia-harper-2018.xml" type="local" title="Cartesian cubical computational type theory: constructive reasoning with paths and equalities">type</link> <link href="cchm-2017.xml" type="local" title="Cubical type theory: a constructive interpretation of the univalence axiom">theory</link></strong> that reorganizes the higher-dimensional structure discussed by considering all the points, lines, squares, cubes, hypercubes, and so-on that one can draw in a given type. The computational interpretation of the new cubical type theory can be split into two different conjectures:</p><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false" taxon="Conjecture"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>8525</anchor> <addr>jms-000S</addr>  <route>jms-000S.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date>  <title>Cubical canonicity</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>For any closed term <tex>\cdot \vdash  N: \mathsf{nat}</tex> of cubical type theory, there exists a unique natural number <tex>n \in \mathbb{N}</tex> such that <tex>\cdot \vdash  N \equiv   \bar{n} : \mathsf{nat}</tex> where <tex>\bar{n}</tex> is the encoding of the number <tex>n</tex> as a term in the type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false" taxon="Conjecture"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>8527</anchor> <addr>jms-000T</addr>  <route>jms-000T.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date>  <title>Decidability of cubical type theory</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The assertions <tex>\Gamma \vdash   { A } \  \textit{type}</tex>, <tex>\Gamma \vdash { A \equiv  B } \  \textit{type}</tex>, <tex>\Gamma \vdash  M:A</tex>, and <tex>\Gamma \vdash  M \equiv  N: A</tex> are all decidable.</p></mainmatter> </tree><p>The <link href="jms-000S.xml" type="local" title="Cubical canonicity">canonicity conjecture</link> ensures that terms written in cubical type theory can be thought of as computer programs, and was verified independently by <link href="huber-2018.xml" type="local" title="Canonicity for cubical type theory">Huber</link> and <link href="angiuli-2019.xml" type="local" title="Computational semantics of cartesian cubical type theory">Angiuli</link> for different variants of cubical type theory. The <link href="jms-000T.xml" type="local" title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability conjecture</link> is no less important, as it is a necessary ingredient to implement a <em>typechecker</em> or a <em>compiler</em> for a programming language based on cubical type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>