<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><addr>jms-001C</addr>  <route>jms-001C.xml</route> <date>January 20, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.3: Information-flow and Noninterference</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Finally, an application of synthetic Tait computability to <em>security</em> and <em>information flow control</em> is identified: a security class is a phase distinction between low and high security. The preliminary results presented in this section have been substantially improved upon by <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>, adding support for general recursion and termination-insensitive noninterference by combining synthetic Tait computability with <link href="hyland-1991.xml" type="local">synthetic domain theory</link>.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><addr>jms-0019</addr>  <route>jms-0019.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Chapter 8: a Plan for PL</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This dissertation has focused almost solely on the development and applications of synthetic Tait computability in the context of pure type theory, but the author originally invented synthetic Tait computability to solve problems in core programming languages, as part of <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>’s re-analysis of the <em>phase distinction</em> in <link href="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990.xml" type="local">ML-style</link> <link href="moggi-1989.xml" type="local">module systems</link> between static (compiletime) and dynamic (runtime) code. The purpose of this chapter is to identify several applications of synthetic Tait computability to core programming languages, and set an agenda for future work — some of which has been executed and published following the completion of this dissertation</p><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><addr>jms-001A</addr>  <route>jms-001A.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.1: two Phase Distinctions for Program Modules</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A brief overview is given of the applications of synthetic Tait computability to program modules, material that is published in the <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">Journal of the ACM</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><addr>jms-001B</addr>  <route>jms-001B.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.2: Type Refinements and Program Extraction</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <em>refinement types</em> and <em>program extraction</em> via a phase distinction between <em>computation</em> and <em>specification</em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when \({ \phi } \sqsubset{A}\) and \({ \psi } \sqsubset{B}\) are refinements of types \(A\) and \(B\) respectively, then \(\phi \to \psi\) refines \(A \to  B\). In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><addr>jms-001C</addr>  <route>jms-001C.xml</route> <date>January 20, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.3: Information-flow and Noninterference</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Finally, an application of synthetic Tait computability to <em>security</em> and <em>information flow control</em> is identified: a security class is a phase distinction between low and high security. The preliminary results presented in this section have been substantially improved upon by <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>, adding support for general recursion and termination-insensitive noninterference by combining synthetic Tait computability with <link href="hyland-1991.xml" type="local">synthetic domain theory</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></context> <related/> <backlinks/> <references><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><addr>hyland-1991</addr>  <route>hyland-1991.xml</route> <date>1991</date> <authors><author>J. M. E. Hyland</author> </authors> <title>First Steps in Synthetic Domain Theory</title> <meta name="doi">10.1007/BFb0084217</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><addr>sterling-harper-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2022.xml</route> <date>2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>Sheaf Semantics of Termination-Insensitive Noninterference</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We propose a new sheaf semantics for secure information flow over a space of abstract behaviors, based on synthetic domain theory: security classes are open/closed partitions, types are sheaves, and redaction of sensitive information corresponds to restricting a sheaf to a closed subspace. Our security-aware computational model satisfies termination-insensitive noninterference automatically, and therefore constitutes an intrinsic alternative to state of the art extrinsic/relational models of noninterference. Our semantics is the latest application of <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>’s recent re-interpretation of phase distinctions and noninterference in programming languages in terms of Artin gluing and topos-theoretic open/closed modalities. Prior applications include <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">parametricity for ML modules</link>, the proof of normalization for cubical type theory by <link href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Angiuli</link>, and the cost-aware logical framework of <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Niu et al</link>. In this paper we employ the phase distinction perspective twice: first to reconstruct the syntax and semantics of secure information flow as a lattice of phase distinctions between “higher” and “lower” security, and second to verify the computational adequacy of our sheaf semantics with respect to a version of Abadi et al.’s dependency core calculus to which we have added a construct for declassifying termination channels.</p></mainmatter> </tree></references></backmatter></tree>