<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Report"><frontmatter> <anchor>23224</anchor> <addr>jms-0075</addr>  <route>jms-0075.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title><link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> final report</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This is the final report for the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> MSCA project.</p><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>23226</anchor> <addr>jms-0076</addr>  <route>jms-0076.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Context and overall objectives</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Software systems mediate a growing proportion of human activity, e.g. communication, transport, medicine, industrial and agricultural production, etc. As a result, it is urgent to understand and better control both the correctness and security properties of these increasingly complex software systems. The diversity of verification requirements speaks to a need for models of program execution that smoothly interpolate between many different levels of abstraction. Models of program execution vary in expressiveness along the spectrum of possible programming languages and specification logics. At one extreme, dependent type theory is a language for mathematically-inspired functional programming that is sufficiently expressive to serve as its own specification logic. Dependent type theory has struggled, however, to incorporate several computational effects that are common in every-day programming languages, such as state and concurrency. One of the most extreme forms of computational effect is “higher-order mutable state”, which is when programs can read and write data as well as entire subroutines to the computer’s memory during execution.  Programming languages that support these features require very sophisticated specification logics due to the myriad details that must be surfaced in their semantic models.</p><p>Recently there have been several significant technical advances in mathematical semantics for programming languages that have been ripe for exploitation. For instance, in <link href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">my doctoral thesis</link> I developed a new technique called <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</link> or “STC” that smoothly combines multiple levels of abstraction into a single language. Inspired by sophisticated mathematical techniques invented in topos theory and category theory for entirely different purposes, STC enables low-level details (even down to execution steps) to be manipulated in a simpler and more abstract way than ever before, making them easier to control mathematically. Perhaps more importantly, the STC method makes it possible to import ideas and techniques from other mathematical fields that are comparatively more developed than programming languages. Another related advance is the use of <link href="bmss-2011.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">Synthetic Guarded Domain Theory</link> or “SGDT” as a mathematical language in which to describe and reason about the behavior of computer programs, potentially exhibiting complex interactions with their environment and with other programs. A third advance setting the stage for this project is the development of <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">Univalent Foundations and Homotopy Type Theory</link>, a new and backwards-compatible foundation of mathematics that places symmetries and reversible transformations of mathematical structures in the forefront.</p><p>The goal of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project has been to combine these three ideas to break a long-standing logjam in the mathematical understanding of computer programming: the denotational semantics and equational separation logic of higher-order mutable state.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>23228</anchor> <addr>jms-0077</addr>  <route>jms-0077.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Work performed and main achievements</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>I highlight the three main achievements of the TypeSynth project below:</p><ol>  <li>a new denotational semantics of higher-order store;</li>  <li>an equational higher-order separation logic based on the above denotational semantics;</li>  <li>the extension of <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">synthetic Tait computability</link> to support computational effects including guarded recursion and higher-order store.</li></ol><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb> <crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>23230</anchor> <addr>jms-0078</addr>  <route>jms-0078.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of higher-order store</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> plan to develop denotational semantics of higher-order store had two components: the first was to develop a practical semantic model of polymorphic higher-order store without garbage collection, and the second was to extend this model to support the equational theory of garbage collection. For the former, the results have greatly outstripped expectations: I have succeeded in constructing not only the indended model of store with polymorphism, but in fact a <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">model of full dependent type theory with higher-order store</link> — posing the prospect for being able to write and verify the correctness of programs in the same language. This result is the first of its kind for higher-order store, and is a significant advance. In the final months of the project, we have also gone further beyond this result in a different direction, and constructed a version of the model of higher-order store satisfying a new gamut of compelling representation independence equations which I refer to as the theory of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml" type="local" title="Free theorems from univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</link>: in short, two programs can be considered equal even if they allocate memory cells of different types, so long as the two types are in bijection and programs' interaction with the memory cell respects this bijection.</p><p>I have begun to extend these results to include the equational theory of garbage collection, but as the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project has been terminated nearly one year early (due to my recent appointment as Associate Professor at University of Cambridge), this further exploitation of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> methodology will continue beyond the conclusion of the project.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb> <crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>23232</anchor> <addr>jms-0079</addr>  <route>jms-0079.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Equational higher-order separation logic for higher-order store</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>In collaboration with my colleagues <link href="flaagaard.xml" type="local" title="Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard">Frederik Ljerbjerg Aagaard</link> and <link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local" title="Lars Birkedal">Professor Lars Birkedal</link>, I have developed a <link href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml" type="local" title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">guarded higher-order separation logic called TULIP</link> over the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational model of higher-order store</link>. This logic represents a significant step forward in the march toward simple, abstract, and compositional reasoning about higher-order stateful programs. Prior program logics (such as Iris and the Verified Software Toolchain) interact with computer programs only indirectly, by verifying properties of a specific “transition function” that simulates the steps that a (highly idealized) computer would take when executing a program; this style is called “operational”. Unfortunately, the important structural properties of programs are highly unnatural to express at the level of transition steps, and as such, existing operationally-based program logics impose a great deal of bureaucracy by forcing those verifying programs to manually mediate the mismatch between the viewpoint of the machine (which cannot see program structure), and the viewpoint of the programmer (which is entirely based on program structure). An equational, or &quot;denotationally-based&quot;, program logic like <link href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml" type="local" title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</link> instead treats programs directly without needing to pass through an encoding in terms of machine transitions. An immediate benefit of the equational approach is that program equivalences can be glued together directly in any context, a kind of practical compositionality that is unique to equational and denotationally-based program logics. Our development of the <link href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml" type="local" title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</link> logic is a strong first step in this direction.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb> <crumb>3</crumb></trail> <anchor>23234</anchor> <addr>jms-007A</addr>  <route>jms-007A.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Effectful <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">synthetic Tait computability</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A third achievement of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project was to extend the highly successful “<link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</link>” method, developed in my <link href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">doctoral thesis</link>, to the case of realistic programming languages with computational effects. The purpose of this extension was to achieve strong representation independence results, by which we can show the computational indistinguishability of even two programs that allocate memory cells of different types that are linked not by a bijection but by a mere relation, in contrast to univalent reference types. We have gone quite a bit beyond our expectations, as our account of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism"><link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> for higher-order store</link> applies not only to the simple polymorphic store model, but also to the full dependent type theory. This allows many classic results from the literature that previously required very complicated reasoning with the semantic model to be reconstructed in a simpler and more direct fashion.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>3</crumb></trail> <anchor>23236</anchor> <addr>jms-007B</addr>  <route>jms-007B.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Results beyond the state of the art</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The results of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project have gone significantly beyond the state of the art in denotational semantics for computational effects: not only is ours the first typed denotational model of higher-order store compatible with parametric polymorphism, but we have shown that the same construction also gives rise to a model of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">full dependent type theory with higher-order store</link> — a long sought-after result whose implications we have not yet fully exploited. Our model of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml" type="local" title="Free theorems from univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</link> is also a significant break with the state of the art, and points the way to a new and more fruitful interaction between the fields of programming languages on the one hand, and homotopy type theory and algebraic topology on the other hand.</p><p>The <link href="jms-0077.xml" type="local" title="Work performed and main achievements">technical achievements</link> of <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> point to healthy growth in the long-neglected area of denotational semantics and equational program logics, but there is an urgent need for further research to bring these superior but comparatively less-developed methods to practical parity with the more established operational paradigm, which currently achieves stronger results in program verification — which we believe can be accounted for by the twenty-year headstart enjoyed by teams favoring operational methods during the relative dormancy of semantic and categorical methods in programming languages. </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>4</crumb></trail> <anchor>23238</anchor> <addr>jms-007C</addr>  <route>jms-007C.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Policy relevant evidence of the project</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Research in program semantics and verification is essentially of two kinds. On the one hand, there is work that pushes the envelope of what kinds of programs can be verified — demonstrating (at great exertion and expense) the potential to verify the correctness of the extremely complex software that makes our society work, including onboard software used in air planes, industrial production, agricultural production, artificial intelligence, etc.  On the other hand, there is research that aims to rethink from the ground up the mathematical understanding of programming, radically simplifying the foundations on which the program verification tools are built. Both kinds of research are important and rely heavily on each other. Applied program verification is critical because the need to prevent software faults is ever-present, and in order to get any kind of uptake and adoption, we must demonstrate the capability of our tools to handle the very complex problems that are raised by industrial and governmental use of software. Likewise, foundational research is extremely important because when applied program verification hits its conceptual limitations, it can only advance by becoming bigger and more expensive — requiring larger and larger teams and budgets to make smaller and smaller incremental improvements. In just one year, the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project has achieved (through careful attention to building bridges between different mathematical disciplines) what many researchers in this area considered impossible or at least significantly farther off in the future; this experience must be replicated with further grants and fellowships to theoretically and foundationally minded researchers who are willing to undertake interdisciplinary work.</p><p>At the present time, my perception is that applied program verification is significantly more intelligible to funders and agencies because it speaks directly to the fears and concerns that we all have for our society in the age of software domination, artificial intelligence, and quantum computing; this is understandable, but it has regrettably led to the neglect of foundational research at the time when it is most urgent — it is now that we must lay the foundations for the next generation of program verifiers, before rather than after applied work in program verification reaches the hard limitations that more theoretically-oriented researchers have been working to remove. Therefore, I urge the European Commission and relevant policy makers to increase their consideration of foundational research as an investment in the future, alongside their continued funding of the very important applied direction in program semantics and verification.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Fellowship"><frontmatter> <anchor>23240</anchor> <addr>jms-0061</addr>  <route>jms-0061.xml</route> <date>2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification</title> <meta name="doi">10.3030/101065303</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><table>        <tr><td><b>Beneficiary</b>:</td><td><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local" title="Jon Sterling">Jonathan Sterling</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Award</b>:</td><td><link href="https://marie-sklodowska-curie-actions.ec.europa.eu/actions/postdoctoral-fellowships" type="external">Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions Postdoctoral Fellowship</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Funder</b>:</td><td><link href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/research-and-innovation/funding/funding-opportunities/funding-programmes-and-open-calls/horizon-europe_en" type="external">European Commission, Horizon Europe Framework Programme (HORIZON)</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Host</b>:</td><td><link href="https://cpv.au.dk/" type="external">Aarhus University, Center for Basic Research in Program Verification</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Years</b>:</td><td>2022–2024 (terminated 2023)</td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Amount</b>:</td><td>214,934.4 EUR</td></tr>  </table><p>See the <link href="jms-0075.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth final report">Final Report</link>.</p><p><b>Abstract.</b> Software systems mediate a growing proportion of human activity, e.g. communication, transport, medicine, industrial and agricultural production, etc. As a result, it is urgent to understand and better control both the correctness and security properties of these increasingly complex software systems. The diversity of verification requirements speaks to a need for models of program execution that smoothly interpolate between many different levels of abstraction.</p><p>Models of program execution vary in expressiveness along the spectrum of possible programming languages and specification logics. At one extreme, dependent type theory is a language for mathematically-inspired functional programming that is sufficiently expressive to serve as its own specification logic. Dependent type theory has struggled, however, to incorporate several computational effects that are common in every-day programming languages, such as state and concurrency. Languages that support these features require very sophisticated specification logics due to the myriad details that must be surfaced in their semantic models.</p><p>In the context of dependent type theory, I have recently developed a new technique called <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</link> or <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> that smoothly combines multiple levels of abstraction into a single language. Inspired by sophisticated mathematical techniques invented in topos theory and category theory for entirely different purposes, <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> enables low-level details (even down to execution steps) to be manipulated in a simpler and more abstract way than ever before, making them easier to control mathematically. Perhaps more importantly, the <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> method makes it possible to import ideas and techniques from other mathematical fields that are comparatively more developed than programming languages.</p><p>The goal of the <b>TypeSynth</b> project is to extend the successful <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> approach to a wider class of programming models, in particular programming languages with effects.</p>          <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>5</crumb></trail> <anchor>23242</anchor>      <title>Refereed papers</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23244</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-generic</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-generic.xml</route> <date>April 25, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>What should a generic object be?</title> <meta name="bibtex">@article{sterling-2023-generic,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  publisher = {Cambridge University Press},
  date = {2023},
  doi = {10.1017/S0960129523000117},
  journaltitle = {Mathematical Structures in Computer Science},
  pages = {1--22},
  title = {What should a generic object be?},
}</meta><meta name="doi">10.1017/S0960129523000117</meta><meta name="venue">Mathematical Structures in Computer Science</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><link href="jacobs-1999.xml" type="local" title="Categorical logic and type theory">Jacobs</link> has proposed definitions for (weak, strong, split) generic objects for a fibered category; building on his definition of (split) generic objects, <link href="jacobs-1999.xml" type="local" title="Categorical logic and type theory">Jacobs</link> develops a menagerie of important fibrational structures with applications to categorical logic and computer science, including higher order fibrations, polymorphic fibrations, 𝜆2-fibrations, triposes, and others. We observe that a split generic object need not in particular be a generic object under the given definitions, and that the definitions of polymorphic fibrations, triposes, etc. are strict enough to rule out some fundamental examples: for instance, the fibered preorder induced by a partial combinatory algebra in realizability is not a tripos in this sense. We propose a new alignment of terminology that emphasizes the forms of generic object appearing most commonly in nature, i.e. in the study of internal categories, triposes, and the denotational semantics of polymorphism. In addition, we propose a new class of acyclic generic objects inspired by recent developments in higher category theory and the semantics of homotopy type theory, generalizing the realignment property of universes to the setting of an arbitrary fibration.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23246</anchor> <addr>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023</addr>  <route>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml</route> <date>April 8, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="flaagaard.xml" type="local">Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store</title> <meta name="external">https://www.cs.au.dk/~birke/papers/tulip.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">39th International Conference on Mathematical Foundations of Programming Semantics</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Separation logic is used to reason locally about stateful programs. State of the art program logics for higher-order store are usually built on top of untyped operational semantics, in part because traditional denotational methods have struggled to simultaneously account for general references and parametric polymorphism. The <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">recent discovery</link> of simple denotational semantics for general references and polymorphism in synthetic guarded domain theory has enabled us to develop <b>Tulip</b>, a higher-order separation logic over the typed equational theory of higher-order store for a monadic version of System <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex>. The <b>Tulip</b> logic differs from operationally-based program logics in two ways: predicates range over the meanings of typed terms rather than over the raw code of untyped terms, and they are automatically invariant under the equational congruence of higher-order store, which applies even underneath a binder. As a result, “pure” proof steps that conventionally require focusing the Hoare triple on an operational redex are replaced by a simple equational rewrite in <b>Tulip</b>. We have evaluated <b>Tulip</b> against standard examples involving linked lists in the heap, comparing our abstract equational reasoning with more familiar operational-style reasoning. Our main result is the soundness of <b>Tulip</b>, which we establish by constructing a BI-hyperdoctrine over the denotational semantics of <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex> in an impredicative version of synthetic guarded domain theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>        <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>6</crumb></trail> <anchor>23248</anchor>      <title>Manuscripts</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23250</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml</route> <date>July 23, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Free theorems from univalent reference types</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.16608</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We develop a denotational semantics for general reference types in an <link href="awodey-frey-speight-2018.xml" type="local" title="Impredicative encodings of (higher) inductive types">impredicative version</link> of <link href="bbcgsv-2019.xml" type="local" title="Guarded cubical type theory"><b><em>guarded homotopy type theory</em></b></link>, an adaptation of <link href="bmss-2011.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">synthetic guarded domain theory</link> to Voevodsky’s <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">univalent foundations</link>. We observe for the first time the profound impact of univalence on the <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational semantics of mutable state</link>. Univalence automatically ensures that all computations are invariant under symmetries of the heap—a bountiful source of <link href="wadler-1989.xml" type="local" title="Theorems for free!">free theorems</link>. In particular, even the most simplistic univalent model enjoys many new program equivalences that do not hold when the same constructions are carried out in the universes of traditional set-level (extensional) type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23252</anchor> <addr>grodin-harper-niu-sterling-2023</addr>  <route>grodin-harper-niu-sterling-2023.xml</route> <date>July 11, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="harrisongrodin.xml" type="local">Harrison Grodin</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author><author><link href="yueniu.xml" type="local">Yue Niu</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title> decalf: a directed, effectful cost-aware logical framework</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.05938</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present <b>decalf</b>, a <b>d</b>irected, <b>e</b>ffectful <b>c</b>ost-<b>a</b>ware <b>l</b>ogical <b>f</b>ramework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs with effects.  Like <b>calf</b>, the language is based on a formal <em>phase distinction</em> between the <em>extension</em> and the <em>intension</em> of a program, its pure <em>behavior</em> as distinct from its <em>cost</em> measured by an effectful step-counting primitive. The type theory ensures that the behavior is unaffected by the cost accounting.  Unlike <b>calf</b>, the present language takes account of <em>effects</em>, such as probabilistic choice and mutable state; this extension requires a reformulation of <b>calf</b>’s approach to cost accounting: rather than rely on a “separable” notion of cost, here <em>a cost bound is simply another program</em>. To make this formal, we equip every type with an intrinsic preorder, relaxing the precise cost accounting intrinsic to a program to a looser but nevertheless informative estimate.  For example, the cost bound of a probabilistic program is itself a probabilistic program that specifies the distribution of costs.  This approach serves as a streamlined alternative to the standard method of isolating a recurrence that bounds the cost in a manner that readily extends to higher-order, effectful programs.</p><p>The development proceeds by first introducing the <b>decalf</b> type system, which is based on an intrinsic ordering among terms that restricts in the extensional phase to extensional equality, but in the intensional phase reflects an approximation of the cost of a program of interest.  This formulation is then applied to a number of illustrative examples, including pure and effectful sorting algorithms, simple probabilistic programs, and higher-order functions.  Finally, we justify <b>decalf</b> via a model in the topos of augmented simplicial sets.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23254</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-grothendieck</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-grothendieck.xml</route> <date>March 27, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Towards a geometry for syntax</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.09497</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>It often happens that free algebras for a given theory satisfy useful reasoning principles that are not preserved under homomorphisms of algebras, and hence need not hold in an arbitrary algebra. For instance, if <tex>M</tex> is the free monoid on a set <tex>A</tex>, then the scalar multiplication function <tex>A \times  M \to  M</tex> is injective. Therefore, when reasoning in the formal theory of monoids under <tex>A</tex>, it is possible to use this injectivity law to make sound deductions even about monoids under A for which scalar multiplication is not injective — a principle known in algebra as the permanence of identity. Properties of this kind are of fundamental practical importance to the logicians and computer scientists who design and implement computerized proof assistants like Lean and Coq, as they enable the formal reductions of equational problems that make type checking tractable.</p><p>As type theories have become increasingly more sophisticated, it has become more and more difficult to establish the useful properties of their free models that facilitate effective implementation. These obstructions have facilitated a fruitful return to foundational work in type theory, which has taken on a more geometrical flavor than ever before. Here we expose a modern way to prove a highly non-trivial injectivity law for free models of Martin-Löf type theory, paying special attention to the ways that contemporary methods in type theory have been influenced by three important ideas of the Grothendieck school: the relative point of view, the language of universes, and the recollement of generalized spaces.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23256</anchor> <addr>gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 10, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local">Carlo Angiuli</link></author><author><link href="thierrycoquand.xml" type="local">Thierry Coquand</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Controlling unfolding in type theory</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.05420</meta><meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2210.05420},
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel and Sterling, Jonathan and Angiuli, Carlo and Coquand, Thierry and Birkedal, Lars},
  title = {Controlling unfolding in type theory},
  year = {2022},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript}
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a novel mechanism for controlling the unfolding of definitions in
dependent type theory. Traditionally, proof assistants let users specify
whether each definition can or cannot be unfolded in the remainder of a
development; unfolding definitions is often necessary in order to reason about
them, but an excess of unfolding can result in brittle proofs and intractably
large proof goals. In our system, definitions are by default not unfolded, but
users can selectively unfold them in a local manner. We justify our mechanism
by means of elaboration to a core type theory with <em>extension types</em>, a
connective first introduced in the context of homotopy type theory.  We prove a
normalization theorem for our core calculus and have implemented our system in
the cooltt proof assistant, providing both theoretical and practical evidence
for it.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23258</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 6, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</meta><meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on <em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational reasoning based on the <em>logical relations as types</em> principle, in which equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value adjunction with higher-order store, improving on <link href="paulblainlevy.xml" type="local" title="Paul Blain Levy">Levy</link>'s possible worlds model construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23260</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-existentials</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-existentials.xml</route> <date>October 1, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Reflections on existential types</title> <meta name="bibtex">@article{sterling-2022-existentials,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2210.00758},
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  title = {Reflections on existential types},
  publisher = {arXiv},
  year = {2022},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
}</meta><meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.00758</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter> 
<p>Existential types are reconstructed in terms of <em>small reflective subuniverses</em> and dependent sums. The folklore decomposition detailed here gives rise to a particularly simple account of first class modules as a mode of use of traditional second class modules in connection with the modal operator induced by a reflective subuniverse, leading to a semantic justification for the rules of first-class modules in languages like OCaml and MoscowML.   Additionally, we expose several constructions that give rise to semantic models of ML-style programming languages with both first-class modules and realistic computational effects, culminating in a model that accommodates higher-order first class recursive modules <em>and</em> higher-order store.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23262</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-naive</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-naive.xml</route> <date>June 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</title> <meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{sterling-2022-naive,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  year = {2022},
  month = jun,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Na\&quot;{i}ve logical relations in synthetic {Tait} computability},
}</meta><meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-2022-naive.pdf</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter> <p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <em>positive</em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <em>non-syntactic</em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <em>Naïve Set Theory</em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <em>synthetic Tait computability</em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>                        <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>7</crumb></trail> <anchor>23264</anchor>      <title>Presentations</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23266</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-catmi</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-catmi.xml</route> <date>June 27, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Naïve denotational semantics: synthetic domains in the 21st century</title> <meta name="external">http://www.catmi.no/</meta><meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-catmi.pdf</meta><meta name="venue"><link href="catmi-2023.xml" type="local" title="Category Theory at Work in Computational Mathematics and Theoretical Informatics">Category Theory at Work in Computational Mathematics and Theoretical Informatics</link></meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>It is easy to teach a student how to give a naïve denotational semantics to a language like System T, and then use it to reason about the equational theory: a type might as well be a set, and a program might as well be a function, and equational adequacy at base type is established using a logical relation between the initial model and the category of sets. Adding any non-trivial feature to this language (e.g. general recursion, polymorphism, state, etc.) immediately increases the difficulty beyond the facility of a beginner: to add recursion, one must replace sets and functions with domains and continuous maps, and to accommodate polymorphism and state, one must pass to increasingly inaccessible variations on this basic picture.</p><p>The dream of the 1990s was to find a category that behaves like <tex>\mathbf{Set}</tex> in which even general recursive and effectful programming languages could be given naïve denotational semantics, where types are interpreted as “sets” and programs are interpreted as a “functions”, without needing to check any arduous technical conditions like continuity. The benefit of this <strong>synthetic domain theory</strong> is not only that it looks “easy” for beginners, as more expert-level constructions like powerdomains or even domain equations for recursively defined semantic worlds become simple and direct. Although there have been starts and stops, the dream of synthetic domain theory is alive and well in the 21st Century. Today’s synthetic domain theory is, however, both more modular and more powerful than ever before, and has yielded significant results in programming language semantics including simple denotational semantics for an state of the art programming language with higher-order polymorphism, dependent types, recursive types, general reference types, and first-class module packages that can be stored in the heap.</p><p>In this talk, I will explain some important classical results in synthetic domain theory as well as more recent results that illustrate the potential impact of “naïve denotational semantics” on the life of a workaday computer scientist.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23268</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-fics</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-fics.xml</route> <date>February 17, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-fics.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Fixed Points in Computer Science 2023</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an
equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a
combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on
<em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning
about stateful abstract datatypes. What is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of
higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus
compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the
operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23270</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-pujet-workshop</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-pujet-workshop.xml</route> <date>December 14, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Controlling unfolding in type theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2022-pujet-workshop.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Workshop on Dependent Type Theory (to celebrate the Defense of <link href="loïcpujet.xml" type="local" title="Loïc Pujet">Loïc Pujet</link>)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a novel mechanism for controlling the unfolding of definitions in dependent type theory. Traditionally, proof assistants let users specify whether each definition can or cannot be unfolded in the remainder of a development; unfolding definitions is often necessary in order to reason about them, but an excess of unfolding can result in brittle proofs and intractably large proof goals. In our system, definitions are by default not unfolded, but users can selectively unfold them in a local manner. We justify our mechanism by means of elaboration to a core type theory with <em>extension types</em>, a connective first introduced in the context of homotopy type theory.  We prove a normalization theorem for our core calculus and have implemented our system in the cooltt proof assistant, providing both theoretical and practical evidence for it.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>        <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>8</crumb></trail> <anchor>23272</anchor>      <title>Seminar talks</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23274</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-logsem</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-logsem.xml</route> <date>April 17, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics in impredicative guarded dependent type theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-logsem.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Logic and Semantics Seminar, Aarhus University</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Impredicative guarded dependent type theory (iGDTT) is a new version of type theory that combines guarded recursion (the &quot;later&quot; modality) with impredicative polymorphism (universal and existential types). It turns out that these two features are sufficient to define a very simple denotational semantics for System F with recursive types and higher-order store. We believe that the expressivity of iGDTT brings us one step closer to a general metalanguage for realistic denotational semantics, and provides a compelling strategy to elude the burden of operational semantics. As a further benefit, we are now able to justify the extension of full dependent type theory with a Haskell-style <code>IO</code>-monad and <code>IORef</code> types.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23276</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-cambridge</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-cambridge.xml</route> <date>February 9, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Crossing boundaries in program semantics</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-cambridge.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Cambridge Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The great semanticist John Reynolds famously wrote in 1983 that “type structure is a syntactic
discipline for enforcing levels of abstraction”. If the last twenty years of programming language
semantics and verification have taught us anything, it is that we also need a syntactic discipline
for breaking abstraction — in other words, a way to glue together programs and verifications that
cut across abstraction barriers.</p><p>In programming language semantics and verification, the problem of combining multiple levels of
abstraction arises when choosing a “level of detail” at which to view program execution:
for instance, one could look at program execution as a detailed operational process of
discrete steps evincing the cost or complexity of an algorithm, or one could think of
it more abstractly as a black box that only sends inputs to outputs. The difficulty is
that in practice, verifications tend to cut across this barrier between complexity
and functional correctness: for instance, complexity bounds often depend on the
functional correctness of subroutines, and the existence of such a bound implies
termination (a correctness property).</p><p>For this reason, it is crucial to develop integrated logical foundations for <strong>soundly</strong> reasoning
using multiple models of execution at the same time, even when they expose different facets of
a program's meaning. For the past three years, my research program has been to uncover and
exploit the basic “laws of motion” governing all such abstraction barriers, which has led
to the solution of a few significant open problems in homotopy type theory and modal type
theory, as well as some preliminary applications to security and cost analysis.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23278</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-birmingham</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-birmingham.xml</route> <date>February 2, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>New spaces for denotational semantics</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-birmingham.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">University of Birmingham</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23280</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-itu</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-itu.xml</route> <date>November 8, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics in impredicative guarded dependent type theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2022-itu.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Programming, Logic and Semantics, ITU Copenhagen</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Impredicative guarded dependent type theory (iGDTT) is a new version of type theory that combines
<em>guarded recursion</em> (the &quot;later&quot; modality) with <em>impredicative polymorphism</em> (universal and existential types).
It turns out that these two features are sufficient to define a very simple denotational semantics for
System F with recursive types and higher-order store. We believe that the expressivity of iGDTT
brings us one step closer to a general metalanguage for realistic denotational semantics,
and provides a compelling strategy to elude the burden of operational semantics.
As a further benefit, we are now able to justify the extension of full dependent
type theory with a Haskell-style <code>IO</code>-monad and <code>IORef</code> types.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>  </mainmatter> </tree></related> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Fellowship"><frontmatter> <anchor>23282</anchor> <addr>jms-0061</addr>  <route>jms-0061.xml</route> <date>2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification</title> <meta name="doi">10.3030/101065303</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><table>        <tr><td><b>Beneficiary</b>:</td><td><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local" title="Jon Sterling">Jonathan Sterling</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Award</b>:</td><td><link href="https://marie-sklodowska-curie-actions.ec.europa.eu/actions/postdoctoral-fellowships" type="external">Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions Postdoctoral Fellowship</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Funder</b>:</td><td><link href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/research-and-innovation/funding/funding-opportunities/funding-programmes-and-open-calls/horizon-europe_en" type="external">European Commission, Horizon Europe Framework Programme (HORIZON)</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Host</b>:</td><td><link href="https://cpv.au.dk/" type="external">Aarhus University, Center for Basic Research in Program Verification</link></td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Years</b>:</td><td>2022–2024 (terminated 2023)</td></tr>        <tr><td><b>Amount</b>:</td><td>214,934.4 EUR</td></tr>  </table><p>See the <link href="jms-0075.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth final report">Final Report</link>.</p><p><b>Abstract.</b> Software systems mediate a growing proportion of human activity, e.g. communication, transport, medicine, industrial and agricultural production, etc. As a result, it is urgent to understand and better control both the correctness and security properties of these increasingly complex software systems. The diversity of verification requirements speaks to a need for models of program execution that smoothly interpolate between many different levels of abstraction.</p><p>Models of program execution vary in expressiveness along the spectrum of possible programming languages and specification logics. At one extreme, dependent type theory is a language for mathematically-inspired functional programming that is sufficiently expressive to serve as its own specification logic. Dependent type theory has struggled, however, to incorporate several computational effects that are common in every-day programming languages, such as state and concurrency. Languages that support these features require very sophisticated specification logics due to the myriad details that must be surfaced in their semantic models.</p><p>In the context of dependent type theory, I have recently developed a new technique called <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</link> or <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> that smoothly combines multiple levels of abstraction into a single language. Inspired by sophisticated mathematical techniques invented in topos theory and category theory for entirely different purposes, <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> enables low-level details (even down to execution steps) to be manipulated in a simpler and more abstract way than ever before, making them easier to control mathematically. Perhaps more importantly, the <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> method makes it possible to import ideas and techniques from other mathematical fields that are comparatively more developed than programming languages.</p><p>The goal of the <b>TypeSynth</b> project is to extend the successful <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> approach to a wider class of programming models, in particular programming languages with effects.</p>          <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>9</crumb></trail> <anchor>23284</anchor>      <title>Refereed papers</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23286</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-generic</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-generic.xml</route> <date>April 25, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>What should a generic object be?</title> <meta name="bibtex">@article{sterling-2023-generic,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  publisher = {Cambridge University Press},
  date = {2023},
  doi = {10.1017/S0960129523000117},
  journaltitle = {Mathematical Structures in Computer Science},
  pages = {1--22},
  title = {What should a generic object be?},
}</meta><meta name="doi">10.1017/S0960129523000117</meta><meta name="venue">Mathematical Structures in Computer Science</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><link href="jacobs-1999.xml" type="local" title="Categorical logic and type theory">Jacobs</link> has proposed definitions for (weak, strong, split) generic objects for a fibered category; building on his definition of (split) generic objects, <link href="jacobs-1999.xml" type="local" title="Categorical logic and type theory">Jacobs</link> develops a menagerie of important fibrational structures with applications to categorical logic and computer science, including higher order fibrations, polymorphic fibrations, 𝜆2-fibrations, triposes, and others. We observe that a split generic object need not in particular be a generic object under the given definitions, and that the definitions of polymorphic fibrations, triposes, etc. are strict enough to rule out some fundamental examples: for instance, the fibered preorder induced by a partial combinatory algebra in realizability is not a tripos in this sense. We propose a new alignment of terminology that emphasizes the forms of generic object appearing most commonly in nature, i.e. in the study of internal categories, triposes, and the denotational semantics of polymorphism. In addition, we propose a new class of acyclic generic objects inspired by recent developments in higher category theory and the semantics of homotopy type theory, generalizing the realignment property of universes to the setting of an arbitrary fibration.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23288</anchor> <addr>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023</addr>  <route>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml</route> <date>April 8, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="flaagaard.xml" type="local">Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store</title> <meta name="external">https://www.cs.au.dk/~birke/papers/tulip.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">39th International Conference on Mathematical Foundations of Programming Semantics</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Separation logic is used to reason locally about stateful programs. State of the art program logics for higher-order store are usually built on top of untyped operational semantics, in part because traditional denotational methods have struggled to simultaneously account for general references and parametric polymorphism. The <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">recent discovery</link> of simple denotational semantics for general references and polymorphism in synthetic guarded domain theory has enabled us to develop <b>Tulip</b>, a higher-order separation logic over the typed equational theory of higher-order store for a monadic version of System <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex>. The <b>Tulip</b> logic differs from operationally-based program logics in two ways: predicates range over the meanings of typed terms rather than over the raw code of untyped terms, and they are automatically invariant under the equational congruence of higher-order store, which applies even underneath a binder. As a result, “pure” proof steps that conventionally require focusing the Hoare triple on an operational redex are replaced by a simple equational rewrite in <b>Tulip</b>. We have evaluated <b>Tulip</b> against standard examples involving linked lists in the heap, comparing our abstract equational reasoning with more familiar operational-style reasoning. Our main result is the soundness of <b>Tulip</b>, which we establish by constructing a BI-hyperdoctrine over the denotational semantics of <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex> in an impredicative version of synthetic guarded domain theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>        <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>10</crumb></trail> <anchor>23290</anchor>      <title>Manuscripts</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23292</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml</route> <date>July 23, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Free theorems from univalent reference types</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.16608</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We develop a denotational semantics for general reference types in an <link href="awodey-frey-speight-2018.xml" type="local" title="Impredicative encodings of (higher) inductive types">impredicative version</link> of <link href="bbcgsv-2019.xml" type="local" title="Guarded cubical type theory"><b><em>guarded homotopy type theory</em></b></link>, an adaptation of <link href="bmss-2011.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">synthetic guarded domain theory</link> to Voevodsky’s <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">univalent foundations</link>. We observe for the first time the profound impact of univalence on the <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational semantics of mutable state</link>. Univalence automatically ensures that all computations are invariant under symmetries of the heap—a bountiful source of <link href="wadler-1989.xml" type="local" title="Theorems for free!">free theorems</link>. In particular, even the most simplistic univalent model enjoys many new program equivalences that do not hold when the same constructions are carried out in the universes of traditional set-level (extensional) type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23294</anchor> <addr>grodin-harper-niu-sterling-2023</addr>  <route>grodin-harper-niu-sterling-2023.xml</route> <date>July 11, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="harrisongrodin.xml" type="local">Harrison Grodin</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author><author><link href="yueniu.xml" type="local">Yue Niu</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title> decalf: a directed, effectful cost-aware logical framework</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.05938</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present <b>decalf</b>, a <b>d</b>irected, <b>e</b>ffectful <b>c</b>ost-<b>a</b>ware <b>l</b>ogical <b>f</b>ramework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs with effects.  Like <b>calf</b>, the language is based on a formal <em>phase distinction</em> between the <em>extension</em> and the <em>intension</em> of a program, its pure <em>behavior</em> as distinct from its <em>cost</em> measured by an effectful step-counting primitive. The type theory ensures that the behavior is unaffected by the cost accounting.  Unlike <b>calf</b>, the present language takes account of <em>effects</em>, such as probabilistic choice and mutable state; this extension requires a reformulation of <b>calf</b>’s approach to cost accounting: rather than rely on a “separable” notion of cost, here <em>a cost bound is simply another program</em>. To make this formal, we equip every type with an intrinsic preorder, relaxing the precise cost accounting intrinsic to a program to a looser but nevertheless informative estimate.  For example, the cost bound of a probabilistic program is itself a probabilistic program that specifies the distribution of costs.  This approach serves as a streamlined alternative to the standard method of isolating a recurrence that bounds the cost in a manner that readily extends to higher-order, effectful programs.</p><p>The development proceeds by first introducing the <b>decalf</b> type system, which is based on an intrinsic ordering among terms that restricts in the extensional phase to extensional equality, but in the intensional phase reflects an approximation of the cost of a program of interest.  This formulation is then applied to a number of illustrative examples, including pure and effectful sorting algorithms, simple probabilistic programs, and higher-order functions.  Finally, we justify <b>decalf</b> via a model in the topos of augmented simplicial sets.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23296</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-grothendieck</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-grothendieck.xml</route> <date>March 27, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Towards a geometry for syntax</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.09497</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>It often happens that free algebras for a given theory satisfy useful reasoning principles that are not preserved under homomorphisms of algebras, and hence need not hold in an arbitrary algebra. For instance, if <tex>M</tex> is the free monoid on a set <tex>A</tex>, then the scalar multiplication function <tex>A \times  M \to  M</tex> is injective. Therefore, when reasoning in the formal theory of monoids under <tex>A</tex>, it is possible to use this injectivity law to make sound deductions even about monoids under A for which scalar multiplication is not injective — a principle known in algebra as the permanence of identity. Properties of this kind are of fundamental practical importance to the logicians and computer scientists who design and implement computerized proof assistants like Lean and Coq, as they enable the formal reductions of equational problems that make type checking tractable.</p><p>As type theories have become increasingly more sophisticated, it has become more and more difficult to establish the useful properties of their free models that facilitate effective implementation. These obstructions have facilitated a fruitful return to foundational work in type theory, which has taken on a more geometrical flavor than ever before. Here we expose a modern way to prove a highly non-trivial injectivity law for free models of Martin-Löf type theory, paying special attention to the ways that contemporary methods in type theory have been influenced by three important ideas of the Grothendieck school: the relative point of view, the language of universes, and the recollement of generalized spaces.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23298</anchor> <addr>gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 10, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local">Carlo Angiuli</link></author><author><link href="thierrycoquand.xml" type="local">Thierry Coquand</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Controlling unfolding in type theory</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.05420</meta><meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2210.05420},
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel and Sterling, Jonathan and Angiuli, Carlo and Coquand, Thierry and Birkedal, Lars},
  title = {Controlling unfolding in type theory},
  year = {2022},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript}
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a novel mechanism for controlling the unfolding of definitions in
dependent type theory. Traditionally, proof assistants let users specify
whether each definition can or cannot be unfolded in the remainder of a
development; unfolding definitions is often necessary in order to reason about
them, but an excess of unfolding can result in brittle proofs and intractably
large proof goals. In our system, definitions are by default not unfolded, but
users can selectively unfold them in a local manner. We justify our mechanism
by means of elaboration to a core type theory with <em>extension types</em>, a
connective first introduced in the context of homotopy type theory.  We prove a
normalization theorem for our core calculus and have implemented our system in
the cooltt proof assistant, providing both theoretical and practical evidence
for it.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23300</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 6, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</meta><meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on <em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational reasoning based on the <em>logical relations as types</em> principle, in which equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value adjunction with higher-order store, improving on <link href="paulblainlevy.xml" type="local" title="Paul Blain Levy">Levy</link>'s possible worlds model construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23302</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-existentials</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-existentials.xml</route> <date>October 1, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Reflections on existential types</title> <meta name="bibtex">@article{sterling-2022-existentials,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2210.00758},
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  title = {Reflections on existential types},
  publisher = {arXiv},
  year = {2022},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
}</meta><meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.00758</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter> 
<p>Existential types are reconstructed in terms of <em>small reflective subuniverses</em> and dependent sums. The folklore decomposition detailed here gives rise to a particularly simple account of first class modules as a mode of use of traditional second class modules in connection with the modal operator induced by a reflective subuniverse, leading to a semantic justification for the rules of first-class modules in languages like OCaml and MoscowML.   Additionally, we expose several constructions that give rise to semantic models of ML-style programming languages with both first-class modules and realistic computational effects, culminating in a model that accommodates higher-order first class recursive modules <em>and</em> higher-order store.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23304</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-naive</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-naive.xml</route> <date>June 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</title> <meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{sterling-2022-naive,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  year = {2022},
  month = jun,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Na\&quot;{i}ve logical relations in synthetic {Tait} computability},
}</meta><meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-2022-naive.pdf</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter> <p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <em>positive</em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <em>non-syntactic</em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <em>Naïve Set Theory</em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <em>synthetic Tait computability</em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>                        <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>11</crumb></trail> <anchor>23306</anchor>      <title>Presentations</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23308</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-catmi</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-catmi.xml</route> <date>June 27, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Naïve denotational semantics: synthetic domains in the 21st century</title> <meta name="external">http://www.catmi.no/</meta><meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-catmi.pdf</meta><meta name="venue"><link href="catmi-2023.xml" type="local" title="Category Theory at Work in Computational Mathematics and Theoretical Informatics">Category Theory at Work in Computational Mathematics and Theoretical Informatics</link></meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>It is easy to teach a student how to give a naïve denotational semantics to a language like System T, and then use it to reason about the equational theory: a type might as well be a set, and a program might as well be a function, and equational adequacy at base type is established using a logical relation between the initial model and the category of sets. Adding any non-trivial feature to this language (e.g. general recursion, polymorphism, state, etc.) immediately increases the difficulty beyond the facility of a beginner: to add recursion, one must replace sets and functions with domains and continuous maps, and to accommodate polymorphism and state, one must pass to increasingly inaccessible variations on this basic picture.</p><p>The dream of the 1990s was to find a category that behaves like <tex>\mathbf{Set}</tex> in which even general recursive and effectful programming languages could be given naïve denotational semantics, where types are interpreted as “sets” and programs are interpreted as a “functions”, without needing to check any arduous technical conditions like continuity. The benefit of this <strong>synthetic domain theory</strong> is not only that it looks “easy” for beginners, as more expert-level constructions like powerdomains or even domain equations for recursively defined semantic worlds become simple and direct. Although there have been starts and stops, the dream of synthetic domain theory is alive and well in the 21st Century. Today’s synthetic domain theory is, however, both more modular and more powerful than ever before, and has yielded significant results in programming language semantics including simple denotational semantics for an state of the art programming language with higher-order polymorphism, dependent types, recursive types, general reference types, and first-class module packages that can be stored in the heap.</p><p>In this talk, I will explain some important classical results in synthetic domain theory as well as more recent results that illustrate the potential impact of “naïve denotational semantics” on the life of a workaday computer scientist.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23310</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-fics</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-fics.xml</route> <date>February 17, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-fics.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Fixed Points in Computer Science 2023</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an
equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a
combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on
<em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning
about stateful abstract datatypes. What is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of
higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus
compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the
operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23312</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-pujet-workshop</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-pujet-workshop.xml</route> <date>December 14, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Controlling unfolding in type theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2022-pujet-workshop.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Workshop on Dependent Type Theory (to celebrate the Defense of <link href="loïcpujet.xml" type="local" title="Loïc Pujet">Loïc Pujet</link>)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a novel mechanism for controlling the unfolding of definitions in dependent type theory. Traditionally, proof assistants let users specify whether each definition can or cannot be unfolded in the remainder of a development; unfolding definitions is often necessary in order to reason about them, but an excess of unfolding can result in brittle proofs and intractably large proof goals. In our system, definitions are by default not unfolded, but users can selectively unfold them in a local manner. We justify our mechanism by means of elaboration to a core type theory with <em>extension types</em>, a connective first introduced in the context of homotopy type theory.  We prove a normalization theorem for our core calculus and have implemented our system in the cooltt proof assistant, providing both theoretical and practical evidence for it.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>        <tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>12</crumb></trail> <anchor>23314</anchor>      <title>Seminar talks</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23316</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-logsem</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-logsem.xml</route> <date>April 17, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics in impredicative guarded dependent type theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-logsem.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Logic and Semantics Seminar, Aarhus University</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Impredicative guarded dependent type theory (iGDTT) is a new version of type theory that combines guarded recursion (the &quot;later&quot; modality) with impredicative polymorphism (universal and existential types). It turns out that these two features are sufficient to define a very simple denotational semantics for System F with recursive types and higher-order store. We believe that the expressivity of iGDTT brings us one step closer to a general metalanguage for realistic denotational semantics, and provides a compelling strategy to elude the burden of operational semantics. As a further benefit, we are now able to justify the extension of full dependent type theory with a Haskell-style <code>IO</code>-monad and <code>IORef</code> types.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23318</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-cambridge</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-cambridge.xml</route> <date>February 9, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Crossing boundaries in program semantics</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-cambridge.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Cambridge Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The great semanticist John Reynolds famously wrote in 1983 that “type structure is a syntactic
discipline for enforcing levels of abstraction”. If the last twenty years of programming language
semantics and verification have taught us anything, it is that we also need a syntactic discipline
for breaking abstraction — in other words, a way to glue together programs and verifications that
cut across abstraction barriers.</p><p>In programming language semantics and verification, the problem of combining multiple levels of
abstraction arises when choosing a “level of detail” at which to view program execution:
for instance, one could look at program execution as a detailed operational process of
discrete steps evincing the cost or complexity of an algorithm, or one could think of
it more abstractly as a black box that only sends inputs to outputs. The difficulty is
that in practice, verifications tend to cut across this barrier between complexity
and functional correctness: for instance, complexity bounds often depend on the
functional correctness of subroutines, and the existence of such a bound implies
termination (a correctness property).</p><p>For this reason, it is crucial to develop integrated logical foundations for <strong>soundly</strong> reasoning
using multiple models of execution at the same time, even when they expose different facets of
a program's meaning. For the past three years, my research program has been to uncover and
exploit the basic “laws of motion” governing all such abstraction barriers, which has led
to the solution of a few significant open problems in homotopy type theory and modal type
theory, as well as some preliminary applications to security and cost analysis.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23320</anchor> <addr>sterling-2023-birmingham</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-birmingham.xml</route> <date>February 2, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>New spaces for denotational semantics</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2023-birmingham.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">University of Birmingham</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23322</anchor> <addr>sterling-2022-itu</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-itu.xml</route> <date>November 8, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics in impredicative guarded dependent type theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2022-itu.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Programming, Logic and Semantics, ITU Copenhagen</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Impredicative guarded dependent type theory (iGDTT) is a new version of type theory that combines
<em>guarded recursion</em> (the &quot;later&quot; modality) with <em>impredicative polymorphism</em> (universal and existential types).
It turns out that these two features are sufficient to define a very simple denotational semantics for
System F with recursive types and higher-order store. We believe that the expressivity of iGDTT
brings us one step closer to a general metalanguage for realistic denotational semantics,
and provides a compelling strategy to elude the burden of operational semantics.
As a further benefit, we are now able to justify the extension of full dependent
type theory with a Haskell-style <code>IO</code>-monad and <code>IORef</code> types.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree>  </mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23324</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml</route> <date>July 23, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Free theorems from univalent reference types</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.16608</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We develop a denotational semantics for general reference types in an <link href="awodey-frey-speight-2018.xml" type="local" title="Impredicative encodings of (higher) inductive types">impredicative version</link> of <link href="bbcgsv-2019.xml" type="local" title="Guarded cubical type theory"><b><em>guarded homotopy type theory</em></b></link>, an adaptation of <link href="bmss-2011.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">synthetic guarded domain theory</link> to Voevodsky’s <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">univalent foundations</link>. We observe for the first time the profound impact of univalence on the <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational semantics of mutable state</link>. Univalence automatically ensures that all computations are invariant under symmetries of the heap—a bountiful source of <link href="wadler-1989.xml" type="local" title="Theorems for free!">free theorems</link>. In particular, even the most simplistic univalent model enjoys many new program equivalences that do not hold when the same constructions are carried out in the universes of traditional set-level (extensional) type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23326</anchor> <addr>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023</addr>  <route>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml</route> <date>April 8, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="flaagaard.xml" type="local">Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store</title> <meta name="external">https://www.cs.au.dk/~birke/papers/tulip.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">39th International Conference on Mathematical Foundations of Programming Semantics</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Separation logic is used to reason locally about stateful programs. State of the art program logics for higher-order store are usually built on top of untyped operational semantics, in part because traditional denotational methods have struggled to simultaneously account for general references and parametric polymorphism. The <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">recent discovery</link> of simple denotational semantics for general references and polymorphism in synthetic guarded domain theory has enabled us to develop <b>Tulip</b>, a higher-order separation logic over the typed equational theory of higher-order store for a monadic version of System <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex>. The <b>Tulip</b> logic differs from operationally-based program logics in two ways: predicates range over the meanings of typed terms rather than over the raw code of untyped terms, and they are automatically invariant under the equational congruence of higher-order store, which applies even underneath a binder. As a result, “pure” proof steps that conventionally require focusing the Hoare triple on an operational redex are replaced by a simple equational rewrite in <b>Tulip</b>. We have evaluated <b>Tulip</b> against standard examples involving linked lists in the heap, comparing our abstract equational reasoning with more familiar operational-style reasoning. Our main result is the soundness of <b>Tulip</b>, which we establish by constructing a BI-hyperdoctrine over the denotational semantics of <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex> in an impredicative version of synthetic guarded domain theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23328</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 6, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</meta><meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on <em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational reasoning based on the <em>logical relations as types</em> principle, in which equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value adjunction with higher-order store, improving on <link href="paulblainlevy.xml" type="local" title="Paul Blain Levy">Levy</link>'s possible worlds model construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23330</anchor> <addr>sterling-2021-thesis</addr>  <route>sterling-2021-thesis.xml</route> <date>September 13, 2021</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory</title> <meta name="bibtex"> @phdthesis{sterling-2021-thesis,
    author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
    school = {Carnegie Mellon University},
    year = {2021},
    doi = {10.5281/zenodo.6990769},
    note = {Version 1.1, revised May 2022},
    number = {CMU-CS-21-142},
    title = {First Steps in Synthetic {Tait} Computability: The Objective Metatheory of Cubical Type Theory},
  }
  </meta><meta name="doi">10.5281/zenodo.6990769</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The implementation and semantics of dependent type theories can be studied in a syntax-independent way: the objective metatheory of dependent type theories exploits the universal properties of their syntactic categories to endow them with computational content, mathematical meaning, and practical implementation (normalization, type checking, elaboration). The semantic methods of the objective metatheory inform the design and implementation of correct-by-construction elaboration algorithms, promising a principled interface between real proof assistants and ideal mathematics.</p><p>In this dissertation, I add synthetic Tait computability to the arsenal of the objective metatheorist. Synthetic Tait computability is a mathematical machine to reduce difficult problems of type theory and programming languages to trivial theorems of topos theory. First employed by Sterling and Harper to reconstruct the theory of program modules and their phase separated parametricity, synthetic Tait computability is deployed here to resolve the last major open question in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory: normalization of open terms.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23332</anchor> <addr>hottbook</addr>  <route>hottbook.xml</route> <date>2013</date> <authors><author>The Univalent Foundations Program</author> </authors> <title>Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics</title> <meta name="external">https://homotopytypetheory.org/book</meta><meta name="venue"><link href="ias-special-year.xml" type="local" title="IAS Special Year on Univalent Foundations">IAS Special Year on Univalent Foundations</link></meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Homotopy type theory is a new branch of mathematics that combines aspects of several different fields in a surprising way. It is based on a recently discovered connection between homotopy theory and type theory. It touches on topics as seemingly distant as the homotopy groups of spheres, the algorithms for type checking, and the definition of weak <tex>\infty</tex>-groupoids. Homotopy type theory offers a new “univalent” foundation of mathematics, in which a central role is played by <link href="vladimirvoevodsky.xml" type="local" title="Vladimir Voevodsky">Voevodsky</link>’s univalence axiom and higher inductive types. The present book is intended as a first systematic exposition of the basics of univalent foundations, and a collection of examples of this new style of reasoning — but without requiring the reader to know or learn any formal logic, or to use any computer proof assistant. We believe that univalent foundations will eventually become a viable alternative to set theory as the “implicit foundation” for the unformalized mathematics done by most mathematicians.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>23334</anchor> <addr>bmss-2011</addr>  <route>bmss-2011.xml</route> <date>2011</date> <authors><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author><author><link href="rasmusmøgelberg.xml" type="local">Rasmus Ejlers Møgelberg</link></author><author>Jan Schwinghammer</author><author>Kristian Støvring</author> </authors> <title>First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees</title> <meta name="bibtex">@inproceedings{bmss-2011,
  author = {Birkedal, Lars and M{\o{}}gelberg, Rasmus Ejlers and Schwinghammer, Jan and St\o{}vring, Kristian},
  address = {Washington, DC, USA},
  publisher = {IEEE Computer Society},
  booktitle = {Proceedings of the 2011 IEEE 26th Annual Symposium on Logic in Computer Science},
  year = {2011},
  doi = {10.1109/LICS.2011.16},
  eprint = {1208.3596},
  eprintclass = {cs.LO},
  eprinttype = {arXiv},
  isbn = {978-0-7695-4412-0},
  pages = {55--64},
  title = {First Steps in Synthetic Guarded Domain Theory: Step-Indexing in the Topos of Trees},
}</meta><meta name="doi">10.1109/LICS.2011.16</meta><meta name="venue">Proceedings of the 2011 IEEE 26th Annual Symposium on Logic in Computer Science</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present the topos <tex>\mathcal{S}</tex> of trees as a model of guarded recursion. We study the internal dependently-typed higher-order logic of <tex>\mathcal{S}</tex> and show that <tex>\mathcal{S}</tex> models two modal operators, on predicates and types, which serve as guards in recursive definitions of terms, predicates, and types. In particular, we show how to solve recursive type equations involving dependent types. We propose that the internal logic of <tex>\mathcal{S}</tex> provides the right setting for the synthetic construction of abstract versions of step-indexed models of programming languages and program logics. As an example, we show how to construct a model of a programming language with higher-order store and recursive types entirely inside the internal logic of <tex>\mathcal{S}</tex>.</p></mainmatter> </tree></references></backmatter></tree>