<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>jms-005T</addr>  <route>jms-005T.xml</route>  <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Bibliography of synthetic Tait computability</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This page collects papers and dissertations about Synthetic Tait Computability, also known as the <em>logical relations as types</em> / LRAT principle; if you have written a paper or dissertation on this topic, please <link href="mailto:jon@jonmsterling.com" type="external">write to me</link> to have it added to this list.</p><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <title>Refereed papers</title></frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>uemura-2023-fscd</addr>  <route>uemura-2023-fscd.xml</route> <date>December 5, 2022</date> <authors><author>Taichi Uemura</author> </authors> <title>Homotopy type theory as internal languages of diagrams of ∞-logoses</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @inproceedings{uemura:2023:fscd,
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  editor = {Gaboardi, Marco and van Raamsdonk, Femke},
  address = {Dagstuhl, Germany},
  publisher = {Schloss Dagstuhl -- Leibniz-Zentrum f\&quot;{u}r Informatik},
  url = {https://drops.dagstuhl.de/opus/volltexte/2023/17989},
  booktitle = {8th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2023)},
  year = {2023},
  doi = {10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2023.5},
  isbn = {978-3-95977-277-8},
  issn = {1868-8969},
  pages = {5:1--5:19},
  series = {Leibniz International Proceedings in Informatics (LIPIcs)},
  title = {{Homotopy Type Theory as Internal Languages of Diagrams of $\infty$-Logoses}},
  volume = {260}
}
 </meta><meta name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2023.5</meta><meta name="venue">8th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2023)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>gratzer-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>April 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>A stratified approach to Löb induction</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @inproceedings{gratzer-birkedal:2022,
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  editor = {Felty, Amy},
  address = {Dagstuhl, Germany},
  publisher = {Schloss Dagstuhl--Leibniz-Zentrum fuer Informatik},
  url = {https://jozefg.github.io/papers/a-stratified-approach-to-lob-induction.pdf},
  booktitle = {7th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2022)},
  year = {2022},
  month = aug,
  doi = {10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.23},
  series = {Leibniz International Proceedings in Informatics (LIPIcs)},
  title = {A Stratified Approach to {L\&quot;{o}b} Induction},
  volume = {228},
}
 </meta><meta name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.23</meta><meta name="venue">International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>gratzer-2022</addr>  <route>gratzer-2022.xml</route> <date>April 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author> </authors> <title>Normalization for multimodal type theory</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @inproceedings{gratzer:2022,
  title = {Normalization for Multimodal Type Theory},
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel},
  address = {New York, NY, USA},
  publisher = {Association for Computing Machinery},
  booktitle = {Proceedings of the 37th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science},
  year = {2022},
  doi = {10.1145/3531130.3532398},
  url = {https://jozefg.github.io/papers/2022-normalization-for-multimodal-type-theory-short.pdf},
}
 </meta><meta name="doi">10.1145/3531130.3532398</meta><meta name="venue">Symposium on Logic and Computer Science (LICS)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022</addr>  <route>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml</route> <date>January 1, 2022</date> <authors><author>Yue Niu</author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author>Harrison Grodin</author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>A cost-aware logical framework</title> <meta name="venue">Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages, Volume 6, Issue POPL</meta><meta name="doi">10.1145/3498670</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present calf, a cost-aware logical framework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs. Taking inspiration from recent work that reconstructs traditional aspects of programming languages in terms of a modal account of phase distinctions, we argue that the cost structure of programs motivates a phase distinction between intension and extension. Armed with this technology, we contribute a synthetic account of cost structure as a computational effect in which cost-aware programs enjoy an internal noninterference property: input/output behavior cannot depend on cost. As a full-spectrum dependent type theory, calf presents a unified language for programming and specification of both cost and behavior that can be integrated smoothly with existing mathematical libraries available in type theoretic proof assistants.</p><p>We evaluate calf as a general framework for cost analysis by implementing two fundamental techniques for algorithm analysis: the method of recurrence relations and physicist’s method for amortized analysis. We deploy these techniques on a variety of case studies: we prove a tight, closed bound for Euclid’s algorithm, verify the amortized complexity of batched queues, and derive tight, closed bounds for the sequential and parallel complexity of merge sort, all fully mechanized in the Agda proof assistant. Lastly we substantiate the soundness of quantitative reasoning in calf by means of a model construction.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-harper-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2022.xml</route> <date>2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>Sheaf Semantics of Termination-Insensitive Noninterference</title> <meta name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.5</meta><meta name="venue">7th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2022)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We propose a new sheaf semantics for secure information flow over a space of abstract behaviors, based on synthetic domain theory: security classes are open/closed partitions, types are sheaves, and redaction of sensitive information corresponds to restricting a sheaf to a closed subspace. Our security-aware computational model satisfies termination-insensitive noninterference automatically, and therefore constitutes an intrinsic alternative to state of the art extrinsic/relational models of noninterference. Our semantics is the latest application of <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>’s recent re-interpretation of phase distinctions and noninterference in programming languages in terms of Artin gluing and topos-theoretic open/closed modalities. Prior applications include <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">parametricity for ML modules</link>, the proof of normalization for cubical type theory by <link href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Angiuli</link>, and the cost-aware logical framework of <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Niu et al</link>. In this paper we employ the phase distinction perspective twice: first to reconstruct the syntax and semantics of secure information flow as a lattice of phase distinctions between “higher” and “lower” security, and second to verify the computational adequacy of our sheaf semantics with respect to a version of Abadi et al.’s dependency core calculus to which we have added a construct for declassifying termination channels.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-harper-2021</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2021.xml</route> <date>December 1, 2021</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>Logical Relations as Types: Proof-Relevant Parametricity for Program Modules</title> <meta name="venue">Journal of the ACM, Volume 68, Issue 6</meta><meta name="doi">10.1145/3474834</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The theory of program modules is of interest to language designers not only for its practical importance to programming, but also because it lies at the nexus of three fundamental concerns in language design: the <em>phase distinction</em>, <em>computational effects</em>, and <em>type abstraction</em>. We contribute a fresh “synthetic” take on program modules that treats modules as the fundamental constructs, in which the usual suspects of prior module calculi (kinds, constructors, dynamic programs) are rendered as derived notions in terms of a modal type-theoretic account of the phase distinction. We simplify the account of type abstraction (embodied in the generativity of module functors) through a <em>lax modality</em> that encapsulates computational effects, placing <em>projectibility</em> of module expressions on a type-theoretic basis.</p><p>Our main result is a (significant) proof-relevant and phase-sensitive generalization of the Reynolds abstraction theorem for a calculus of program modules, based on a new kind of logical relation called a <em>parametricity structure</em>. Parametricity structures generalize the proof-irrelevant relations of classical parametricity to proof-<em>relevant</em> families, where there may be non-trivial evidence witnessing the relatedness of two programs—simplifying the metatheory of strong sums over the collection of types, for although there can be no “relation classifying relations,” one easily accommodates a “family classifying small families.”</p><p>Using the insight that logical relations/parametricity is itself a form of phase distinction between the syntactic and the semantic, we contribute a new synthetic approach to phase separated parametricity based on the slogan <em>logical relations as types</em>, by iterating our modal account of the phase distinction. We axiomatize a dependent type theory of parametricity structures using two pairs of complementary modalities (syntactic, semantic) and (static, dynamic), substantiated using the topos theoretic <em>Artin gluing</em> construction. Then, to construct a simulation between two implementations of an abstract type, one simply programs a third implementation whose type component carries the representation invariant.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-angiuli-2021</addr>  <route>sterling-angiuli-2021.xml</route> <date>July 7, 2021</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local">Carlo Angiuli</link></author> </authors> <title>Normalization for Cubical Type Theory</title> <meta name="venue">2021 36th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science (LICS)</meta><meta name="doi">10.1109/LICS52264.2021.9470719</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We prove normalization for (univalent, Cartesian) cubical type theory, closing the last major open problem in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory. Our normalization result is reduction-free, in the sense of yielding a bijection between equivalence classes of terms in context and a tractable language of <tex>\beta</tex>/<tex>\eta</tex>-normal forms. As corollaries we obtain both decidability of judgmental equality and the injectivity of type constructors.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter></tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <title>Unpublished manuscripts</title></frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>grodin-sterling-niu-harper-2023</addr>  <route>grodin-sterling-niu-harper-2023.xml</route> <date>July 11, 2023</date> <authors><author>Harrison Grodin</author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author>Yue Niu</author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>Decalf: A Directed, Effectful Cost-Aware Logical Framework</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.05938</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present <b>decalf</b>, a <b>d</b>irected, <b>e</b>ffectful <b>c</b>ost-<b>a</b>ware <b>l</b>ogical <b>f</b>ramework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs with effects.  Like <b>calf</b>, the language is based on a formal <em>phase distinction</em> between the <em>extension</em> and the <em>intension</em> of a program, its pure <em>behavior</em> as distinct from its <em>cost</em> measured by an effectful step-counting primitive. The type theory ensures that the behavior is unaffected by the cost accounting.  Unlike <b>calf</b>, the present language takes account of <em>effects</em>, such as probabilistic choice and mutable state; this extension requires a reformulation of <b>calf</b>’s approach to cost accounting: rather than rely on a “separable” notion of cost, here <em>a cost bound is simply another program</em>. To make this formal, we equip every type with an intrinsic preorder, relaxing the precise cost accounting intrinsic to a program to a looser but nevertheless informative estimate.  For example, the cost bound of a probabilistic program is itself a probabilistic program that specifies the distribution of costs.  This approach serves as a streamlined alternative to the standard method of isolating a recurrence that bounds the cost in a manner that readily extends to higher-order, effectful programs.</p><p>The development proceeds by first introducing the <b>decalf</b> type system, which is based on an intrinsic ordering among terms that restricts in the extensional phase to extensional equality, but in the intensional phase reflects an approximation of the cost of a program of interest.  This formulation is then applied to a number of illustrative examples, including pure and effectful sorting algorithms, simple probabilistic programs, and higher-order functions.  Finally, we justify <b>decalf</b> via a model in the topos of augmented simplicial sets.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-2023-grothendieck</addr>  <route>sterling-2023-grothendieck.xml</route> <date>March 27, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Towards a geometry for syntax</title> <meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-2023-grothendieck.pdf</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>It often happens that free algebras for a given theory satisfy useful reasoning principles that are not preserved under homomorphisms of algebras, and hence need not hold in an arbitrary algebra. For instance, if <tex>M</tex> is the free monoid on a set <tex>A</tex>, then the scalar multiplication function <tex>A  \times  M \to  M</tex> is injective. Therefore, when reasoning in the formal theory of monoids under <tex>A</tex>, it is possible to use this injectivity law to make sound deductions even about monoids under A for which scalar multiplication is not injective — a principle known in algebra as the permanence of identity. Properties of this kind are of fundamental practical importance to the logicians and computer scientists who design and implement computerized proof assistants like Lean and Coq, as they enable the formal reductions of equational problems that make type checking tractable.</p><p>As type theories have become increasingly more sophisticated, it has become more and more difficult to establish the useful properties of their free models that facilitate effective implementation. These obstructions have facilitated a fruitful return to foundational work in type theory, which has taken on a more geometrical flavor than ever before. Here we expose a modern way to prove a highly non-trivial injectivity law for free models of Martin-Löf type theory, paying special attention to the ways that contemporary methods in type theory have been influenced by three important ideas of the Grothendieck school: the relative point of view, the language of universes, and the recollement of generalized spaces.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>uemura-2022-coh</addr>  <route>uemura-2022-coh.xml</route> <date>December 22, 2022</date> <authors><author>Taichi Uemura</author> </authors> <title>Normalization and coherence for ∞-type theories</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @unpublished{uemura:2022:coh,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2212.11764},
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  title = {Normalization and coherence for $\infty$-type theories},
  publisher = {arXiv},
  year = {2022},
}
 </meta><meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2212.11764</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 10, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local">Carlo Angiuli</link></author><author>Thierry Coquand</author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Controlling unfolding in type theory</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.05420</meta><meta name="bibtex">
 @unpublished{gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal:2022,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2210.05420},
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel and Sterling, Jonathan and Angiuli, Carlo and Coquand, Thierry and Birkedal, Lars},
  title = {Controlling unfolding in type theory},
  year = {2022},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript}
}
 </meta><meta name="venue">Under review</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a novel mechanism for controlling the unfolding of definitions in
dependent type theory. Traditionally, proof assistants let users specify
whether each definition can or cannot be unfolded in the remainder of a
development; unfolding definitions is often necessary in order to reason about
them, but an excess of unfolding can result in brittle proofs and intractably
large proof goals. In our system, definitions are by default not unfolded, but
users can selectively unfold them in a local manner. We justify our mechanism
by means of elaboration to a core type theory with <em>extension types</em>, a
connective first introduced in the context of homotopy type theory.  We prove a
normalization theorem for our core calculus and have implemented our system in
the cooltt proof assistant, providing both theoretical and practical evidence
for it.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 6, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</meta><meta name="bibtex">
 @unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal:2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}
 </meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type
theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order)reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded
recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on
<em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with
polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We
then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational
reasoning based on the <em>logical relations as types</em> principle, in which
equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established
synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a
general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value
adjunction with higher-order store, improving on Levy's possible worlds model
construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of
higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically
definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our
work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the
purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>niu-harper-2022</addr>  <route>niu-harper-2022.xml</route> <date>September 26, 2022</date> <authors><author>Yue Niu</author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>A metalanguage for cost-aware denotational semantics</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @article{niu-harper:2022,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2209.12669},
  author = {Niu, Yue and Harper, Robert},
  title = {A metalanguage for cost-aware denotational semantics},
  publisher = {arXiv},
  year = {2022},
}
 </meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-2022-naive</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-naive.xml</route> <date>June 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @unpublished{sterling:2022:naive,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  year = {2022},
  month = jun,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Na\&quot;{i}ve logical relations in synthetic {Tait} computability},
}
 </meta><meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-2022-naive.pdf</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter> <p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <em>positive</em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <em>non-syntactic</em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <em>Naïve Set Theory</em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <em>synthetic Tait computability</em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>gratzer-2021-crisp-induction</addr>  <route>gratzer-2021-crisp-induction.xml</route> <date>2021</date> <authors><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author> </authors> <title>Crisp induction for intensional identity types</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @unpublished{gratzer:2021:crisp-induction,
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel},
  url = {https://jozefg.github.io/papers/crisp-induction-for-intensional-identity-types.pdf},
  year = {2021},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Crisp induction for intensional identity types},
}
 </meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree></mainmatter></tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>3</crumb></trail> <title>Dissertations</title></frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-2021-thesis</addr>  <route>sterling-2021-thesis.xml</route> <date>September 13, 2021</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability: The Objective Metatheory of Cubical Type Theory</title> <meta name="bibtex">
  @phdthesis{sterling-2021-thesis,
    author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
    school = {Carnegie Mellon University},
    year = {2021},
    doi = {10.5281/zenodo.6990769},
    note = {Version 1.1, revised May 2022},
    number = {CMU-CS-21-142},
    title = {First Steps in Synthetic {Tait} Computability: The Objective Metatheory of Cubical Type Theory},
  }
  </meta><meta name="doi">10.5281/zenodo.6990769</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The implementation and semantics of dependent type theories can be studied in a syntax-independent way: the objective metatheory of dependent type theories exploits the universal properties of their syntactic categories to endow them with computational content, mathematical meaning, and practical implementation (normalization, type checking, elaboration). The semantic methods of the objective metatheory inform the design and implementation of correct-by-construction elaboration algorithms, promising a principled interface between real proof assistants and ideal mathematics.</p><p>In this dissertation, I add synthetic Tait computability to the arsenal of the objective metatheorist. Synthetic Tait computability is a mathematical machine to reduce difficult problems of type theory and programming languages to trivial theorems of topos theory. First employed by Sterling and Harper to reconstruct the theory of program modules and their phase separated parametricity, synthetic Tait computability is deployed here to resolve the last major open question in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory: normalization of open terms.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter></tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>4</crumb></trail> <title>Workshop presentations</title></frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>uemura-2022-hott-uf</addr>  <route>uemura-2022-hott-uf.xml</route> <date>July 2022</date> <authors><author>Taichi Uemura</author> </authors> <title>Internal languages of diagrams of ∞-toposes</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @misc{uemura:2022:hott-uf,
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  year = {2022},
  month = july,
  note = {Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations},
  title = {Internal languages of diagrams of $\infty$-toposes},
  url = {https://hott-uf.github.io/2022/uemura-hott-uf-2022-notes.pdf}
}
 </meta><meta name="venue">Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-hott-uf</addr>  <route>weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-hott-uf.xml</route> <date>July 2022</date> <authors><author>Jonathan Weinberger</author><author>Benedikt Ahrens</author><author>Ulrik Buchholtz</author><author>Paige North</author> </authors> <title>Towards Normalization of Simplicial Type Theory via Synthetic Tait Computability</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @misc{weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north:2022:hott-uf,
  author = {Weinberger, Jonathan and Ahrens, Benedikt and Buchholtz, Ulrik and North, Paige},
  year = {2022},
  month = july,
  note = {Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations},
  title = {Towards Normalization of Simplicial Type Theory via Synthetic Tait Computability},
  url = {https://hott-uf.github.io/2022/HoTTUF_2022_paper_6.pdf}
}
 </meta><meta name="video">https://www.dropbox.com/s/6dhiqiaemzmewm1/weinberger_HoTTUF22_SSTC.mp4?dl=0</meta><meta name="venue">Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-2022-muri</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-muri.xml</route> <date>June 30, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @misc{sterling-harper:2022:muri,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Harper, Robert},
  url = {https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling:2022:muri.pdf},
  year = {2022},
  month = jun,
  note = {Talk given at the 2022 MURI Team Meeting},
  title = {Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference},
}
 </meta><meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2022-muri.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">MURI Team Meeting 2022</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-types</addr>  <route>weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-types.xml</route> <date>June 2022</date> <authors><author>Jonathan Weinberger</author><author>Benedikt Ahrens</author><author>Ulrik Buchholtz</author><author>Paige North</author> </authors> <title>Synthetic Tait Computability for Simplicial Type Theory</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @inproceedings{weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north:2022:types,
  author = {Weinberger, Jonathan and Ahrens, Benedikt and Buchholtz, Ulrik and North, Paige},
  booktitle = {28th International Conference on Types for Proofs and Programs (TYPES 2022)},
  year = {2022},
  title = {Synthetic {Tait} Computability for Simplicial Type Theory},
  url = {https://types22.inria.fr/files/2022/06/TYPES_2022_paper_17.pdf}
}
 </meta><meta name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jX76Kv-E_ls</meta><meta name="venue">28th International Conference on Types for Proofs and Programs</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>uemura-2022-wg6</addr>  <route>uemura-2022-wg6.xml</route> <date>May 21, 2022</date> <authors><author>Taichi Uemura</author> </authors> <title>Normalization for initial space-valued models of type theories</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @misc{uemura:2022:wg6,
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  year = {2022},
  month = may,
  note = {WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories},
  title = {Normalization for initial space-valued models of type theories},
}
 </meta><meta name="venue">WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-2022-wg6</addr>  <route>sterling-2022-wg6.xml</route> <date>May 20, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @misc{sterling:2022:wg6,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  year = {2022},
  month = may,
  note = {WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories (Invited Talk)},
  title = {Na\&quot;{i}ve logical relations in synthetic {Tait} computability},
}
 </meta><meta name="venue">WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <em>positive</em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <em>non-syntactic</em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <em>Naïve Set Theory</em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <em>synthetic Tait computability</em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-2021-muri</addr>  <route>sterling-2021-muri.xml</route> <date>October 15, 2021</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Normalization for (Cartesian) Cubical Type Theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2021-muri.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">MURI Team Meeting 2021</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-harper-2021-mlw</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2021-mlw.xml</route> <date>2021</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author>Robert Harper</author> </authors> <title>A metalanguage for multi-phase modularity</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @unpublished{sterling-harper:2021:mlw,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Harper, Robert},
  url = {https://icfp21.sigplan.org/details/mlfamilyworkshop-2021-papers/5/A-metalanguage-for-multi-phase-modularity},
  year = {2021},
  month = aug,
  note = {ML 2021 abstract and talk},
  title = {A metalanguage for multi-phase modularity},
}
 </meta><meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-harper-2021-mlw.pdf</meta><meta name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5kWS-umBA7k</meta><meta name="venue"/></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Type abstraction, the phase distinction, and computational effects all play an important role in the design and implementation of ML-style module systems. We propose a simple type theoretic metalanguage <strong>φML</strong> for multi-phase modularity in which these concepts are treated individually, supporting the definition of high-level modular constructs such as generative and applicative functors, as well as all extant forms of structure sharing.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="collapsed" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>sterling-angiuli-2021-ct</addr>  <route>sterling-angiuli-2021-ct.xml</route> <date>2021</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="carloangiuli.xml" type="local">Carlo Angiuli</link></author> </authors> <title>Normalization for cubical type theory</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-angiuli-2021-ct.pdf</meta><meta name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AhivFjnBakE</meta><meta name="venue"/></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree></mainmatter></tree></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks/> <references/></backmatter></tree>