<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16637</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000V</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000V.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Detailed overview of First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability">Detailed overview of <fr:em>First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:em></fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We give a chapter-by-chapter overview of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory"><fr:em>First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:em></fr:link>. The novel contributions are contained in Chapters 4, 5, 7, and 8; the remaining Chapters 0-3 and 6 are primarily expository.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16457</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000W</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000W.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part I: dependent dype theory">Part I: dependent dype theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16459</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000X</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000X.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 0: conspectus on type theory">Chapter 0: conspectus on type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This chapter situates the motivations and applications of type theory in mathematics and computer science, and poses these against the semantic and syntactic properties of type theory that are needed to substantiate these applications. On the semantic side, type theory needs a number of properties including function extensionality, function comprehension, propositional univalence, effective quotients, etc.; on the syntactic side, type theory needs to be at least consistent, and many applications require both canonicity and decidability. Combining these syntactic and semantic properties into a single system has been a challenge, and cubical type theory was designed with the intention of satisfying them all. Prior to this dissertation, only the decidability conjecture remained open; thus with the present contribution, we regard the <fr:em>Cubical Hypothesis</fr:em> confirmed.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16461</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000Y</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000Y.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 1: objective syntax of dependent types">Chapter 1: objective syntax of dependent types</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>To state and prove theorems like <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000S.xml"
addr="jms-000S"
title="Cubical canonicity">canonicity</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000T.xml"
addr="jms-000T"
title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability</fr:link> for a type theory, we must have a mathematical definition of the <fr:em>syntax</fr:em> of type theory. Conventionally, the syntax of type theory has been studied in several layers: one starts with a definition of “raw” syntax as trees labeled by the names of the generating operations, quotients these trees under permutation of bound variables, and then layers on top of this an additional inductively defined formalism expressing the well-formedness of types, well-formedness of terms, definitional equality of types, and definitional equality of terms. After this, one verifies that definitional equivalence classes of well-formed types and terms can be used as the raw materials to construct a universal model of the type theory that has a universal property: any other model of type theory can be equipped with a unique structure-preserving homomorphism from the universal model. The described universal property determines the universal model up to unique isomorphism, if such a model exists.</fr:p><fr:p>We refer to the painstaking process described above as the subjective metatheory, building on the <fr:link
type="local"
href="hegel-sol.xml"
addr="hegel-sol"
title="Wissenschaft der Logik">Hegel</fr:link>–<fr:link
type="local"
href="lawvere-1994.xml"
addr="lawvere-1994"
title="Tools for the advancement of objective logic: closed categories and toposes">Lawvere</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="lawvere-schanuel-2009.xml"
addr="lawvere-schanuel-2009"
title="Conceptual mathematics: a first introduction to categories">distinction</fr:link> between objective and subjective approaches to logic. The objective metatheory, in contrast, involves stating and proving results about type theories and programming languages relying only on the universal property of the universal model and not on any specifics of its presentation; the advantage of the objective metatheory is that it is simpler, more direct, more modular, and more composable.</fr:p><fr:p>Chapter 1 argues that the subjective metatheory in the sense described is redundant: the decidability conjecture can be stated with respect to any representative of the universal model and does not depend in any way on the raw syntax of type theory, and moreover, for all the type theories considered in this dissertation the existence of at least one representative of the universal model is guaranteed for somewhat trivial reasons that have nothing to do with the specifics of type theory. In this chapter, we develop a logical framework for specifying type theories modularly and working with their universal models in an objective fashion.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16463</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000Z</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000Z.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part II: mathematical Background">Part II: mathematical Background</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16465</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0010</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0010.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 2: the language of topoi">Chapter 2: the language of topoi</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Much of this dissertation is stated and proved by exploiting the language of (Grothendieck) topoi, a concept that leads a dual life as a kind of generalized logic <fr:em>and</fr:em> as a kind of generalized topology. The viewpoint of topos theory <fr:em>qua</fr:em> generalized topology plays an important role in this dissertation, and yet it nonetheless remains unfamiliar to most computer scientists and logicians. For this reason, Chapter 2 is provided as sufficient exposition to understand the use of topoi in the remainder of the dissertation, focusing on the <fr:em>recollement</fr:em> or <fr:em>gluing</fr:em> of a topos from a pair of complementary open and closed subtopoi, a classical construction that provides the geometrical basis for synthetic Tait computability.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16467</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0011</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0011.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 3: the theory of universes">Chapter 3: the theory of universes</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Universes started their life in the <fr:link
type="local"
href="sga-4.xml"
addr="sga-4"
title="Théorie des topos et cohomologie étale des schémas (SGA 4)">Grothendieck school of algebraic geometry</fr:link> as a technical device to circumvent the annoyance that there cannot be a “set of all sets”; a universe is a set of enough sets, and whilst a universe cannot contain itself, it may nonetheless lie within an even bigger universe. Several important developments in the theory of universes from the 1970s onward by <fr:link
type="local"
href="jeanb%C3%A9nabou.xml"
addr="jeanbénabou"
title="Jean Bénabou">Bénabou</fr:link>, <fr:link
type="local"
href="permartinl%C3%B6f.xml"
addr="permartinlöf"
title="Per Martin-Löf">Martin-Löf</fr:link>, Dybjer, <fr:link
type="local"
href="martinhofmann.xml"
addr="martinhofmann"
title="Martin Hofmann">Hofmann</fr:link>, <fr:link
type="local"
href="thomasstreicher.xml"
addr="thomasstreicher"
title="Thomas Streicher">Streicher</fr:link>, <fr:link
type="local"
href="steveawodey.xml"
addr="steveawodey"
title="Steve Awodey">Awodey</fr:link>, and others have collided to deliver the present-day understanding of the centrality of universes in semantics: a model of type theory is just a special kind of universe in a special kind of category. This chapter provides expository background on the theory of universes, including a novel account of open and closed subuniverses to reflect the recollement theory of topoi from <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0010.xml"
addr="jms-0010"
title="Chapter 2: the language of topoi">Chapter 2</fr:link>. These open and closed subuniverses will play a critical role in the development of synthetic Tait computability in subsequent chapters.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16469</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0012</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0012.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part III: synthetic Tait computability">Part III: synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16471</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0013</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0013.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 4: Tait's method of computability">Chapter 4: Tait's method of computability</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>It is simple enough to verify <fr:strong>negative</fr:strong> properties of a formal system, e.g. the non-derivability of a given assertion <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Phi ]]></fr:tex>: find a mathematical object that models all the rules of the formal system and yet refutes <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Phi ]]></fr:tex>. In contrast, it is much harder to verify any non-trivial <fr:strong>positive</fr:strong> property of a formal system (such as canonicity, normalization, decidability, etc.). To handle such results, new techniques were needed — and delivered in the late 1960s by Tait, Martin-Löf and others under the name of Tait’s method of computability or logical predicates. Since its inception, Tait’s method has been the primary tool for verifying positive properties of logics, programming languages, and type theories. Early on, <fr:link
type="local"
href="freyd-1978.xml"
addr="freyd-1978"
title="On proving that 1 is an indecomposable projective in various free categories">Freyd</fr:link> noticed that the logical predicates arguments can be rephrased as model constructions that glue together geometrical objects corresponding to <fr:em>syntax</fr:em> (object) and <fr:em>set theory</fr:em> (meta), setting the stage for this thesis. Thus despite appearances, both positive and negative properties can both be proved using semantic methods.</fr:p><fr:p>In the subsequent development of the computability method for applications in computer science, <fr:em>indexed</fr:em> variants of the logical predicates have proved to be fundamental and a number of variations on indexed logical predicates have appeared including the Kripke logical predicates of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jung-tiuryn-1993.xml"
addr="jung-tiuryn-1993"
title="A new characterization of lambda definability">Jung and Tiuryn</fr:link> and the much more sophisticated <fr:em>Grothendieck</fr:em> logical predicates of <fr:link
type="local"
href="fiore-simpson-1999.xml"
addr="fiore-simpson-1999"
title="Lambda definability with sums via Grothendieck logical relations">Fiore and Simpson</fr:link> as well as <fr:link
type="local"
href="altenkirch-dybjer-hofmann-scott-2001.xml"
addr="altenkirch-dybjer-hofmann-scott-2001"
title="Normalization by evaluation for typed lambda calculus with coproducts">Altenkirch, Dybjer, Hofmann, and Scott</fr:link>. This chapter points out that all of these forms of indexing arise in the same way from what is referred to as a <fr:strong>figure shape</fr:strong>, a continuous map into the classifying space of “Henkin models” of a given theory. Then the (Kripke, Grothendieck, etc.) logical predicates model is presented much more simply as the Artin gluing of this morphism’s inverse image.</fr:p><fr:p>An explicit proof of canonicity for the simply typed <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\lambda ]]></fr:tex>-calculus motivates the abstraction and axiomatization of the geometry of figure shapes and their gluings as a new language for syntactic metatheory, namely <fr:strong>synthetic Tait computability</fr:strong>. The idea of synthetic Tait computability is to treat both object-level notions (e.g. the collection of terms of type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathsf {bool}]]></fr:tex>) and meta-level notions (e.g. a normal form of a given term) in the same language by means of a pair of lex idempotent modalities. One strength of this presentation is that both object-level and meta-level notions can be treated using higher-order abstract syntax (HOAS) in the sense of <fr:link
type="local"
href="hofmann-1999.xml"
addr="hofmann-1999"
title="Semantical analysis of higher-order abstract syntax">Hofmann</fr:link>, which greatly simplifies the manipulation of variables.</fr:p><fr:p>The first demonstration of the power and modularity of synthetic Tait
  computability is a new a proof of the canonicity property for Martin-Löf type theory. Unlike traditional proofs of canonicity via non-synthetic Tait computability, the synthetic version is completely modular and broken up into general-purpose lemmas that are stated at a high level of abstraction and can be reused in proofs of <fr:em>different properties</fr:em> for <fr:em>different type theories</fr:em>. (Indeed, some of the constructions isolated in this chapter are used off the shelf in <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0014.xml"
addr="jms-0014"
title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">Chapter 7</fr:link> to prove normalization for cubical type theory.) The modularization of syntactic metatheory is one of the main contributions of this dissertation.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16473</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0015</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0015.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 5: synthetic normalization by evaluation">Chapter 5: synthetic normalization by evaluation</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This chapter develops a more sophisticated application of synthetic Tait computability, the proof of normalization and decidability of Martin-Löf’s type theory with a cumulative hierarchy of universes. The synthetic argument contained in this chapter builds on the work of <fr:link
type="local"
href="fiore-2002.xml"
addr="fiore-2002"
title="Semantic analysis of normalisation by evaluation for typed lambda calculus">Fiore</fr:link> on categorical normalization by gluing for simply typed λ-calculus, and that of <fr:link
type="local"
href="coquand-2019.xml"
addr="coquand-2019"
title="Canonicity and normalization for dependent type theory">Coquand</fr:link> on a presheaf-theoretic version of normalization by evaluation for dependent types. Analogous to the external argument of <fr:link
type="local"
href="fiore-2002.xml"
addr="fiore-2002"
title="Semantic analysis of normalisation by evaluation for typed lambda calculus">Fiore</fr:link>, we construe the syntax of normal and neutral forms as the initial algebra for an internal inductive definition in the language of synthetic Tait computability. The influence of <fr:link
type="local"
href="coquand-2019.xml"
addr="coquand-2019"
title="Canonicity and normalization for dependent type theory">Coquand</fr:link> is visible in the definition of the <fr:em>Tait saturation yoga</fr:em> for dependent types in the synthetic setting, an important closure condition for logical predicates that comprised one of the main innovations of <fr:link
type="local"
href="tait-1967.xml"
addr="tait-1967"
title="Intensional interpretations of functionals of finite type I">Tait</fr:link> in the context of simply typed combinators. Although this chapter is intended only as “dry run” for the main result (to be exposed in <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0014.xml"
addr="jms-0014"
title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">Chapter 7</fr:link>), the normalization argument presented here has intrinsic value: it is the simplest and most direct proof of normalization and decidability for Martin-Löf type theory with <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\eta ]]></fr:tex>-laws and cumulative universes that has appeared in the literature so far.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16475</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0016</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0016.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part IV: cubical type theory">Part IV: cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16477</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0017</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0017.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 6: cartesian cubical type theory">Chapter 6: cartesian cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This expository chapter introduces cubical type theory as an extension to Martin-Löf’s type theory by an interval <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> with two distinct endpoints <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[0, 1 : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex>. The interval is a basic “figure” that defines a notion of <fr:em>path</fr:em> or <fr:em>identification</fr:em> <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{u}\mathrel {{\sim }_{A}}{v}]]></fr:tex> between two elements of any type; for instance, to identify <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[u,v:A]]></fr:tex> is the same as to construct a function <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p:\mathbb {I}\to  A]]></fr:tex> such that <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p0 = u]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p1=v]]></fr:tex>. Terms involving <fr:em>variables</fr:em> of type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> can exhibit complex computational behavior that is difficult to account for: for instance, if <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p:{u}\mathrel {{\sim }_{A}}{v}]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[i:\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> are variables, then the application <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[pi:A]]></fr:tex> is a normal form, but it must nonetheless reduce to either <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[u]]></fr:tex> or <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[v]]></fr:tex> when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[i]]></fr:tex> is substituted for by a constant. Despite appearances, this scenario is fundamentally different from the way that <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[pi]]></fr:tex> must reduce when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p]]></fr:tex> is replaced
by a <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\lambda ]]></fr:tex>-abstraction, as normal forms must <fr:em>a priori</fr:em> be closed under arbitrary <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex>-substitutions — a necessity, because the normal form of an <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n]]></fr:tex>-cube must be an <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n]]></fr:tex>-cube of normal forms. One of the main technical contributions of this dissertation, introduced in the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0014.xml"
addr="jms-0014"
title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">next chapter</fr:link>, is to generalization of the notion of neutral form and the Tait saturation yoga that smoothly accommodates the problematic computational behavior of the interval.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16479</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0014</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0014.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This chapter reports the main result of the dissertation, normalization for cubical type theory and its corollaries: injectivity of type constructors, and <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000T.xml"
addr="jms-000T"
title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability of equality &amp; typing</fr:link>. These results were first obtained by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-angiuli-2021"
title="Normalization for cubical type theory">Sterling and Angiuli</fr:link> for the fragment of cubical type theory <fr:em>without</fr:em> universes; the present chapter extends the results of <fr:em>op. cit.</fr:em> to support a cumulative hierarchy of universes.</fr:p><fr:p>The central innovation of this chapter is to generalize the notion of neutral form to accommodate the computational behavior of terms that have free variables of type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> discussed in our <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0017.xml"
addr="jms-0017"
title="Chapter 6: cartesian cubical type theory">synopsis of Chapter 6</fr:link>.  In the conventional account of neutral and normal forms, neutrals <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> are built up inductively from
<fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x]]></fr:tex> for term variables <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x : A]]></fr:tex>, function applications to normal forms <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{\bullet }}}{{\color {DarkBlue}{m}}}]]></fr:tex>
and projections from neutral pairs <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}{\color {DarkRed}{.1}}]]></fr:tex>, <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}{\color {DarkRed}{.2}}]]></fr:tex>; our account of neutrals is much the same, except that each neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> comes equipped with a <fr:strong>“frontier
  of instability”</fr:strong> <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}]]></fr:tex>, a predicate on its free <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex>-variables that indicates when it “needs to compute further”. We think of a neutral form for an <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n]]></fr:tex>-cube as being <fr:em>undefined</fr:em> on its frontier of instability; the process of restricting a neutral to its frontier of instability is then referred to as <fr:em>destabilization</fr:em>.</fr:p><fr:p>When <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x : A]]></fr:tex> is a variable of an ordinary type, the frontier of instability <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }\,{\mathopen {}\left ({\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,{x}\right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex> is empty because variables never need to compute further. Where something new happens is the path type: given a neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}} : \mathsf {ne}\,{\mathopen {}\left ({u}\mathrel {{\sim }_{A}}{v}\right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex>
of path type, we have for each term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[r : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> a neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r} : \mathsf {ne}\,A]]></fr:tex> whose frontier of instability is defined like so:</fr:p><fr:tex
display="block"><![CDATA[  \boldsymbol {\partial }\,{\mathopen {}\left ({{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}\right )\mathclose {}} = \boldsymbol {\partial }{\color {DarkRed}{e}} \lor  {\mathopen {}\left (r=0\right )\mathclose {}} \lor  {\mathopen {}\left (r=1\right )\mathclose {}} ]]></fr:tex><fr:p>In other words, the path neutral application <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}]]></fr:tex> needs to compute as soon as e needs to compute, and as soon as the interval term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[r : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> becomes equal to a constant. Prior to the introduction of the frontier of instability, the neutrals are embedded into the normals at base types unconditionally, i.e. for each neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}} : \mathsf {ne}\,\mathsf {bool}]]></fr:tex>, we have a normal form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkBlue}{\lfloor }}{e}{\color {DarkBlue}{\rfloor }} : \mathsf {nf}\,\mathsf {bool}]]></fr:tex>.</fr:p><fr:p>Now that neutrals are equipped with frontiers of instability, a more refined notion of normal form is needed: when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> is a neutral form, the corresponding normal form should contain (recursively) normal forms for <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[e]]></fr:tex> that are defined under the frontier of instability <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }\,{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex>. To be more concrete,
let <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x : {\mathsf {tt}}\mathrel {{\sim }_{\mathsf {bool}}}{\mathsf {tt}}]]></fr:tex> be a variable of path type and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[r : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> is a term; then <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,x}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}:\mathsf {ne}\,{\mathopen {}\left ({\mathsf {tt}}\mathrel {{\sim }_{\mathsf {bool}}}{\mathsf {tt}}\right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex> is a neutral form for the term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[xr]]></fr:tex> whose frontier of instability is the boundary <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[(r = 0) \lor  (r = 1)]]></fr:tex>; the corresponding normal form must therefore glue onto <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,x}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}]]></fr:tex> additional normal forms for <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x0]]></fr:tex> and
<fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x1]]></fr:tex>. We refer to the process of completing a neutral with additional data defined on its frontier of instability as stabilization; the <fr:em>stabilized</fr:em> normal form of <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[xr]]></fr:tex> is then written</fr:p><fr:tex
display="block"><![CDATA[ {\color {DarkBlue}{\lfloor }}{{{\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,x}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r} \mid  r = 0 \hookrightarrow  {\color {DarkBlue}{\mathsf {tt}}}, r = 1 \hookrightarrow {\color {DarkBlue}{\mathsf {tt}}}}{\color {DarkBlue}{\rfloor }} ]]></fr:tex><fr:p>where <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkBlue}{\mathsf {tt}}}]]></fr:tex> is the normal form representing the term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathsf {tt}]]></fr:tex></fr:p><fr:p>Just as the embedding of neutrals into normals is “stabilized” by a com patible normal form defined on the neutral’s frontier of instability, so too must the Tait saturation yoga be adjusted. Conventionally one requires the computability predicate for a type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A]]></fr:tex> to be equipped with a function that takes neutral forms <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> of terms <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[e : A]]></fr:tex> to computability witnesses for the same term. In the <fr:strong>stabilized Tait saturation yoga</fr:strong>, we strengthen the induction hypothesis to require for each neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> a function that extends a computability witness defined only on the frontier of instability <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> to a computability witnessed defined everywhere</fr:p><fr:p>The twin innovations of <fr:em>frontiers of instability</fr:em> and <fr:em>stabilization</fr:em> then suffice to adapt the synthetic normalization argument of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0015.xml"
addr="jms-0015"
title="Chapter 5: synthetic normalization by evaluation">Chapter 5</fr:link> to a proof of normalization (and thus decidability) for cubical type theory.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16481</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0018</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0018.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part V: prospects">Part V: prospects</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16483</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0019</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0019.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 8: a plan for PL">Chapter 8: a plan for PL</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This dissertation has focused almost solely on the development and applications of synthetic Tait computability in the context of pure type theory, but the author originally invented synthetic Tait computability to solve problems in core programming languages, as part of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>’s re-analysis of the <fr:em>phase distinction</fr:em> in <fr:link
type="local"
href="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990.xml"
addr="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990"
title="Higher-order modules and the phase distinction">ML-style</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="moggi-1989.xml"
addr="moggi-1989"
title="A category-theoretic account of program modules">module systems</fr:link> between static (compiletime) and dynamic (runtime) code. The purpose of this chapter is to identify several applications of synthetic Tait computability to core programming languages, and set an agenda for future work — some of which has been executed and published following the completion of this dissertation</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16381</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-001A</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001A.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules">§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A brief overview is given of the applications of synthetic Tait computability to program modules, material that is published in the <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Journal of the ACM</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16383</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-001B</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001B.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction">§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <fr:em>refinement types</fr:em> and <fr:em>program extraction</fr:em> via a phase distinction between <fr:em>computation</fr:em> and <fr:em>specification</fr:em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\phi }\sqsubset {A}]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\psi }\sqsubset {B}]]></fr:tex> are refinements of types <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[B]]></fr:tex> respectively, then <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\phi \to \psi ]]></fr:tex> refines <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A\to  B]]></fr:tex>. In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</fr:link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16385</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-001C</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001C.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="§ 8.3: information-flow and noninterference">§ 8.3: information-flow and noninterference</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>20</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Finally, an application of synthetic Tait computability to <fr:em>security</fr:em> and <fr:em>information flow control</fr:em> is identified: a security class is a phase distinction between low and high security. The preliminary results presented in this section have been substantially improved upon by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2022"
title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>, adding support for general recursion and termination-insensitive noninterference by combining synthetic Tait computability with <fr:link
type="local"
href="hyland-1991.xml"
addr="hyland-1991"
title="First steps in synthetic domain theory">synthetic domain theory</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="References">References</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16639</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A cost-aware logical framework">A cost-aware logical framework</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="pacmpl.xml"
addr="pacmpl"
title="Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages">Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages</fr:link>, Volume 6, Issue POPL</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3498670</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We present calf, a cost-aware logical framework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs. Taking inspiration from recent work that reconstructs traditional aspects of programming languages in terms of a modal account of phase distinctions, we argue that the cost structure of programs motivates a phase distinction between intension and extension. Armed with this technology, we contribute a synthetic account of cost structure as a computational effect in which cost-aware programs enjoy an internal noninterference property: input/output behavior cannot depend on cost. As a full-spectrum dependent type theory, calf presents a unified language for programming and specification of both cost and behavior that can be integrated smoothly with existing mathematical libraries available in type theoretic proof assistants.</fr:p><fr:p>We evaluate calf as a general framework for cost analysis by implementing two fundamental techniques for algorithm analysis: the method of recurrence relations and physicist’s method for amortized analysis. We deploy these techniques on a variety of case studies: we prove a tight, closed bound for Euclid’s algorithm, verify the amortized complexity of batched queues, and derive tight, closed bounds for the sequential and parallel complexity of merge sort, all fully mechanized in the Agda proof assistant. Lastly we substantiate the soundness of quantitative reasoning in calf by means of a model construction.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16644</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-harper-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-harper-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.5</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-harper-2022.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">7th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2022)</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We propose a new sheaf semantics for secure information flow over a space of abstract behaviors, based on synthetic domain theory: security classes are open/closed partitions, types are sheaves, and redaction of sensitive information corresponds to restricting a sheaf to a closed subspace. Our security-aware computational model satisfies termination-insensitive noninterference automatically, and therefore constitutes an intrinsic alternative to state of the art extrinsic/relational models of noninterference. Our semantics is the latest application of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>’s recent re-interpretation of phase distinctions and noninterference in programming languages in terms of Artin gluing and topos-theoretic open/closed modalities. Prior applications include <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">parametricity for ML modules</fr:link>, the proof of normalization for cubical type theory by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-angiuli-2021"
title="Normalization for cubical type theory">Sterling and Angiuli</fr:link>, and the cost-aware logical framework of <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework">Niu et al</fr:link>. In this paper we employ the phase distinction perspective twice: first to reconstruct the syntax and semantics of secure information flow as a lattice of phase distinctions between “higher” and “lower” security, and second to verify the computational adequacy of our sheaf semantics with respect to a version of Abadi et al.’s dependency core calculus to which we have added a construct for declassifying termination channels.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>1476</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-005Y</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-005Y.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Minor mistakes in sheaf semantics of noninterference">Minor mistakes in <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2022"
title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">sheaf semantics of noninterference</fr:link></fr:title><fr:taxon>Erratum</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>In the published version of this paper, there were a few mistakes that have been corrected in the local copy hosted here.</fr:p><fr:ol><fr:li>In the <fr:em>Critique of relational semantics for information flow</fr:em>, our discussion of the <fr:em>Failure of monotonicity</fr:em> stated incorrectly that algebras for the sealing monad at a higher security level could not be transformed into algebras for the sealing monad at a lower security level in the semantics of Abadi et al. This is not true, as pointed out to us privately by Carlos Tomé Cortiñas. What we meant to say was that it is not the case that a type whose component at a high security level is trivial shall always remain trivial at a lower security level.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>The original version of the extended edition of this paper, we claimed that the constructive existence of tensor products on pointed dcpos was obvious; in fact, tensor products do exist, but their construction involves a reflexive coequalizer of pointed dcpos.</fr:li></fr:ol></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>1478</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-005Z</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-005Z.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Adequacy of sheaf semantics of noninterference">Adequacy of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2022"
title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">sheaf semantics of noninterference</fr:link></fr:title><fr:taxon>Erratum</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>7</fr:month><fr:day>17</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A serious (and as-yet unfixed) problem was discovered in July of 2023 by <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link>, which undermines the proof of adequacy given; in particular, the proof that the logical relation on free algebras is admissible is not correct. I believe there is a different proof of adequacy for the calculus described, but it will have a different structure from what currently appears in the paper. We thank <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link> for his attention to detail and careful reading of this paper.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16647</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-harper-2021</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-harper-2021.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>12</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-harper-2021.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="jacm.xml"
addr="jacm"
title="Journal of the ACM">Journal of the ACM</fr:link>, Volume 68, Issue 6</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3474834</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The theory of program modules is of interest to language designers not only for its practical importance to programming, but also because it lies at the nexus of three fundamental concerns in language design: the <fr:em>phase distinction</fr:em>, <fr:em>computational effects</fr:em>, and <fr:em>type abstraction</fr:em>. We contribute a fresh “synthetic” take on program modules that treats modules as the fundamental constructs, in which the usual suspects of prior module calculi (kinds, constructors, dynamic programs) are rendered as derived notions in terms of a modal type-theoretic account of the phase distinction. We simplify the account of type abstraction (embodied in the generativity of module functors) through a <fr:em>lax modality</fr:em> that encapsulates computational effects, placing <fr:em>projectibility</fr:em> of module expressions on a type-theoretic basis.</fr:p><fr:p>Our main result is a (significant) proof-relevant and phase-sensitive generalization of the Reynolds abstraction theorem for a calculus of program modules, based on a new kind of logical relation called a <fr:em>parametricity structure</fr:em>. Parametricity structures generalize the proof-irrelevant relations of classical parametricity to proof-<fr:em>relevant</fr:em> families, where there may be non-trivial evidence witnessing the relatedness of two programs—simplifying the metatheory of strong sums over the collection of types, for although there can be no “relation classifying relations,” one easily accommodates a “family classifying small families.”</fr:p><fr:p>Using the insight that logical relations/parametricity is itself a form of phase distinction between the syntactic and the semantic, we contribute a new synthetic approach to phase separated parametricity based on the slogan <fr:em>logical relations as types</fr:em>, by iterating our modal account of the phase distinction. We axiomatize a dependent type theory of parametricity structures using two pairs of complementary modalities (syntactic, semantic) and (static, dynamic), substantiated using the topos theoretic <fr:em>Artin gluing</fr:em> construction. Then, to construct a simulation between two implementations of an abstract type, one simply programs a third implementation whose type component carries the representation invariant.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>1483</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0060</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0060.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Minor mistakes in logical relations as types">Minor mistakes in <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">logical relations as types</fr:link></fr:title><fr:taxon>Erratum</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>After going to press, we have fixed the following mistakes:</fr:p><fr:ol><fr:li>In the definition of a logos, we mistakenly said that "colimits commute with finite limits" but we meant to say that they are preserved by pullback. We thank <fr:link
type="local"
href="sarahzrf.xml"
addr="sarahzrf"
title="Sarah Z. Rovner-Frydman">Sarah Z. Rovner-Frydman</fr:link> for noticing this mistake.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>In Remark 5.15, we used the notation for the closed immersion prior to introducing it.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>We have fixed a few broken links in the bibliography.</fr:li></fr:ol><fr:p>The local copy hosted here has the corrections implemented</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16650</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-thesis</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-thesis.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>9</fr:month><fr:day>13</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Doctoral dissertation, <fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-2021-thesis.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@phdthesis{sterling-2021-thesis,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  school = {Carnegie Mellon University},
  year = {2021},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.6990769},
  note = {Version 1.1, revised May 2022},
  number = {CMU-CS-21-142},
  title = {First Steps in Synthetic {Tait} Computability: The Objective Metatheory of Cubical Type Theory},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.5281/zenodo.6990769</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The implementation and semantics of dependent type theories can be studied in a syntax-independent way: the objective metatheory of dependent type theories exploits the universal properties of their syntactic categories to endow them with computational content, mathematical meaning, and practical implementation (normalization, type checking, elaboration). The semantic methods of the objective metatheory inform the design and implementation of correct-by-construction elaboration algorithms, promising a principled interface between real proof assistants and ideal mathematics.</fr:p><fr:p>In this dissertation, I add synthetic Tait computability to the arsenal of the objective metatheorist. Synthetic Tait computability is a mathematical machine to reduce difficult problems of type theory and programming languages to trivial theorems of topos theory. First employed by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</fr:link> to reconstruct the theory of program modules and their phase separated parametricity, synthetic Tait computability is deployed here to resolve the last major open question in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory: normalization of open terms.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16652</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-angiuli-2021</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-angiuli-2021.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for cubical type theory">Normalization for cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>7</fr:month><fr:day>7</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="carloangiuli.xml"
addr="carloangiuli"
title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">2021 36th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science (LICS)</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1109/LICS52264.2021.9470719</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.11479</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We prove normalization for (univalent, Cartesian) cubical type theory, closing the last major open problem in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory. Our normalization result is reduction-free, in the sense of yielding a bijection between equivalence classes of terms in context and a tractable language of <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\beta ]]></fr:tex>/<fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\eta ]]></fr:tex>-normal forms. As corollaries we obtain both decidability of judgmental equality and the injectivity of type constructors.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16655</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">coquand-2019</fr:addr><fr:route>coquand-2019.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Canonicity and normalization for dependent type theory">Canonicity and normalization for dependent type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2019</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="thierrycoquand.xml"
addr="thierrycoquand"
title="Thierry Coquand">Thierry Coquand</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1016/j.tcs.2019.01.015</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Theoretical Computer Science</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16657</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">lawvere-schanuel-2009</fr:addr><fr:route>lawvere-schanuel-2009.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Conceptual mathematics: a first introduction to categories">Conceptual mathematics: a first introduction to categories</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2009</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>31</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>F. William Lawvere</fr:author><fr:author>Stephen H. Schanuel</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.5555/1594905</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>In the last 60 years, the use of the notion of category has led to a remarkable unification and simplification of mathematics. Conceptual Mathematics, Second Edition, introduces the concept of ‘category’ for the learning, development, and use of mathematics, to both beginning students and general readers, and to practicing mathematical scientists. The treatment does not presuppose knowledge of specific fields, but rather develops, from basic definitions, such elementary categories as discrete dynamical systems and directed graphs; the fundamental ideas are then illuminated by examples in these categories.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16660</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">fiore-2002</fr:addr><fr:route>fiore-2002.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Semantic analysis of normalisation by evaluation for typed lambda calculus">Semantic analysis of normalisation by evaluation for typed lambda calculus</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2002</fr:year><fr:month>10</fr:month><fr:day>6</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="marcelofiore.xml"
addr="marcelofiore"
title="Marcelo Fiore">Marcelo Fiore</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/571157.571161</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This paper studies normalisation by evaluation for typed lambda calculus from a categorical and algebraic viewpoint. The first part of the paper analyses the lambda definability result of Jung and Tiuryn via Kripke logical relations and shows how it can be adapted to unify definability and normalisation, yielding an extensional normalisation result. In the second part of the paper the analysis is refined further by considering intensional Kripke relations (in the form of glueing) and shown to provide a function for normalising terms, casting normalisation by evaluation in the context of categorical glueing. The technical development includes an algebraic treatment of the syntax and semantics of the typed lambda calculus that allows the definition of the normalisation function to be given within a simply typed meta-theory.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16662</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">altenkirch-dybjer-hofmann-scott-2001</fr:addr><fr:route>altenkirch-dybjer-hofmann-scott-2001.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization by evaluation for typed lambda calculus with coproducts">Normalization by evaluation for typed lambda calculus with coproducts</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2001</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>Thorsten Altenkirch</fr:author><fr:author>Peter Dybjer</fr:author><fr:author>Martin Hofmann</fr:author><fr:author>Philip Scott</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1109/LICS.2001.932506</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Solves the decision problem for the simply typed lambda calculus with a strong binary sum, or, equivalently, the word problem for free Cartesian closed categories with binary co-products. Our method is based on the semantic technique known as “normalization by evaluation”, and involves inverting the interpretation of the syntax in a suitable sheaf model and, from this, extracting an appropriate unique normal form. There is no rewriting theory involved and the proof is completely constructive, allowing program extraction from the proof.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16667</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">fiore-simpson-1999</fr:addr><fr:route>fiore-simpson-1999.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Lambda definability with sums via Grothendieck logical relations">Lambda definability with sums via Grothendieck logical relations</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1999</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="marcelofiore.xml"
addr="marcelofiore"
title="Marcelo Fiore">Marcelo Fiore</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="alexsimpson.xml"
addr="alexsimpson"
title="Alex Simpson">Alex Simpson</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1007/3-540-48959-2_12</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We introduce a notion of <fr:em>Grothendieck logical relation</fr:em> and use it to characterise the definability of morphisms in stable bicartesian closed categories by terms of the simply-typed lambda calculus with finite products and finite sums. Our techniques are based on concepts from topos theory, however our exposition is elementary.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16670</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">hofmann-1999</fr:addr><fr:route>hofmann-1999.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Semantical analysis of higher-order abstract syntax">Semantical analysis of higher-order abstract syntax</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1999</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>Martin Hofmann</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1109/LICS.1999.782616</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A functor category semantics for higher-order abstract syntax is proposed with the following aims: relating higher-order and first order syntax, justifying induction principles, suggesting new logical principles to reason about higher-order syntax</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16672</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">lawvere-1994</fr:addr><fr:route>lawvere-1994.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Tools for the advancement of objective logic: closed categories and toposes">Tools for the advancement of objective logic: closed categories and toposes</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1994</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>F. William Lawvere</fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16674</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jung-tiuryn-1993</fr:addr><fr:route>jung-tiuryn-1993.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A new characterization of lambda definability">A new characterization of lambda definability</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1993</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>Achim Jung</fr:author><fr:author>Jerzy Tiuryn</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1007/BFb0037110</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We give a new characterization of lambda definability in Henkin models using logical relations defined over ordered sets with varying arity. The advantage of this over earlier approaches by Plotkin and Statman is its simplicity and universality. Yet, decidability of lambda definability for hereditarily finite Henkin models remains an open problem. But if the variable set allowed in terms is also restricted to be finite then our techniques lead to a decision procedure.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16677</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">hyland-1991</fr:addr><fr:route>hyland-1991.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="First steps in synthetic domain theory">First steps in synthetic domain theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1991</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="martinhyland.xml"
addr="martinhyland"
title="Martin Hyland">Martin Hyland</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Category Theory (Como, 1990)</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1007/BFb0084217</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@inproceedings{hyland-1991,
  author = {Hyland, J. M. E.},
  editor = {Carboni, Aurelio and Pedicchio, Maria Cristina and Rosolini, Guiseppe},
  address = {Berlin, Heidelberg},
  publisher = {Springer Berlin Heidelberg},
  booktitle = {Category Theory},
  year = {1991},
  isbn = {978-3-540-46435-8},
  pages = {131--156},
  title = {First steps in synthetic domain theory},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16679</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">harper-mitchell-moggi-1990</fr:addr><fr:route>harper-mitchell-moggi-1990.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Higher-order modules and the phase distinction">Higher-order modules and the phase distinction</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1989</fr:year><fr:month>12</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author>John C. Mitchell</fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="eugeniomoggi.xml"
addr="eugeniomoggi"
title="Eugenio Moggi">Eugenio Moggi</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/96709.96744</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>In earlier work, we used a typed function calculus, XML, with dependent types to analyze several aspects of the Standard ML type system. In this paper, we introduce a refinement of XML with a clear compile-time/run-time phase distinction, and a direct compile-time type checking algorithm. The calculus uses a finer separation of types into universes than XML and enforces the phase distinction using a nonstandard equational theory for module and signature expressions. While unusual from a type-theoretic point of view, the nonstandard equational theory arises naturally from the well-known Grothendieck construction on an indexed category.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16683</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">moggi-1989</fr:addr><fr:route>moggi-1989.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A category-theoretic account of program modules">A category-theoretic account of program modules</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1989</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="eugeniomoggi.xml"
addr="eugeniomoggi"
title="Eugenio Moggi">Eugenio Moggi</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1007/BFb0018347</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The type-theoretic explanation of modules proposed to date (for programming languages like ML) is unsatisfactory, in that it fails to reflect the distinction between compile-time, when type-expressions are evaluated, and run-time, when value-expressions are evaluated. This paper proposes a new explanation based on “programming languages as indexed categories” and illustrates, as an application, how ML should be extended to support higher order modules. The paper also outlines a methodology for a modular approach to programming languages, where programming languages (of a certain kind) are identified with objects in a 2-category and features are viewed as 2-categorical notions.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16685</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">freyd-1978</fr:addr><fr:route>freyd-1978.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="On proving that 1 is an indecomposable projective in various free categories">On proving that 1 is an indecomposable projective in various free categories</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1978</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>Peter Freyd</fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Unpublished manuscript.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16687</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sga-4</fr:addr><fr:route>sga-4.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Théorie des topos et cohomologie étale des schémas (SGA 4)">Théorie des topos et cohomologie étale des schémas (SGA 4)</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1972</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="alexandergrothendieck.xml"
addr="alexandergrothendieck"
title="Alexander Grothendieck">Alexander Grothendieck</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author>Jean-Louis Verdier</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1007/BFb0081551</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16690</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">tait-1967</fr:addr><fr:route>tait-1967.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Intensional interpretations of functionals of finite type I">Intensional interpretations of functionals of finite type I</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1967</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>William W. Tait</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.2307/2271658</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16692</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">hegel-sol</fr:addr><fr:route>hegel-sol.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Wissenschaft der Logik">Wissenschaft der Logik</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>1812</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="Context">Context</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16694</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000Q</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000Q.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Dissertation overview: first steps in synthetic Tait computability">Dissertation overview: <fr:em>first steps in synthetic Tait computability</fr:em></fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This is a chapter-by-chapter overview of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">dissertation of Jonathan Sterling</fr:link>.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16451</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000R</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000R.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Background on homotopy and cubical type theory">Background on homotopy and cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>For more than four decades, dependent type theory has been positioned as the “common language” that can finally <fr:link
type="local"
href="martin-loef-1982.xml"
addr="martin-loef-1982"
title="Constructive mathematics and computer programming">unify mathematics and computer programming</fr:link>: while it has never been controversial that a computer program is a form of mathematical construction, the running hypothesis of the type theoretic community has been the converse to this claim, namely that mathematical constructions should be viewed as programs that can in principle be executed by a physical machine — roughly, <fr:strong>sets</fr:strong> = <fr:strong>types</fr:strong> and <fr:strong>elements</fr:strong> = <fr:strong>programs</fr:strong>. Thus the struggle to realize this type theoretic hypothesis has been a two-way process, punctuated by moments at which the mathematical meaning of a programming construct is elucidated, or at which the computational content of a mathematical construct is uncovered.</fr:p><fr:p>In the current millennium, a new identification has been taking shape in which <fr:strong>types</fr:strong> = <fr:strong><html:span
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
style="white-space: nowrap"><fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\infty ]]></fr:tex>-groupoids</html:span></fr:strong> (homotopy types), which are an infinite-dimensional generalization of sets; the origins of this new perspective on type theory lie with <fr:link
type="local"
href="hofmann-streicher-1998.xml"
addr="hofmann-streicher-1998"
title="The groupoid interpretation of type theory">Hofmann and Streicher’s 1998 groupoid interpretation of type theory</fr:link>, combined with the revolutionary contributions of <fr:link
type="local"
href="voevodsky-2006.xml"
addr="voevodsky-2006"
title="A very short note on the homotopy λ-calculus">Voevodsky</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="awodey-warren-2009.xml"
addr="awodey-warren-2009"
title="Homotopy theoretic models of identity types">Awodey and Warren</fr:link> respectively. The main feature of the new language, dubbed <fr:link
type="local"
href="hottbook.xml"
addr="hottbook"
title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics"><fr:strong>homotopy type theory</fr:strong></fr:link> or <fr:strong>HoTT</fr:strong>, is that isomorphisms between types are equipped with a new induction rule called univalence stating that all type theoretic constructs respect isomorphisms: to a first approximation, if <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A \cong  B]]></fr:tex> then <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[P(A) \cong  P(B)]]></fr:tex> for any <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[P]]></fr:tex>. The univalence principle is motivated by the phenomenon of homotopy invariance that pervades the large-scale structure of modern-day mathematics, from algebraic topology to algebraic geometry to mathematical physics; as a programming construct, univalence suggests <fr:link
type="local"
href="acmz-2021.xml"
addr="acmz-2021"
title="Internalizing representation independence with univalence">new approaches</fr:link> to both generic and modular programming.</fr:p><fr:p>Thus one of the main projects for the first decade of homotopy type theory was to substantiate the relationship between HoTT and mathematics on the one hand, and between HoTT and computer programming on the other hand. The question of whether homotopy type theoretic language can be interpreted in sheaves on arbitrary infinite-dimensional spaces (<html:span
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
style="white-space: nowrap"><fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\infty ]]></fr:tex>-topoi</html:span>) has finally been resolved satisfactorily by <fr:link
type="local"
href="shulman-2019.xml"
addr="shulman-2019"
title="All (∞,1)-toposes have strict univalent universes">Shulman</fr:link> in 2019. On the other hand, the computational interpretation of homotopy type theory has involved a reformulation of HoTT called <fr:strong><fr:link
type="local"
href="abchfl-2021.xml"
addr="abchfl-2021"
title="Syntax and models of Cartesian cubical type theory">cubical</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="angiuli-favonia-harper-2018.xml"
addr="angiuli-favonia-harper-2018"
title="Cartesian cubical computational type theory: constructive reasoning with paths and equalities">type</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="cchm-2017.xml"
addr="cchm-2017"
title="Cubical type theory: a constructive interpretation of the univalence axiom">theory</fr:link></fr:strong> that reorganizes the higher-dimensional structure discussed by considering all the points, lines, squares, cubes, hypercubes, and so-on that one can draw in a given type. The computational interpretation of the new cubical type theory can be split into two different conjectures:</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16408</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000S</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000S.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Cubical canonicity">Cubical canonicity</fr:title><fr:taxon>Conjecture</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>For any closed term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\cdot \vdash  N:\mathsf {nat}]]></fr:tex> of cubical type theory, there exists a unique natural number <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n\in \mathbb {N}]]></fr:tex> such that <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\cdot \vdash  N\equiv  \bar {n}:\mathsf {nat}]]></fr:tex> where <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\bar {n}]]></fr:tex> is the encoding of the number <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n]]></fr:tex> as a term in the type theory.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16409</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000T</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000T.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Decidability of cubical type theory">Decidability of cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Conjecture</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The assertions <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Gamma \vdash  {A}\ \textit {type}]]></fr:tex>, <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Gamma \vdash {A\equiv  B}\ \textit {type}]]></fr:tex>, <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Gamma \vdash  M:A]]></fr:tex>, and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Gamma \vdash  M\equiv  N: A]]></fr:tex> are all decidable.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:p>The <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000S.xml"
addr="jms-000S"
title="Cubical canonicity">canonicity conjecture</fr:link> ensures that terms written in cubical type theory can be thought of as computer programs, and was verified independently by <fr:link
type="local"
href="huber-2018.xml"
addr="huber-2018"
title="Canonicity for cubical type theory">Huber</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="angiuli-2019.xml"
addr="angiuli-2019"
title="Computational semantics of cartesian cubical type theory">Angiuli</fr:link> for different variants of cubical type theory. The <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000T.xml"
addr="jms-000T"
title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability conjecture</fr:link> is no less important, as it is a necessary ingredient to implement a <fr:em>typechecker</fr:em> or a <fr:em>compiler</fr:em> for a programming language based on cubical type theory.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16453</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000U</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000U.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Contributions of First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability">Contributions of <fr:em>First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:em></fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">dissertation</fr:link> positively resolves the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000T.xml"
addr="jms-000T"
title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability conjecture</fr:link> for cubical type theory, the last remaining open question in its syntactic metatheory. Standard techniques proved inadequate for tackling this problem, so the bulk of this dissertation focuses on developing a new mathematical technique called <fr:strong>synthetic Tait computability</fr:strong> that generalizes and abstracts the method of <fr:em>Tait computability</fr:em> or <fr:em>logical predicates</fr:em>; in the past two years, synthetic Tait computability has played a central role in solving several problems in both type theory and core programming languages, suggesting that this dissertation presents a lasting and transformative contribution to the state of the art.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16455</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000V</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000V.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Detailed overview of First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability">Detailed overview of <fr:em>First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:em></fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We give a chapter-by-chapter overview of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory"><fr:em>First Steps in Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:em></fr:link>. The novel contributions are contained in Chapters 4, 5, 7, and 8; the remaining Chapters 0-3 and 6 are primarily expository.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16457</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000W</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000W.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part I: dependent dype theory">Part I: dependent dype theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16459</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000X</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000X.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 0: conspectus on type theory">Chapter 0: conspectus on type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This chapter situates the motivations and applications of type theory in mathematics and computer science, and poses these against the semantic and syntactic properties of type theory that are needed to substantiate these applications. On the semantic side, type theory needs a number of properties including function extensionality, function comprehension, propositional univalence, effective quotients, etc.; on the syntactic side, type theory needs to be at least consistent, and many applications require both canonicity and decidability. Combining these syntactic and semantic properties into a single system has been a challenge, and cubical type theory was designed with the intention of satisfying them all. Prior to this dissertation, only the decidability conjecture remained open; thus with the present contribution, we regard the <fr:em>Cubical Hypothesis</fr:em> confirmed.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16461</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000Y</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000Y.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 1: objective syntax of dependent types">Chapter 1: objective syntax of dependent types</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>To state and prove theorems like <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000S.xml"
addr="jms-000S"
title="Cubical canonicity">canonicity</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000T.xml"
addr="jms-000T"
title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability</fr:link> for a type theory, we must have a mathematical definition of the <fr:em>syntax</fr:em> of type theory. Conventionally, the syntax of type theory has been studied in several layers: one starts with a definition of “raw” syntax as trees labeled by the names of the generating operations, quotients these trees under permutation of bound variables, and then layers on top of this an additional inductively defined formalism expressing the well-formedness of types, well-formedness of terms, definitional equality of types, and definitional equality of terms. After this, one verifies that definitional equivalence classes of well-formed types and terms can be used as the raw materials to construct a universal model of the type theory that has a universal property: any other model of type theory can be equipped with a unique structure-preserving homomorphism from the universal model. The described universal property determines the universal model up to unique isomorphism, if such a model exists.</fr:p><fr:p>We refer to the painstaking process described above as the subjective metatheory, building on the <fr:link
type="local"
href="hegel-sol.xml"
addr="hegel-sol"
title="Wissenschaft der Logik">Hegel</fr:link>–<fr:link
type="local"
href="lawvere-1994.xml"
addr="lawvere-1994"
title="Tools for the advancement of objective logic: closed categories and toposes">Lawvere</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="lawvere-schanuel-2009.xml"
addr="lawvere-schanuel-2009"
title="Conceptual mathematics: a first introduction to categories">distinction</fr:link> between objective and subjective approaches to logic. The objective metatheory, in contrast, involves stating and proving results about type theories and programming languages relying only on the universal property of the universal model and not on any specifics of its presentation; the advantage of the objective metatheory is that it is simpler, more direct, more modular, and more composable.</fr:p><fr:p>Chapter 1 argues that the subjective metatheory in the sense described is redundant: the decidability conjecture can be stated with respect to any representative of the universal model and does not depend in any way on the raw syntax of type theory, and moreover, for all the type theories considered in this dissertation the existence of at least one representative of the universal model is guaranteed for somewhat trivial reasons that have nothing to do with the specifics of type theory. In this chapter, we develop a logical framework for specifying type theories modularly and working with their universal models in an objective fashion.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16463</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000Z</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000Z.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part II: mathematical Background">Part II: mathematical Background</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16465</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0010</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0010.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 2: the language of topoi">Chapter 2: the language of topoi</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Much of this dissertation is stated and proved by exploiting the language of (Grothendieck) topoi, a concept that leads a dual life as a kind of generalized logic <fr:em>and</fr:em> as a kind of generalized topology. The viewpoint of topos theory <fr:em>qua</fr:em> generalized topology plays an important role in this dissertation, and yet it nonetheless remains unfamiliar to most computer scientists and logicians. For this reason, Chapter 2 is provided as sufficient exposition to understand the use of topoi in the remainder of the dissertation, focusing on the <fr:em>recollement</fr:em> or <fr:em>gluing</fr:em> of a topos from a pair of complementary open and closed subtopoi, a classical construction that provides the geometrical basis for synthetic Tait computability.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16467</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0011</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0011.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 3: the theory of universes">Chapter 3: the theory of universes</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Universes started their life in the <fr:link
type="local"
href="sga-4.xml"
addr="sga-4"
title="Théorie des topos et cohomologie étale des schémas (SGA 4)">Grothendieck school of algebraic geometry</fr:link> as a technical device to circumvent the annoyance that there cannot be a “set of all sets”; a universe is a set of enough sets, and whilst a universe cannot contain itself, it may nonetheless lie within an even bigger universe. Several important developments in the theory of universes from the 1970s onward by <fr:link
type="local"
href="jeanb%C3%A9nabou.xml"
addr="jeanbénabou"
title="Jean Bénabou">Bénabou</fr:link>, <fr:link
type="local"
href="permartinl%C3%B6f.xml"
addr="permartinlöf"
title="Per Martin-Löf">Martin-Löf</fr:link>, Dybjer, <fr:link
type="local"
href="martinhofmann.xml"
addr="martinhofmann"
title="Martin Hofmann">Hofmann</fr:link>, <fr:link
type="local"
href="thomasstreicher.xml"
addr="thomasstreicher"
title="Thomas Streicher">Streicher</fr:link>, <fr:link
type="local"
href="steveawodey.xml"
addr="steveawodey"
title="Steve Awodey">Awodey</fr:link>, and others have collided to deliver the present-day understanding of the centrality of universes in semantics: a model of type theory is just a special kind of universe in a special kind of category. This chapter provides expository background on the theory of universes, including a novel account of open and closed subuniverses to reflect the recollement theory of topoi from <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0010.xml"
addr="jms-0010"
title="Chapter 2: the language of topoi">Chapter 2</fr:link>. These open and closed subuniverses will play a critical role in the development of synthetic Tait computability in subsequent chapters.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16469</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0012</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0012.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part III: synthetic Tait computability">Part III: synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16471</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0013</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0013.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 4: Tait's method of computability">Chapter 4: Tait's method of computability</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>It is simple enough to verify <fr:strong>negative</fr:strong> properties of a formal system, e.g. the non-derivability of a given assertion <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Phi ]]></fr:tex>: find a mathematical object that models all the rules of the formal system and yet refutes <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\Phi ]]></fr:tex>. In contrast, it is much harder to verify any non-trivial <fr:strong>positive</fr:strong> property of a formal system (such as canonicity, normalization, decidability, etc.). To handle such results, new techniques were needed — and delivered in the late 1960s by Tait, Martin-Löf and others under the name of Tait’s method of computability or logical predicates. Since its inception, Tait’s method has been the primary tool for verifying positive properties of logics, programming languages, and type theories. Early on, <fr:link
type="local"
href="freyd-1978.xml"
addr="freyd-1978"
title="On proving that 1 is an indecomposable projective in various free categories">Freyd</fr:link> noticed that the logical predicates arguments can be rephrased as model constructions that glue together geometrical objects corresponding to <fr:em>syntax</fr:em> (object) and <fr:em>set theory</fr:em> (meta), setting the stage for this thesis. Thus despite appearances, both positive and negative properties can both be proved using semantic methods.</fr:p><fr:p>In the subsequent development of the computability method for applications in computer science, <fr:em>indexed</fr:em> variants of the logical predicates have proved to be fundamental and a number of variations on indexed logical predicates have appeared including the Kripke logical predicates of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jung-tiuryn-1993.xml"
addr="jung-tiuryn-1993"
title="A new characterization of lambda definability">Jung and Tiuryn</fr:link> and the much more sophisticated <fr:em>Grothendieck</fr:em> logical predicates of <fr:link
type="local"
href="fiore-simpson-1999.xml"
addr="fiore-simpson-1999"
title="Lambda definability with sums via Grothendieck logical relations">Fiore and Simpson</fr:link> as well as <fr:link
type="local"
href="altenkirch-dybjer-hofmann-scott-2001.xml"
addr="altenkirch-dybjer-hofmann-scott-2001"
title="Normalization by evaluation for typed lambda calculus with coproducts">Altenkirch, Dybjer, Hofmann, and Scott</fr:link>. This chapter points out that all of these forms of indexing arise in the same way from what is referred to as a <fr:strong>figure shape</fr:strong>, a continuous map into the classifying space of “Henkin models” of a given theory. Then the (Kripke, Grothendieck, etc.) logical predicates model is presented much more simply as the Artin gluing of this morphism’s inverse image.</fr:p><fr:p>An explicit proof of canonicity for the simply typed <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\lambda ]]></fr:tex>-calculus motivates the abstraction and axiomatization of the geometry of figure shapes and their gluings as a new language for syntactic metatheory, namely <fr:strong>synthetic Tait computability</fr:strong>. The idea of synthetic Tait computability is to treat both object-level notions (e.g. the collection of terms of type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathsf {bool}]]></fr:tex>) and meta-level notions (e.g. a normal form of a given term) in the same language by means of a pair of lex idempotent modalities. One strength of this presentation is that both object-level and meta-level notions can be treated using higher-order abstract syntax (HOAS) in the sense of <fr:link
type="local"
href="hofmann-1999.xml"
addr="hofmann-1999"
title="Semantical analysis of higher-order abstract syntax">Hofmann</fr:link>, which greatly simplifies the manipulation of variables.</fr:p><fr:p>The first demonstration of the power and modularity of synthetic Tait
  computability is a new a proof of the canonicity property for Martin-Löf type theory. Unlike traditional proofs of canonicity via non-synthetic Tait computability, the synthetic version is completely modular and broken up into general-purpose lemmas that are stated at a high level of abstraction and can be reused in proofs of <fr:em>different properties</fr:em> for <fr:em>different type theories</fr:em>. (Indeed, some of the constructions isolated in this chapter are used off the shelf in <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0014.xml"
addr="jms-0014"
title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">Chapter 7</fr:link> to prove normalization for cubical type theory.) The modularization of syntactic metatheory is one of the main contributions of this dissertation.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16473</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0015</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0015.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 5: synthetic normalization by evaluation">Chapter 5: synthetic normalization by evaluation</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This chapter develops a more sophisticated application of synthetic Tait computability, the proof of normalization and decidability of Martin-Löf’s type theory with a cumulative hierarchy of universes. The synthetic argument contained in this chapter builds on the work of <fr:link
type="local"
href="fiore-2002.xml"
addr="fiore-2002"
title="Semantic analysis of normalisation by evaluation for typed lambda calculus">Fiore</fr:link> on categorical normalization by gluing for simply typed λ-calculus, and that of <fr:link
type="local"
href="coquand-2019.xml"
addr="coquand-2019"
title="Canonicity and normalization for dependent type theory">Coquand</fr:link> on a presheaf-theoretic version of normalization by evaluation for dependent types. Analogous to the external argument of <fr:link
type="local"
href="fiore-2002.xml"
addr="fiore-2002"
title="Semantic analysis of normalisation by evaluation for typed lambda calculus">Fiore</fr:link>, we construe the syntax of normal and neutral forms as the initial algebra for an internal inductive definition in the language of synthetic Tait computability. The influence of <fr:link
type="local"
href="coquand-2019.xml"
addr="coquand-2019"
title="Canonicity and normalization for dependent type theory">Coquand</fr:link> is visible in the definition of the <fr:em>Tait saturation yoga</fr:em> for dependent types in the synthetic setting, an important closure condition for logical predicates that comprised one of the main innovations of <fr:link
type="local"
href="tait-1967.xml"
addr="tait-1967"
title="Intensional interpretations of functionals of finite type I">Tait</fr:link> in the context of simply typed combinators. Although this chapter is intended only as “dry run” for the main result (to be exposed in <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0014.xml"
addr="jms-0014"
title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">Chapter 7</fr:link>), the normalization argument presented here has intrinsic value: it is the simplest and most direct proof of normalization and decidability for Martin-Löf type theory with <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\eta ]]></fr:tex>-laws and cumulative universes that has appeared in the literature so far.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16475</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0016</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0016.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part IV: cubical type theory">Part IV: cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16477</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0017</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0017.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 6: cartesian cubical type theory">Chapter 6: cartesian cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This expository chapter introduces cubical type theory as an extension to Martin-Löf’s type theory by an interval <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> with two distinct endpoints <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[0, 1 : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex>. The interval is a basic “figure” that defines a notion of <fr:em>path</fr:em> or <fr:em>identification</fr:em> <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{u}\mathrel {{\sim }_{A}}{v}]]></fr:tex> between two elements of any type; for instance, to identify <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[u,v:A]]></fr:tex> is the same as to construct a function <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p:\mathbb {I}\to  A]]></fr:tex> such that <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p0 = u]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p1=v]]></fr:tex>. Terms involving <fr:em>variables</fr:em> of type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> can exhibit complex computational behavior that is difficult to account for: for instance, if <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p:{u}\mathrel {{\sim }_{A}}{v}]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[i:\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> are variables, then the application <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[pi:A]]></fr:tex> is a normal form, but it must nonetheless reduce to either <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[u]]></fr:tex> or <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[v]]></fr:tex> when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[i]]></fr:tex> is substituted for by a constant. Despite appearances, this scenario is fundamentally different from the way that <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[pi]]></fr:tex> must reduce when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[p]]></fr:tex> is replaced
by a <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\lambda ]]></fr:tex>-abstraction, as normal forms must <fr:em>a priori</fr:em> be closed under arbitrary <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex>-substitutions — a necessity, because the normal form of an <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n]]></fr:tex>-cube must be an <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n]]></fr:tex>-cube of normal forms. One of the main technical contributions of this dissertation, introduced in the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0014.xml"
addr="jms-0014"
title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">next chapter</fr:link>, is to generalization of the notion of neutral form and the Tait saturation yoga that smoothly accommodates the problematic computational behavior of the interval.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16479</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0014</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0014.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory">Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This chapter reports the main result of the dissertation, normalization for cubical type theory and its corollaries: injectivity of type constructors, and <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000T.xml"
addr="jms-000T"
title="Decidability of cubical type theory">decidability of equality &amp; typing</fr:link>. These results were first obtained by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-angiuli-2021"
title="Normalization for cubical type theory">Sterling and Angiuli</fr:link> for the fragment of cubical type theory <fr:em>without</fr:em> universes; the present chapter extends the results of <fr:em>op. cit.</fr:em> to support a cumulative hierarchy of universes.</fr:p><fr:p>The central innovation of this chapter is to generalize the notion of neutral form to accommodate the computational behavior of terms that have free variables of type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> discussed in our <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0017.xml"
addr="jms-0017"
title="Chapter 6: cartesian cubical type theory">synopsis of Chapter 6</fr:link>.  In the conventional account of neutral and normal forms, neutrals <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> are built up inductively from
<fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x]]></fr:tex> for term variables <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x : A]]></fr:tex>, function applications to normal forms <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{\bullet }}}{{\color {DarkBlue}{m}}}]]></fr:tex>
and projections from neutral pairs <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}{\color {DarkRed}{.1}}]]></fr:tex>, <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}{\color {DarkRed}{.2}}]]></fr:tex>; our account of neutrals is much the same, except that each neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> comes equipped with a <fr:strong>“frontier
  of instability”</fr:strong> <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}]]></fr:tex>, a predicate on its free <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex>-variables that indicates when it “needs to compute further”. We think of a neutral form for an <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[n]]></fr:tex>-cube as being <fr:em>undefined</fr:em> on its frontier of instability; the process of restricting a neutral to its frontier of instability is then referred to as <fr:em>destabilization</fr:em>.</fr:p><fr:p>When <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x : A]]></fr:tex> is a variable of an ordinary type, the frontier of instability <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }\,{\mathopen {}\left ({\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,{x}\right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex> is empty because variables never need to compute further. Where something new happens is the path type: given a neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}} : \mathsf {ne}\,{\mathopen {}\left ({u}\mathrel {{\sim }_{A}}{v}\right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex>
of path type, we have for each term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[r : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> a neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r} : \mathsf {ne}\,A]]></fr:tex> whose frontier of instability is defined like so:</fr:p><fr:tex
display="block"><![CDATA[  \boldsymbol {\partial }\,{\mathopen {}\left ({{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}\right )\mathclose {}} = \boldsymbol {\partial }{\color {DarkRed}{e}} \lor  {\mathopen {}\left (r=0\right )\mathclose {}} \lor  {\mathopen {}\left (r=1\right )\mathclose {}} ]]></fr:tex><fr:p>In other words, the path neutral application <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{e}}}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}]]></fr:tex> needs to compute as soon as e needs to compute, and as soon as the interval term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[r : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> becomes equal to a constant. Prior to the introduction of the frontier of instability, the neutrals are embedded into the normals at base types unconditionally, i.e. for each neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}} : \mathsf {ne}\,\mathsf {bool}]]></fr:tex>, we have a normal form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkBlue}{\lfloor }}{e}{\color {DarkBlue}{\rfloor }} : \mathsf {nf}\,\mathsf {bool}]]></fr:tex>.</fr:p><fr:p>Now that neutrals are equipped with frontiers of instability, a more refined notion of normal form is needed: when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> is a neutral form, the corresponding normal form should contain (recursively) normal forms for <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[e]]></fr:tex> that are defined under the frontier of instability <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }\,{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex>. To be more concrete,
let <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x : {\mathsf {tt}}\mathrel {{\sim }_{\mathsf {bool}}}{\mathsf {tt}}]]></fr:tex> be a variable of path type and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[r : \mathbb {I}]]></fr:tex> is a term; then <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,x}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}:\mathsf {ne}\,{\mathopen {}\left ({\mathsf {tt}}\mathrel {{\sim }_{\mathsf {bool}}}{\mathsf {tt}}\right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex> is a neutral form for the term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[xr]]></fr:tex> whose frontier of instability is the boundary <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[(r = 0) \lor  (r = 1)]]></fr:tex>; the corresponding normal form must therefore glue onto <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{{\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,x}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r}]]></fr:tex> additional normal forms for <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x0]]></fr:tex> and
<fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[x1]]></fr:tex>. We refer to the process of completing a neutral with additional data defined on its frontier of instability as stabilization; the <fr:em>stabilized</fr:em> normal form of <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[xr]]></fr:tex> is then written</fr:p><fr:tex
display="block"><![CDATA[ {\color {DarkBlue}{\lfloor }}{{{\color {DarkRed}{\mathsf {var}}}\,x}\mathrel {{\color {DarkRed}{@}}}{r} \mid  r = 0 \hookrightarrow  {\color {DarkBlue}{\mathsf {tt}}}, r = 1 \hookrightarrow {\color {DarkBlue}{\mathsf {tt}}}}{\color {DarkBlue}{\rfloor }} ]]></fr:tex><fr:p>where <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkBlue}{\mathsf {tt}}}]]></fr:tex> is the normal form representing the term <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\mathsf {tt}]]></fr:tex></fr:p><fr:p>Just as the embedding of neutrals into normals is “stabilized” by a com patible normal form defined on the neutral’s frontier of instability, so too must the Tait saturation yoga be adjusted. Conventionally one requires the computability predicate for a type <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A]]></fr:tex> to be equipped with a function that takes neutral forms <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> of terms <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[e : A]]></fr:tex> to computability witnesses for the same term. In the <fr:strong>stabilized Tait saturation yoga</fr:strong>, we strengthen the induction hypothesis to require for each neutral form <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> a function that extends a computability witness defined only on the frontier of instability <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\boldsymbol {\partial }{\color {DarkRed}{e}}]]></fr:tex> to a computability witnessed defined everywhere</fr:p><fr:p>The twin innovations of <fr:em>frontiers of instability</fr:em> and <fr:em>stabilization</fr:em> then suffice to adapt the synthetic normalization argument of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0015.xml"
addr="jms-0015"
title="Chapter 5: synthetic normalization by evaluation">Chapter 5</fr:link> to a proof of normalization (and thus decidability) for cubical type theory.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16481</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0018</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0018.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Part V: prospects">Part V: prospects</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16483</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0019</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0019.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Chapter 8: a plan for PL">Chapter 8: a plan for PL</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This dissertation has focused almost solely on the development and applications of synthetic Tait computability in the context of pure type theory, but the author originally invented synthetic Tait computability to solve problems in core programming languages, as part of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>’s re-analysis of the <fr:em>phase distinction</fr:em> in <fr:link
type="local"
href="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990.xml"
addr="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990"
title="Higher-order modules and the phase distinction">ML-style</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="moggi-1989.xml"
addr="moggi-1989"
title="A category-theoretic account of program modules">module systems</fr:link> between static (compiletime) and dynamic (runtime) code. The purpose of this chapter is to identify several applications of synthetic Tait computability to core programming languages, and set an agenda for future work — some of which has been executed and published following the completion of this dissertation</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16381</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-001A</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001A.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules">§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A brief overview is given of the applications of synthetic Tait computability to program modules, material that is published in the <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Journal of the ACM</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16383</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-001B</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001B.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction">§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <fr:em>refinement types</fr:em> and <fr:em>program extraction</fr:em> via a phase distinction between <fr:em>computation</fr:em> and <fr:em>specification</fr:em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\phi }\sqsubset {A}]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[{\psi }\sqsubset {B}]]></fr:tex> are refinements of types <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A]]></fr:tex> and <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[B]]></fr:tex> respectively, then <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\phi \to \psi ]]></fr:tex> refines <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A\to  B]]></fr:tex>. In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</fr:link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16385</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-001C</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001C.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="§ 8.3: information-flow and noninterference">§ 8.3: information-flow and noninterference</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>20</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Finally, an application of synthetic Tait computability to <fr:em>security</fr:em> and <fr:em>information flow control</fr:em> is identified: a security class is a phase distinction between low and high security. The preliminary results presented in this section have been substantially improved upon by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2022"
title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>, adding support for general recursion and termination-insensitive noninterference by combining synthetic Tait computability with <fr:link
type="local"
href="hyland-1991.xml"
addr="hyland-1991"
title="First steps in synthetic domain theory">synthetic domain theory</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>