<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16114</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000J</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000J.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Euclid’s parallel postulate">Euclid’s parallel postulate</fr:title><fr:taxon>Postulate</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>“If a straight line falling on two straight lines make the interior angles on the same side less than two right angles, the two straight lines, if produced indefinitely, meet on that side on which the angles are less than two right angles.”</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16116</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000I</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000I.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Synthesis, analysis, and the axiomatic method">Synthesis, analysis, and the axiomatic method</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The axiomatic method in mathematics is a tug of war between analysis and synthesis: analysis studies an object by modeling it with some substance that reliably behaves like the object in question, whereas synthesis takes stock of the competing models for an object and proceeds from an axiomatization of their essential properties. Analysis is important because it allows scientists to distinguish between empty fantasies and concepts that are grounded in reality by proceeding from the general to the particular; synthesis is no less important because it sharpens our view of the objects we study by summating our historical (analytical) experience in the form of axioms.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16118</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-000L</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000L.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Euclid’s synthetic plane geometry">Euclid’s synthetic plane geometry</fr:title><fr:taxon>Example</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The canonical example of the synthetic method is the ancient Greek mathematician Euclid’s plane geometry, which starts from an axiomatization of the properties of points, lines, circles, and angles as primitive notions. For instance:</fr:p><fr:ol><fr:li>A straight line can be drawn between any two points.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>A line segment can be extended to a straight line.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>There exists a circle with any center and radius.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>All right angles are equal to each other.</fr:li></fr:ol></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:p>The postulates above are descriptive of many <fr:strong>different</fr:strong> “models” for the concept of a line: this can be seen by considering the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-000J.xml"
addr="jms-000J"
title="Euclid’s parallel postulate">parallel postulate</fr:link>, whose affirmation and negation are both consistent with the four postulates above. The revolution in modern mathematics brought on by the introduction of <fr:em>analytic</fr:em> (coordinate-based) methods under Descartes and Fermat should be understood as affirming the need for a plurality of models given that useful axiomatic systems can almost never uniquely determine their subject matter.</fr:p><fr:p>Analytic methods have been utterly dominant in recent mathematics: today, almost no mathematics is done purely synthetically, i.e. without reference whatsoever to a model. The modern viewpoint however accommodates (and greatly relies upon) the summation of analytic experience in the form of axioms, e.g. the <fr:link
type="local"
href="lawvere-1964-etcs.xml"
addr="lawvere-1964-etcs"
title="An elementary theory of the category of sets">axioms of set theory</fr:link>, the <fr:link
type="local"
href="grothendieck-1957-tohoku.xml"
addr="grothendieck-1957-tohoku"
title="Sur quelques points d’algèbre homologique, I.">axioms of abelian categories</fr:link>, or the <fr:link
type="local"
href="eilenberg-steenrod-1945.xml"
addr="eilenberg-steenrod-1945"
title="Axiomatic approach to homology theory">axioms of homology theories</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>