<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12616</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0077</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0077.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Work performed and main achievements">Work performed and main achievements</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>I highlight the three main achievements of the TypeSynth project below:</fr:p><fr:ol><fr:li>a new denotational semantics of higher-order store;</fr:li>
  <fr:li>an equational higher-order separation logic based on the above denotational semantics;</fr:li>
  <fr:li>the extension of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">synthetic Tait computability</fr:link> to support computational effects including guarded recursion and higher-order store.</fr:li></fr:ol><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12329</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0078</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0078.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Denotational semantics of higher-order store">Denotational semantics of higher-order store</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> plan to develop denotational semantics of higher-order store had two components: the first was to develop a practical semantic model of polymorphic higher-order store without garbage collection, and the second was to extend this model to support the equational theory of garbage collection. For the former, the results have greatly outstripped expectations: I have succeeded in constructing not only the indended model of store with polymorphism, but in fact a <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">model of full dependent type theory with higher-order store</fr:link> — posing the prospect for being able to write and verify the correctness of programs in the same language. This result is the first of its kind for higher-order store, and is a significant advance. In the final months of the project, we have also gone further beyond this result in a different direction, and constructed a version of the model of higher-order store satisfying a new gamut of compelling representation independence equations which I refer to as the theory of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent"
title="Towards univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</fr:link>: in short, two programs can be considered equal even if they allocate memory cells of different types, so long as the two types are in bijection and programs' interaction with the memory cell respects this bijection.</fr:p><fr:p>I have begun to extend these results to include the equational theory of garbage collection, but as the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project has been terminated nearly one year early (due to my recent appointment as Associate Professor at University of Cambridge), this further exploitation of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> methodology will continue beyond the conclusion of the project.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12331</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0079</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0079.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Equational higher-order separation logic for higher-order store">Equational higher-order separation logic for higher-order store</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>In collaboration with my colleagues <fr:link
type="local"
href="flaagaard.xml"
addr="flaagaard"
title="Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard">Frederik Ljerbjerg Aagaard</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Professor Lars Birkedal</fr:link>, I have developed a <fr:link
type="local"
href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml"
addr="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023"
title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">guarded higher-order separation logic called TULIP</fr:link> over the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational model of higher-order store</fr:link>. This logic represents a significant step forward in the march toward simple, abstract, and compositional reasoning about higher-order stateful programs. Prior program logics (such as Iris and the Verified Software Toolchain) interact with computer programs only indirectly, by verifying properties of a specific “transition function” that simulates the steps that a (highly idealized) computer would take when executing a program; this style is called “operational”. Unfortunately, the important structural properties of programs are highly unnatural to express at the level of transition steps, and as such, existing operationally-based program logics impose a great deal of bureaucracy by forcing those verifying programs to manually mediate the mismatch between the viewpoint of the machine (which cannot see program structure), and the viewpoint of the programmer (which is entirely based on program structure). An equational, or "denotationally-based", program logic like <fr:link
type="local"
href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml"
addr="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023"
title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</fr:link> instead treats programs directly without needing to pass through an encoding in terms of machine transitions. An immediate benefit of the equational approach is that program equivalences can be glued together directly in any context, a kind of practical compositionality that is unique to equational and denotationally-based program logics. Our development of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml"
addr="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023"
title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</fr:link> logic is a strong first step in this direction.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12333</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-007A</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-007A.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Effectful synthetic Tait computability">Effectful <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">synthetic Tait computability</fr:link></fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A third achievement of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project was to extend the highly successful “<fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:link>” method, developed in my <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">doctoral thesis</fr:link>, to the case of realistic programming languages with computational effects. The purpose of this extension was to achieve strong representation independence results, by which we can show the computational indistinguishability of even two programs that allocate memory cells of different types that are linked not by a bijection but by a mere relation, in contrast to univalent reference types. We have gone quite a bit beyond our expectations, as our account of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism"><fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</fr:link> for higher-order store</fr:link> applies not only to the simple polymorphic store model, but also to the full dependent type theory. This allows many classic results from the literature that previously required very complicated reasoning with the semantic model to be reconstructed in a simpler and more direct fashion.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="References">References</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12618</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Towards univalent reference types">Towards univalent reference types</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2024</fr:year><fr:month>2</fr:month><fr:day>7</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.CSL.2024.47</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="csl-2024.xml"
addr="csl-2024"
title="CSL ’24: 32nd EACSL Annual Conference on Computer Science Logic 2024"><fr:em>CSL ’24</fr:em>: 32nd EACSL Annual Conference on Computer Science Logic 2024</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@inproceedings{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  title = {{Towards Univalent Reference Types: The Impact of Univalence on Denotational Semantics}},
  booktitle = {32nd EACSL Annual Conference on Computer Science Logic (CSL 2024)},
  pages = {47:1--47:21},
  series = {Leibniz International Proceedings in Informatics (LIPIcs)},
  ISBN = {978-3-95977-310-2},
  ISSN = {1868-8969},
  year = {2024},
  volume = {288},
  editor = {Murano, Aniello and Silva, Alexandra},
  publisher = {Schloss Dagstuhl -- Leibniz-Zentrum f{\"u}r Informatik},
  address = {Dagstuhl, Germany},
  doi =  {10.4230/LIPIcs.CSL.2024.47},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We develop a denotational semantics for general reference types in an <fr:link
type="local"
href="awodey-frey-speight-2018.xml"
addr="awodey-frey-speight-2018"
title="Impredicative encodings of (higher) inductive types">impredicative version</fr:link> of <fr:link
type="local"
href="bbcgsv-2019.xml"
addr="bbcgsv-2019"
title="Guarded cubical type theory"><fr:strong><fr:em>guarded homotopy type theory</fr:em></fr:strong></fr:link>, an adaptation of <fr:link
type="local"
href="bmss-2011.xml"
addr="bmss-2011"
title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">synthetic guarded domain theory</fr:link> to Voevodsky’s <fr:link
type="local"
href="hottbook.xml"
addr="hottbook"
title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">univalent foundations</fr:link>. We observe for the first time the profound impact of univalence on the <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational semantics of mutable state</fr:link>. Univalence automatically ensures that all computations are invariant under symmetries of the heap—a bountiful source of program equivalences. In particular, even the most simplistic univalent model enjoys many new program equivalences that do not hold when the same constructions are carried out in the universes of traditional set-level (extensional) type theory.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12622</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023</fr:addr><fr:route>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>11</fr:month><fr:day>23</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="flaagaard.xml"
addr="flaagaard"
title="Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard">Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.46298/entics.12232</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">39th International Conference on Mathematical Foundations of Programming Semantics</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Separation logic is used to reason locally about stateful programs. State of the art program logics for higher-order store are usually built on top of untyped operational semantics, in part because traditional denotational methods have struggled to simultaneously account for general references and parametric polymorphism. The <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">recent discovery</fr:link> of simple denotational semantics for general references and polymorphism in synthetic guarded domain theory has enabled us to develop <fr:strong>Tulip</fr:strong>, a higher-order separation logic over the typed equational theory of higher-order store for a monadic version of System <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\textbf {F}^{\mu ,\textit {ref}}]]></fr:tex>. The <fr:strong>Tulip</fr:strong> logic differs from operationally-based program logics in two ways: predicates range over the meanings of typed terms rather than over the raw code of untyped terms, and they are automatically invariant under the equational congruence of higher-order store, which applies even underneath a binder. As a result, “pure” proof steps that conventionally require focusing the Hoare triple on an operational redex are replaced by a simple equational rewrite in <fr:strong>Tulip</fr:strong>. We have evaluated <fr:strong>Tulip</fr:strong> against standard examples involving linked lists in the heap, comparing our abstract equational reasoning with more familiar operational-style reasoning. Our main result is the soundness of <fr:strong>Tulip</fr:strong>, which we establish by constructing a BI-hyperdoctrine over the denotational semantics of <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\textbf {F}^{\mu ,\textit {ref}}]]></fr:tex> in an impredicative version of synthetic guarded domain theory.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12626</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>10</fr:month><fr:day>6</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on <fr:em>recursively defined semantic worlds</fr:em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational reasoning based on the <fr:em>logical relations as types</fr:em> principle, in which equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value adjunction with higher-order store, improving on <fr:link
type="local"
href="paulblainlevy.xml"
addr="paulblainlevy"
title="Paul Blain Levy">Levy</fr:link>'s possible worlds model construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <fr:em>synthetic guarded domain theory</fr:em>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12630</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-thesis</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-thesis.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>9</fr:month><fr:day>13</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Doctoral dissertation, <fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-2021-thesis.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@phdthesis{sterling-2021-thesis,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  school = {Carnegie Mellon University},
  year = {2021},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.6990769},
  note = {Version 1.1, revised May 2022},
  number = {CMU-CS-21-142},
  title = {First Steps in Synthetic {Tait} Computability: The Objective Metatheory of Cubical Type Theory},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.5281/zenodo.6990769</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The implementation and semantics of dependent type theories can be studied in a syntax-independent way: the objective metatheory of dependent type theories exploits the universal properties of their syntactic categories to endow them with computational content, mathematical meaning, and practical implementation (normalization, type checking, elaboration). The semantic methods of the objective metatheory inform the design and implementation of correct-by-construction elaboration algorithms, promising a principled interface between real proof assistants and ideal mathematics.</fr:p><fr:p>In this dissertation, I add synthetic Tait computability to the arsenal of the objective metatheorist. Synthetic Tait computability is a mathematical machine to reduce difficult problems of type theory and programming languages to trivial theorems of topos theory. First employed by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</fr:link> to reconstruct the theory of program modules and their phase separated parametricity, synthetic Tait computability is deployed here to resolve the last major open question in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory: normalization of open terms.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="Context">Context</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12632</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0075</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0075.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="TypeSynth final report"><fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> final report</fr:title><fr:taxon>Report</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This is the final report for the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> MSCA project.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12325</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0076</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0076.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Context and overall objectives">Context and overall objectives</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Software systems mediate a growing proportion of human activity, e.g. communication, transport, medicine, industrial and agricultural production, etc. As a result, it is urgent to understand and better control both the correctness and security properties of these increasingly complex software systems. The diversity of verification requirements speaks to a need for models of program execution that smoothly interpolate between many different levels of abstraction. Models of program execution vary in expressiveness along the spectrum of possible programming languages and specification logics. At one extreme, dependent type theory is a language for mathematically-inspired functional programming that is sufficiently expressive to serve as its own specification logic. Dependent type theory has struggled, however, to incorporate several computational effects that are common in every-day programming languages, such as state and concurrency. One of the most extreme forms of computational effect is “higher-order mutable state”, which is when programs can read and write data as well as entire subroutines to the computer’s memory during execution.  Programming languages that support these features require very sophisticated specification logics due to the myriad details that must be surfaced in their semantic models.</fr:p><fr:p>Recently there have been several significant technical advances in mathematical semantics for programming languages that have been ripe for exploitation. For instance, in <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">my doctoral thesis</fr:link> I developed a new technique called <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:link> or “STC” that smoothly combines multiple levels of abstraction into a single language. Inspired by sophisticated mathematical techniques invented in topos theory and category theory for entirely different purposes, STC enables low-level details (even down to execution steps) to be manipulated in a simpler and more abstract way than ever before, making them easier to control mathematically. Perhaps more importantly, the STC method makes it possible to import ideas and techniques from other mathematical fields that are comparatively more developed than programming languages. Another related advance is the use of <fr:link
type="local"
href="bmss-2011.xml"
addr="bmss-2011"
title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">Synthetic Guarded Domain Theory</fr:link> or “SGDT” as a mathematical language in which to describe and reason about the behavior of computer programs, potentially exhibiting complex interactions with their environment and with other programs. A third advance setting the stage for this project is the development of <fr:link
type="local"
href="hottbook.xml"
addr="hottbook"
title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">Univalent Foundations and Homotopy Type Theory</fr:link>, a new and backwards-compatible foundation of mathematics that places symmetries and reversible transformations of mathematical structures in the forefront.</fr:p><fr:p>The goal of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project has been to combine these three ideas to break a long-standing logjam in the mathematical understanding of computer programming: the denotational semantics and equational separation logic of higher-order mutable state.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12327</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0077</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0077.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Work performed and main achievements">Work performed and main achievements</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>I highlight the three main achievements of the TypeSynth project below:</fr:p><fr:ol><fr:li>a new denotational semantics of higher-order store;</fr:li>
  <fr:li>an equational higher-order separation logic based on the above denotational semantics;</fr:li>
  <fr:li>the extension of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">synthetic Tait computability</fr:link> to support computational effects including guarded recursion and higher-order store.</fr:li></fr:ol><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12329</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0078</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0078.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Denotational semantics of higher-order store">Denotational semantics of higher-order store</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> plan to develop denotational semantics of higher-order store had two components: the first was to develop a practical semantic model of polymorphic higher-order store without garbage collection, and the second was to extend this model to support the equational theory of garbage collection. For the former, the results have greatly outstripped expectations: I have succeeded in constructing not only the indended model of store with polymorphism, but in fact a <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">model of full dependent type theory with higher-order store</fr:link> — posing the prospect for being able to write and verify the correctness of programs in the same language. This result is the first of its kind for higher-order store, and is a significant advance. In the final months of the project, we have also gone further beyond this result in a different direction, and constructed a version of the model of higher-order store satisfying a new gamut of compelling representation independence equations which I refer to as the theory of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent"
title="Towards univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</fr:link>: in short, two programs can be considered equal even if they allocate memory cells of different types, so long as the two types are in bijection and programs' interaction with the memory cell respects this bijection.</fr:p><fr:p>I have begun to extend these results to include the equational theory of garbage collection, but as the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project has been terminated nearly one year early (due to my recent appointment as Associate Professor at University of Cambridge), this further exploitation of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> methodology will continue beyond the conclusion of the project.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12331</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0079</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0079.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Equational higher-order separation logic for higher-order store">Equational higher-order separation logic for higher-order store</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>In collaboration with my colleagues <fr:link
type="local"
href="flaagaard.xml"
addr="flaagaard"
title="Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard">Frederik Ljerbjerg Aagaard</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Professor Lars Birkedal</fr:link>, I have developed a <fr:link
type="local"
href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml"
addr="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023"
title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">guarded higher-order separation logic called TULIP</fr:link> over the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational model of higher-order store</fr:link>. This logic represents a significant step forward in the march toward simple, abstract, and compositional reasoning about higher-order stateful programs. Prior program logics (such as Iris and the Verified Software Toolchain) interact with computer programs only indirectly, by verifying properties of a specific “transition function” that simulates the steps that a (highly idealized) computer would take when executing a program; this style is called “operational”. Unfortunately, the important structural properties of programs are highly unnatural to express at the level of transition steps, and as such, existing operationally-based program logics impose a great deal of bureaucracy by forcing those verifying programs to manually mediate the mismatch between the viewpoint of the machine (which cannot see program structure), and the viewpoint of the programmer (which is entirely based on program structure). An equational, or "denotationally-based", program logic like <fr:link
type="local"
href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml"
addr="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023"
title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</fr:link> instead treats programs directly without needing to pass through an encoding in terms of machine transitions. An immediate benefit of the equational approach is that program equivalences can be glued together directly in any context, a kind of practical compositionality that is unique to equational and denotationally-based program logics. Our development of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml"
addr="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023"
title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</fr:link> logic is a strong first step in this direction.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12333</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-007A</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-007A.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Effectful synthetic Tait computability">Effectful <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">synthetic Tait computability</fr:link></fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A third achievement of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project was to extend the highly successful “<fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:link>” method, developed in my <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">doctoral thesis</fr:link>, to the case of realistic programming languages with computational effects. The purpose of this extension was to achieve strong representation independence results, by which we can show the computational indistinguishability of even two programs that allocate memory cells of different types that are linked not by a bijection but by a mere relation, in contrast to univalent reference types. We have gone quite a bit beyond our expectations, as our account of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism"><fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-005T.xml"
addr="jms-005T"
title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</fr:link> for higher-order store</fr:link> applies not only to the simple polymorphic store model, but also to the full dependent type theory. This allows many classic results from the literature that previously required very complicated reasoning with the semantic model to be reconstructed in a simpler and more direct fashion.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12335</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-007B</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-007B.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Results beyond the state of the art">Results beyond the state of the art</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The results of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project have gone significantly beyond the state of the art in denotational semantics for computational effects: not only is ours the first typed denotational model of higher-order store compatible with parametric polymorphism, but we have shown that the same construction also gives rise to a model of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">full dependent type theory with higher-order store</fr:link> — a long sought-after result whose implications we have not yet fully exploited. Our model of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent"
title="Towards univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</fr:link> is also a significant break with the state of the art, and points the way to a new and more fruitful interaction between the fields of programming languages on the one hand, and homotopy type theory and algebraic topology on the other hand.</fr:p><fr:p>The <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0077.xml"
addr="jms-0077"
title="Work performed and main achievements">technical achievements</fr:link> of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> point to healthy growth in the long-neglected area of denotational semantics and equational program logics, but there is an urgent need for further research to bring these superior but comparatively less-developed methods to practical parity with the more established operational paradigm, which currently achieves stronger results in program verification — which we believe can be accounted for by the twenty-year headstart enjoyed by teams favoring operational methods during the relative dormancy of semantic and categorical methods in programming languages.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12337</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-007C</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-007C.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Policy relevant evidence of the project">Policy relevant evidence of the project</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Research in program semantics and verification is essentially of two kinds. On the one hand, there is work that pushes the envelope of what kinds of programs can be verified — demonstrating (at great exertion and expense) the potential to verify the correctness of the extremely complex software that makes our society work, including onboard software used in air planes, industrial production, agricultural production, artificial intelligence, etc.  On the other hand, there is research that aims to rethink from the ground up the mathematical understanding of programming, radically simplifying the foundations on which the program verification tools are built. Both kinds of research are important and rely heavily on each other. Applied program verification is critical because the need to prevent software faults is ever-present, and in order to get any kind of uptake and adoption, we must demonstrate the capability of our tools to handle the very complex problems that are raised by industrial and governmental use of software. Likewise, foundational research is extremely important because when applied program verification hits its conceptual limitations, it can only advance by becoming bigger and more expensive — requiring larger and larger teams and budgets to make smaller and smaller incremental improvements. In just one year, the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project has achieved (through careful attention to building bridges between different mathematical disciplines) what many researchers in this area considered impossible or at least significantly farther off in the future; this experience must be replicated with further grants and fellowships to theoretically and foundationally minded researchers who are willing to undertake interdisciplinary work.</fr:p><fr:p>At the present time, my perception is that applied program verification is significantly more intelligible to funders and agencies because it speaks directly to the fears and concerns that we all have for our society in the age of software domination, artificial intelligence, and quantum computing; this is understandable, but it has regrettably led to the neglect of foundational research at the time when it is most urgent — it is now that we must lay the foundations for the next generation of program verifiers, before rather than after applied work in program verification reaches the hard limitations that more theoretically-oriented researchers have been working to remove. Therefore, I urge the European Commission and relevant policy makers to increase their consideration of foundational research as an investment in the future, alongside their continued funding of the very important applied direction in program semantics and verification.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12634</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-007B</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-007B.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Results beyond the state of the art">Results beyond the state of the art</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The results of the <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> project have gone significantly beyond the state of the art in denotational semantics for computational effects: not only is ours the first typed denotational model of higher-order store compatible with parametric polymorphism, but we have shown that the same construction also gives rise to a model of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022"
title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">full dependent type theory with higher-order store</fr:link> — a long sought-after result whose implications we have not yet fully exploited. Our model of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent.xml"
addr="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2024-univalent"
title="Towards univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</fr:link> is also a significant break with the state of the art, and points the way to a new and more fruitful interaction between the fields of programming languages on the one hand, and homotopy type theory and algebraic topology on the other hand.</fr:p><fr:p>The <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0077.xml"
addr="jms-0077"
title="Work performed and main achievements">technical achievements</fr:link> of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</fr:link> point to healthy growth in the long-neglected area of denotational semantics and equational program logics, but there is an urgent need for further research to bring these superior but comparatively less-developed methods to practical parity with the more established operational paradigm, which currently achieves stronger results in program verification — which we believe can be accounted for by the twenty-year headstart enjoyed by teams favoring operational methods during the relative dormancy of semantic and categorical methods in programming languages.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="Related">Related</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>12636</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-005T</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-005T.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:taxon>Bibliography</fr:taxon><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This page collects papers and dissertations about Synthetic Tait Computability, also known as the <fr:em>logical relations as types</fr:em> / LRAT principle; if you have written a paper or dissertation on this topic, please <fr:link
type="external"
href="mailto:jon@jonmsterling.com">write to me</fr:link> to have it added to this list.</fr:p>
  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11760</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#283</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-283.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Accepted papers">Accepted papers</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11762</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2023-grothendieck</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2023-grothendieck.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Towards a geometry for syntax">Towards a geometry for syntax</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>9</fr:month><fr:day>28</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.09497</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Invited contribution to the proceedings of the Chapman <fr:link
type="local"
href="chapman-grothendieck-2022.xml"
addr="chapman-grothendieck-2022"
title="Grothendieck Conference">Grothendieck Conference</fr:link>, to appear</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>It often happens that free algebras for a given theory satisfy useful reasoning principles that are not preserved under homomorphisms of algebras, and hence need not hold in an arbitrary algebra. For instance, if <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[M]]></fr:tex> is the free monoid on a set <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A]]></fr:tex>, then the scalar multiplication function <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A\times  M\to  M]]></fr:tex> is injective. Therefore, when reasoning in the formal theory of monoids under <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[A]]></fr:tex>, it is possible to use this injectivity law to make sound deductions even about monoids under A for which scalar multiplication is not injective — a principle known in algebra as the permanence of identity. Properties of this kind are of fundamental practical importance to the logicians and computer scientists who design and implement computerized proof assistants like Lean and Coq, as they enable the formal reductions of equational problems that make type checking tractable.</fr:p><fr:p>As type theories have become increasingly more sophisticated, it has become more and more difficult to establish the useful properties of their free models that facilitate effective implementation. These obstructions have facilitated a fruitful return to foundational work in type theory, which has taken on a more geometrical flavor than ever before. Here we expose a modern way to prove a highly non-trivial injectivity law for free models of Martin-Löf type theory, paying special attention to the ways that contemporary methods in type theory have been influenced by three important ideas of the Grothendieck school: the relative point of view, the language of universes, and the recollement of generalized spaces.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>

  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11764</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#284</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-284.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Refereed papers">Refereed papers</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11766</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">grodin-niu-sterling-harper-2024</fr:addr><fr:route>grodin-niu-sterling-harper-2024.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text=" decalf: a directed, effectful cost-aware logical framework"><![CDATA[ decalf]]>: a directed, effectful cost-aware logical framework</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2024</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>5</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="popl-2024.xml"
addr="popl-2024"
title="POPL ’24: 51st ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages"><fr:em>POPL ’24</fr:em>: 51st ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3632852</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05938</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@article{grodin-niu-sterling-harper-2024,
  author = {Grodin, Harrison and Niu, Yue and Sterling, Jonathan and Harper, Robert},
  title = {Decalf: A Directed, Effectful Cost-Aware Logical Framework},
  year = {2024},
  publisher = {Association for Computing Machinery},
  address = {New York, NY, USA},
  volume = {8},
  number = {POPL},
  doi = {10.1145/3632852},
  journal = {Proc. ACM Program. Lang.},
  month = {jan},
  articleno = {10},
  numpages = {29},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We present <fr:strong>decalf</fr:strong>, a <fr:strong>d</fr:strong>irected, <fr:strong>e</fr:strong>ffectful <fr:strong>c</fr:strong>ost-<fr:strong>a</fr:strong>ware <fr:strong>l</fr:strong>ogical <fr:strong>f</fr:strong>ramework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs with effects.  Like <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework"><fr:strong>calf</fr:strong></fr:link>, the language is based on a formal <fr:em>phase distinction</fr:em> between the <fr:em>extension</fr:em> and the <fr:em>intension</fr:em> of a program, its pure <fr:em>behavior</fr:em> as distinct from its <fr:em>cost</fr:em> measured by an effectful step-counting primitive. The type theory ensures that the behavior is unaffected by the cost accounting.  Unlike <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework"><fr:strong>calf</fr:strong></fr:link>, the present language takes account of <fr:em>effects</fr:em>, such as probabilistic choice and mutable state; this extension requires a reformulation of <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework"><fr:strong>calf</fr:strong></fr:link>’s approach to cost accounting: rather than rely on a “separable” notion of cost, here <fr:em>a cost bound is simply another program</fr:em>. To make this formal, we equip every type with an intrinsic preorder, relaxing the precise cost accounting intrinsic to a program to a looser but nevertheless informative estimate.  For example, the cost bound of a probabilistic program is itself a probabilistic program that specifies the distribution of costs.  This approach serves as a streamlined alternative to the standard method of isolating a recurrence that bounds the cost in a manner that readily extends to higher-order, effectful programs.</fr:p><fr:p>The development proceeds by first introducing the <fr:strong>decalf</fr:strong> type system, which is based on an intrinsic ordering among terms that restricts in the extensional phase to extensional equality, but in the intensional phase reflects an approximation of the cost of a program of interest.  This formulation is then applied to a number of illustrative examples, including pure and effectful sorting algorithms, simple probabilistic programs, and higher-order functions.  Finally, we justify <fr:strong>decalf</fr:strong> via a model in the topos of augmented simplicial sets.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11771</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">uemura-2023-fscd</fr:addr><fr:route>uemura-2023-fscd.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Homotopy type theory as internal languages of diagrams of ∞-logoses">Homotopy type theory as internal languages of diagrams of ∞-logoses</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>12</fr:month><fr:day>5</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="taichiuemura.xml"
addr="taichiuemura"
title="Taichi Uemura">Taichi Uemura</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@inproceedings{uemura-2023-fscd,
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  editor = {Gaboardi, Marco and van Raamsdonk, Femke},
  address = {Dagstuhl, Germany},
  publisher = {Schloss Dagstuhl -- Leibniz-Zentrum f\"{u}r Informatik},
  url = {https://drops.dagstuhl.de/opus/volltexte/2023/17989},
  booktitle = {8th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2023)},
  year = {2023},
  doi = {10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2023.5},
  isbn = {978-3-95977-277-8},
  issn = {1868-8969},
  pages = {5:1--5:19},
  series = {Leibniz International Proceedings in Informatics (LIPIcs)},
  title = {{Homotopy Type Theory as Internal Languages of Diagrams of $\infty$-Logoses}},
  volume = {260}
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2023.5</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">8th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2023)</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11773</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">niu-harper-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>niu-harper-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A metalanguage for cost-aware denotational semantics">A metalanguage for cost-aware denotational semantics</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>9</fr:month><fr:day>26</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2209.12669</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Thirty-Eighth Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on
Logic in Computer Science (LICS)</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@article{niu-harper-2022,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2209.12669},
  author = {Niu, Yue and Harper, Robert},
  title = {A metalanguage for cost-aware denotational semantics},
  publisher = {arXiv},
  year = {2022},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11776</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">gratzer-birkedal-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A stratified approach to Löb induction">A stratified approach to Löb induction</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>4</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@inproceedings{gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  editor = {Felty, Amy},
  address = {Dagstuhl, Germany},
  publisher = {Schloss Dagstuhl--Leibniz-Zentrum fuer Informatik},
  url = {https://jozefg.github.io/papers/a-stratified-approach-to-lob-induction.pdf},
  booktitle = {7th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2022)},
  year = {2022},
  month = aug,
  doi = {10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.23},
  series = {Leibniz International Proceedings in Informatics (LIPIcs)},
  title = {A Stratified Approach to {L\"{o}b} Induction},
  volume = {228},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.23</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD)</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11779</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">gratzer-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>gratzer-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for multimodal type theory">Normalization for multimodal type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>4</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@inproceedings{gratzer-2022,
  title = {Normalization for Multimodal Type Theory},
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel},
  address = {New York, NY, USA},
  publisher = {Association for Computing Machinery},
  booktitle = {Proceedings of the 37th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science},
  year = {2022},
  doi = {10.1145/3531130.3532398},
  url = {https://jozefg.github.io/papers/2022-normalization-for-multimodal-type-theory-short.pdf},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3531130.3532398</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Symposium on Logic and Computer Science (LICS)</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11781</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A cost-aware logical framework">A cost-aware logical framework</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="pacmpl.xml"
addr="pacmpl"
title="Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages">Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages</fr:link>, Volume 6, Issue POPL</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3498670</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We present calf, a cost-aware logical framework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs. Taking inspiration from recent work that reconstructs traditional aspects of programming languages in terms of a modal account of phase distinctions, we argue that the cost structure of programs motivates a phase distinction between intension and extension. Armed with this technology, we contribute a synthetic account of cost structure as a computational effect in which cost-aware programs enjoy an internal noninterference property: input/output behavior cannot depend on cost. As a full-spectrum dependent type theory, calf presents a unified language for programming and specification of both cost and behavior that can be integrated smoothly with existing mathematical libraries available in type theoretic proof assistants.</fr:p><fr:p>We evaluate calf as a general framework for cost analysis by implementing two fundamental techniques for algorithm analysis: the method of recurrence relations and physicist’s method for amortized analysis. We deploy these techniques on a variety of case studies: we prove a tight, closed bound for Euclid’s algorithm, verify the amortized complexity of batched queues, and derive tight, closed bounds for the sequential and parallel complexity of merge sort, all fully mechanized in the Agda proof assistant. Lastly we substantiate the soundness of quantitative reasoning in calf by means of a model construction.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11786</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-harper-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-harper-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.5</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-harper-2022.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">7th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2022)</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We propose a new sheaf semantics for secure information flow over a space of abstract behaviors, based on synthetic domain theory: security classes are open/closed partitions, types are sheaves, and redaction of sensitive information corresponds to restricting a sheaf to a closed subspace. Our security-aware computational model satisfies termination-insensitive noninterference automatically, and therefore constitutes an intrinsic alternative to state of the art extrinsic/relational models of noninterference. Our semantics is the latest application of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>’s recent re-interpretation of phase distinctions and noninterference in programming languages in terms of Artin gluing and topos-theoretic open/closed modalities. Prior applications include <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">parametricity for ML modules</fr:link>, the proof of normalization for cubical type theory by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-angiuli-2021"
title="Normalization for cubical type theory">Sterling and Angiuli</fr:link>, and the cost-aware logical framework of <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework">Niu et al</fr:link>. In this paper we employ the phase distinction perspective twice: first to reconstruct the syntax and semantics of secure information flow as a lattice of phase distinctions between “higher” and “lower” security, and second to verify the computational adequacy of our sheaf semantics with respect to a version of Abadi et al.’s dependency core calculus to which we have added a construct for declassifying termination channels.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>1405</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-005Y</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-005Y.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Minor mistakes in sheaf semantics of noninterference">Minor mistakes in <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2022"
title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">sheaf semantics of noninterference</fr:link></fr:title><fr:taxon>Erratum</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>In the published version of this paper, there were a few mistakes that have been corrected in the local copy hosted here.</fr:p><fr:ol><fr:li>In the <fr:em>Critique of relational semantics for information flow</fr:em>, our discussion of the <fr:em>Failure of monotonicity</fr:em> stated incorrectly that algebras for the sealing monad at a higher security level could not be transformed into algebras for the sealing monad at a lower security level in the semantics of Abadi et al. This is not true, as pointed out to us privately by Carlos Tomé Cortiñas. What we meant to say was that it is not the case that a type whose component at a high security level is trivial shall always remain trivial at a lower security level.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>The original version of the extended edition of this paper, we claimed that the constructive existence of tensor products on pointed dcpos was obvious; in fact, tensor products do exist, but their construction involves a reflexive coequalizer of pointed dcpos.</fr:li></fr:ol></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>1407</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-005Z</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-005Z.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Adequacy of sheaf semantics of noninterference">Adequacy of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2022"
title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">sheaf semantics of noninterference</fr:link></fr:title><fr:taxon>Erratum</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>7</fr:month><fr:day>17</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A serious (and as-yet unfixed) problem was discovered in July of 2023 by <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link>, which undermines the proof of adequacy given; in particular, the proof that the logical relation on free algebras is admissible is not correct. I believe there is a different proof of adequacy for the calculus described, but it will have a different structure from what currently appears in the paper. We thank <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link> for his attention to detail and careful reading of this paper.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11789</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-harper-2021</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-harper-2021.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>12</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-harper-2021.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="jacm.xml"
addr="jacm"
title="Journal of the ACM">Journal of the ACM</fr:link>, Volume 68, Issue 6</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1145/3474834</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The theory of program modules is of interest to language designers not only for its practical importance to programming, but also because it lies at the nexus of three fundamental concerns in language design: the <fr:em>phase distinction</fr:em>, <fr:em>computational effects</fr:em>, and <fr:em>type abstraction</fr:em>. We contribute a fresh “synthetic” take on program modules that treats modules as the fundamental constructs, in which the usual suspects of prior module calculi (kinds, constructors, dynamic programs) are rendered as derived notions in terms of a modal type-theoretic account of the phase distinction. We simplify the account of type abstraction (embodied in the generativity of module functors) through a <fr:em>lax modality</fr:em> that encapsulates computational effects, placing <fr:em>projectibility</fr:em> of module expressions on a type-theoretic basis.</fr:p><fr:p>Our main result is a (significant) proof-relevant and phase-sensitive generalization of the Reynolds abstraction theorem for a calculus of program modules, based on a new kind of logical relation called a <fr:em>parametricity structure</fr:em>. Parametricity structures generalize the proof-irrelevant relations of classical parametricity to proof-<fr:em>relevant</fr:em> families, where there may be non-trivial evidence witnessing the relatedness of two programs—simplifying the metatheory of strong sums over the collection of types, for although there can be no “relation classifying relations,” one easily accommodates a “family classifying small families.”</fr:p><fr:p>Using the insight that logical relations/parametricity is itself a form of phase distinction between the syntactic and the semantic, we contribute a new synthetic approach to phase separated parametricity based on the slogan <fr:em>logical relations as types</fr:em>, by iterating our modal account of the phase distinction. We axiomatize a dependent type theory of parametricity structures using two pairs of complementary modalities (syntactic, semantic) and (static, dynamic), substantiated using the topos theoretic <fr:em>Artin gluing</fr:em> construction. Then, to construct a simulation between two implementations of an abstract type, one simply programs a third implementation whose type component carries the representation invariant.</fr:p><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>1412</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-0060</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0060.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Minor mistakes in logical relations as types">Minor mistakes in <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">logical relations as types</fr:link></fr:title><fr:taxon>Erratum</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>After going to press, we have fixed the following mistakes:</fr:p><fr:ol><fr:li>In the definition of a logos, we mistakenly said that "colimits commute with finite limits" but we meant to say that they are preserved by pullback. We thank <fr:link
type="local"
href="sarahzrf.xml"
addr="sarahzrf"
title="Sarah Z. Rovner-Frydman">Sarah Z. Rovner-Frydman</fr:link> for noticing this mistake.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>In Remark 5.15, we used the notation for the closed immersion prior to introducing it.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>We have fixed a few broken links in the bibliography.</fr:li></fr:ol><fr:p>The local copy hosted here has the corrections implemented</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11792</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-angiuli-2021</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-angiuli-2021.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for cubical type theory">Normalization for cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>7</fr:month><fr:day>7</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="carloangiuli.xml"
addr="carloangiuli"
title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">2021 36th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science (LICS)</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1109/LICS52264.2021.9470719</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.11479</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We prove normalization for (univalent, Cartesian) cubical type theory, closing the last major open problem in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory. Our normalization result is reduction-free, in the sense of yielding a bijection between equivalence classes of terms in context and a tractable language of <fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\beta ]]></fr:tex>/<fr:tex
display="inline"><![CDATA[\eta ]]></fr:tex>-normal forms. As corollaries we obtain both decidability of judgmental equality and the injectivity of type constructors.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>

  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11795</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#285</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-285.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Manuscripts">Manuscripts</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11797</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">huang-2023</fr:addr><fr:route>huang-2023.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Synthetic Tait computability the hard way">Synthetic Tait computability the hard way</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>10</fr:month><fr:day>3</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="treborhuang.xml"
addr="treborhuang"
title="Trebor Huang">Trebor Huang</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2310.02051</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We walk through a few proofs of canonicity and normalization, each one with more aspects dissected and re-expressed in category theory, so that readers can compare the difference across proofs. During this process we isolate the different ideas that make up the proofs. Finally we arrive at <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">synthetic Tait computability</fr:link> as proposed by <fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">J. Sterling</fr:link>. We also give a synthetic proof for parametricity of system F.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11799</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">uemura-2022-coh</fr:addr><fr:route>uemura-2022-coh.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization and coherence for ∞-type theories">Normalization and coherence for ∞-type theories</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>12</fr:month><fr:day>22</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="taichiuemura.xml"
addr="taichiuemura"
title="Taichi Uemura">Taichi Uemura</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@unpublished{uemura-2022-coh,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2212.11764},
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  title = {Normalization and coherence for $\infty$-type theories},
  publisher = {arXiv},
  year = {2022},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2212.11764</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11801</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Controlling unfolding in type theory">Controlling unfolding in type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>10</fr:month><fr:day>10</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="carloangiuli.xml"
addr="carloangiuli"
title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="thierrycoquand.xml"
addr="thierrycoquand"
title="Thierry Coquand">Thierry Coquand</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.05420</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@unpublished{gratzer-sterling-angiuli-coquand-birkedal-2022,
  doi = {10.48550/ARXIV.2210.05420},
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel and Sterling, Jonathan and Angiuli, Carlo and Coquand, Thierry and Birkedal, Lars},
  title = {Controlling unfolding in type theory},
  year = {2022},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript}
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We present a novel mechanism for controlling the unfolding of definitions in
dependent type theory. Traditionally, proof assistants let users specify
whether each definition can or cannot be unfolded in the remainder of a
development; unfolding definitions is often necessary in order to reason about
them, but an excess of unfolding can result in brittle proofs and intractably
large proof goals. In our system, definitions are by default not unfolded, but
users can selectively unfold them in a local manner. We justify our mechanism
by means of elaboration to a core type theory with <fr:em>extension types</fr:em>, a
connective first introduced in the context of homotopy type theory.  We prove a
normalization theorem for our core calculus and have implemented our system in
the cooltt proof assistant, providing both theoretical and practical evidence
for it.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11807</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>10</fr:month><fr:day>6</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on <fr:em>recursively defined semantic worlds</fr:em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational reasoning based on the <fr:em>logical relations as types</fr:em> principle, in which equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value adjunction with higher-order store, improving on <fr:link
type="local"
href="paulblainlevy.xml"
addr="paulblainlevy"
title="Paul Blain Levy">Levy</fr:link>'s possible worlds model construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <fr:em>synthetic guarded domain theory</fr:em>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11811</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2022-naive</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2022-naive.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability">Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@unpublished{sterling-2022-naive,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  year = {2022},
  month = jun,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Na\"{i}ve logical relations in synthetic {Tait} computability},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-2022-naive.pdf</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <fr:em>positive</fr:em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <fr:em>non-syntactic</fr:em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <fr:em>Naïve Set Theory</fr:em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <fr:em>synthetic Tait computability</fr:em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11813</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">gratzer-2021-crisp-induction</fr:addr><fr:route>gratzer-2021-crisp-induction.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Crisp induction for intensional identity types">Crisp induction for intensional identity types</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="external">https://jozefg.github.io/papers/crisp-induction-for-intensional-identity-types.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@unpublished{gratzer-2021-crisp-induction,
  author = {Gratzer, Daniel},
  url = {https://jozefg.github.io/papers/crisp-induction-for-intensional-identity-types.pdf},
  year = {2021},
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Crisp induction for intensional identity types},
}]]></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>

  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11815</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#286</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-286.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Dissertations">Dissertations</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11817</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">gratzer-2023-thesis</fr:addr><fr:route>gratzer-2023-thesis.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Syntax and semantics of modal type theory">Syntax and semantics of modal type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>29</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="danielgratzer.xml"
addr="danielgratzer"
title="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">PhD Dissertation, <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GC.xml"
addr="jms-00GC"
title="Aarhus University">Aarhus University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">https://iris-project.org/pdfs/2023-phd-gratzer.pdf</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>One idiosyncratic framing of type theory is as the study of operations invariant under substitution. Modal type theory, by contrast, concerns the controlled integration of operations—modalities—into type theory which violate this discipline, so-called <fr:em>non-fibered connectives</fr:em>. Modal type theory is therefore built around a fundamental tension: the desire to include modalities and powerful principles for reasoning with them on one hand, and the need to maintain the conveniences and character of Martin-Löf type theory which stem from substitution invariance.</fr:p><fr:p>In this thesis, we thoroughly explore and discuss this contradiction. We discuss several different formulations of modal type theory, explore their various syntactic properties, and relate them through their categorical semantics. In particular, we show that most modal type theories that have arisen in the last two decades can be understood through the abstraction of <fr:em>weak dependent right adjoints</fr:em>. We also put forward a new <fr:em>general</fr:em> modal type theory, MTT, based on this abstraction.</fr:p><fr:p>The generality of MTT means that, without any additional work, it can be specialized to an arbitrary collection of type theories related by modalities and natural transformations between them. It is therefore easy to obtain a type theory for a comonad, an adjunction, a local topos, or any other number of complex and realistic scenarios. In addition to showing that many modal type theories are closely related to specific instantiations of MTT, we thoroughly explore the syntax and semantics of MTT itself. We prove that MTT enjoys an unconditional normalization result and decidable type-checking under mild assumptions. We show how MTT may be interpreted into a wide variety of structured categories and use this to study the expressive power of the type theory and various extensions thereof.</fr:p><fr:p>Finally, we explore several concrete applications of MTT in the context of guarded type theory and guarded denotational semantics. We propose a highly usable language for guarded recursion and explore its particular models and metatheorems. We show a relatively sharp result bounding the extent to which classical guarded recursion can be added to any type theory with decidable type-checking and propose a system to mitigate this issue. Finally, we conduct an in-depth case study using guarded MTT to obtain a fully synthetic account of the Iris program logic, proving adequacy in a fully internal manner.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11819</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-thesis</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-thesis.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>9</fr:month><fr:day>13</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Doctoral dissertation, <fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">papers/sterling-2021-thesis.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@phdthesis{sterling-2021-thesis,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  school = {Carnegie Mellon University},
  year = {2021},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.6990769},
  note = {Version 1.1, revised May 2022},
  number = {CMU-CS-21-142},
  title = {First Steps in Synthetic {Tait} Computability: The Objective Metatheory of Cubical Type Theory},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="doi">10.5281/zenodo.6990769</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The implementation and semantics of dependent type theories can be studied in a syntax-independent way: the objective metatheory of dependent type theories exploits the universal properties of their syntactic categories to endow them with computational content, mathematical meaning, and practical implementation (normalization, type checking, elaboration). The semantic methods of the objective metatheory inform the design and implementation of correct-by-construction elaboration algorithms, promising a principled interface between real proof assistants and ideal mathematics.</fr:p><fr:p>In this dissertation, I add synthetic Tait computability to the arsenal of the objective metatheorist. Synthetic Tait computability is a mathematical machine to reduce difficult problems of type theory and programming languages to trivial theorems of topos theory. First employed by <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</fr:link> to reconstruct the theory of program modules and their phase separated parametricity, synthetic Tait computability is deployed here to resolve the last major open question in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory: normalization of open terms.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>

  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11821</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#287</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-287.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Technical reports">Technical reports</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p><fr:info>Query returned no results</fr:info></fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>

  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11823</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#288</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-288.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Presentations">Presentations</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11825</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">harper-2023-calco-mfps</fr:addr><fr:route>harper-2023-calco-mfps.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Integrating cost and behavior in type theory">Integrating cost and behavior in type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>21</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~rwh/talks/calco-mfps-2023.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"> Plenary invited lecture for CALCO/MFPS 2023</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Joint work with <fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:link> (Carnegie Mellon), <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link> (Carnegie Mellon), and <fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link> (Cambridge).</fr:p><fr:p>The computational view of intuitionistic dependent type theory is as an intrinsic logic of (functional) programs in which types are viewed as specifications of their behavior. Equational reasoning is particularly relevant in the functional case, where correctness can be formulated as equality between two implementations of the same behavior. Besides behavior, it is also important to specify and verify the cost of programs, measured in terms of their resource usage, with respect to both sequential and parallel evaluation. Although program cost can—and has been—verified in type theory using an extrinsic formulation of programs as data objects, what we seek here is, instead, an intrinsic account within type theory itself.</fr:p><fr:p>In this talk we discuss Calf, the <fr:link
type="local"
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022"
title="A cost-aware logical framework">Cost-Aware Logical Framework</fr:link>, which is an extension of dependent call-by-push-value type theory that provides an intrinsic account of both parallel and sequential resource usage for a variety of problem-specific measures of cost. Thus, for example, it is possible to prove that insertion sort and merge sort are equal as regards behavior, but differ in terms of the number of comparisons required to achieve the same results. But how can equal functions have different cost? To provide an intrinsic account of both intensional and extensional properties of programs, we make use of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">Sterling's notion of Synthetic Tait Computability</fr:link>, a generalization of Tait's method originally developed for the study of higher type theory. In STC the concept of a “phase” plays a central role: originally as the distinction between the syntactic and semantic aspects of a computability structure, but more recently applied to the formulation of type theories for program modules and for information flow properties of programs. In Calf we distinguish two phases, the intensional and extensional, which differ as regards the significance of cost accounting—extensionally it is neglected, intensionally it is of paramount importance. Thus, in the extensional phase insertion sort and merge sort are equal, but in the intensional phase they are distinct, and indeed one is proved to have optimal behavior as regards comparisons, and the other not. Importantly, both phases are needed in a cost verification—the proof of the complexity of an algorithm usually relies on aspects of its correctness.</fr:p><fr:p>We will provide an overview of Calf itself, and of its application in the verification of the cost and behavior of a variety of programs. So far we have been able to verify cost bounds on Euclid's Algorithm, amortized bounds on batched queues, parallel cost bounds on a joinable form of red-black trees, and the equivalence and cost of the aforementioned sorting methods. In a <fr:link
type="local"
href="grodin-harper-2023-calco.xml"
addr="grodin-harper-2023-calco"
title="Amortized analysis via coinduction">companion paper</fr:link> at this meeting <fr:link
type="local"
href="harrisongrodin.xml"
addr="harrisongrodin"
title="Harrison Grodin">Grodin</fr:link> and I develop an account of amortization that relates the standard inductive view of instruction sequences with the coinductive view of data structures characterized by the same operations. In ongoing work we are extending the base of verified deterministic algorithms to those taught in the undergraduate parallel algorithms course at Carnegie Mellon, and are extending Calf itself to account for probabilistic methods, which are also used in that course.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11827</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">uemura-2022-hott-uf</fr:addr><fr:route>uemura-2022-hott-uf.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Internal languages of diagrams of ∞-toposes">Internal languages of diagrams of ∞-toposes</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>7</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="taichiuemura.xml"
addr="taichiuemura"
title="Taichi Uemura">Taichi Uemura</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@misc{uemura-2022-hott-uf,
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  year = {2022},
  month = july,
  note = {Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations},
  title = {Internal languages of diagrams of $\infty$-toposes},
  url = {https://hott-uf.github.io/2022/uemura-hott-uf-2022-notes.pdf}
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11829</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-hott-uf</fr:addr><fr:route>weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-hott-uf.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Towards normalization of simplicial type theory via synthetic Tait computability">Towards normalization of simplicial type theory via synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>7</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonathanweinberger.xml"
addr="jonathanweinberger"
title="Jonathan Weinberger">Jonathan Weinberger</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="benediktahrens.xml"
addr="benediktahrens"
title="Benedikt Ahrens">Benedikt Ahrens</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="ulrikbuchholtz.xml"
addr="ulrikbuchholtz"
title="Ulrik Buchholtz">Ulrik Buchholtz</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="paigenorth.xml"
addr="paigenorth"
title="Paige Randall North">Paige Randall North</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@misc{weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-hott-uf,
  author = {Weinberger, Jonathan and Ahrens, Benedikt and Buchholtz, Ulrik and North, Paige},
  year = {2022},
  month = july,
  note = {Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations},
  title = {Towards Normalization of Simplicial Type Theory via Synthetic Tait Computability},
  url = {https://hott-uf.github.io/2022/HoTTUF_2022_paper_6.pdf}
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="video">https://www.dropbox.com/s/6dhiqiaemzmewm1/weinberger_HoTTUF22_SSTC.mp4?dl=0</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory / Univalent Foundations</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11834</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2022-muri</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2022-muri.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>30</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@misc{sterling-harper-2022-muri,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Harper, Robert},
  url = {slides/sterling:2022:muri.pdf},
  year = {2022},
  month = jun,
  note = {Talk given at the 2022 MURI Team Meeting},
  title = {Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-2022-muri.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">MURI Team Meeting 2022</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11837</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jms-005Z</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-005Z.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Adequacy of sheaf semantics of noninterference">Adequacy of <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2022"
title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">sheaf semantics of noninterference</fr:link></fr:title><fr:taxon>Erratum</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>7</fr:month><fr:day>17</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A serious (and as-yet unfixed) problem was discovered in July of 2023 by <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link>, which undermines the proof of adequacy given; in particular, the proof that the logical relation on free algebras is admissible is not correct. I believe there is a different proof of adequacy for the calculus described, but it will have a different structure from what currently appears in the paper. We thank <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link> for his attention to detail and careful reading of this paper.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11839</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-types</fr:addr><fr:route>weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-types.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Synthetic Tait computability for simplicial type theory">Synthetic Tait computability for simplicial type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonathanweinberger.xml"
addr="jonathanweinberger"
title="Jonathan Weinberger">Jonathan Weinberger</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="benediktahrens.xml"
addr="benediktahrens"
title="Benedikt Ahrens">Benedikt Ahrens</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="ulrikbuchholtz.xml"
addr="ulrikbuchholtz"
title="Ulrik Buchholtz">Ulrik Buchholtz</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="paigenorth.xml"
addr="paigenorth"
title="Paige Randall North">Paige Randall North</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@inproceedings{weinberger-ahrens-buchholtz-north-2022-types,
  author = {Weinberger, Jonathan and Ahrens, Benedikt and Buchholtz, Ulrik and North, Paige},
  booktitle = {28th International Conference on Types for Proofs and Programs (TYPES 2022)},
  year = {2022},
  title = {Synthetic {Tait} Computability for Simplicial Type Theory},
  url = {https://types22.inria.fr/files/2022/06/TYPES_2022_paper_17.pdf}
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jX76Kv-E_ls</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">28th International Conference on Types for Proofs and Programs</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11844</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">uemura-2022-wg6</fr:addr><fr:route>uemura-2022-wg6.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for initial space-valued models of type theories">Normalization for initial space-valued models of type theories</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>5</fr:month><fr:day>21</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="taichiuemura.xml"
addr="taichiuemura"
title="Taichi Uemura">Taichi Uemura</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@misc{uemura-2022-wg6,
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  year = {2022},
  month = may,
  note = {WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories},
  title = {Normalization for initial space-valued models of type theories},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11846</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2022-wg6</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2022-wg6.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability">Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>5</fr:month><fr:day>20</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@misc{sterling-2022-wg6,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  year = {2022},
  month = may,
  note = {WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories (Invited Talk)},
  title = {Na\"{i}ve logical relations in synthetic {Tait} computability},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <fr:em>positive</fr:em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <fr:em>non-syntactic</fr:em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <fr:em>Naïve Set Theory</fr:em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <fr:em>synthetic Tait computability</fr:em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11848</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-muri</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-muri.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for (Cartesian) cubical type theory">Normalization for (Cartesian) cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>10</fr:month><fr:day>15</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-2021-muri.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">MURI Team Meeting 2021</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11850</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-harper-2021-mlw</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-harper-2021-mlw.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="A metalanguage for multi-phase modularity">A metalanguage for multi-phase modularity</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@unpublished{sterling-harper-2021-mlw,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Harper, Robert},
  url = {https://icfp21.sigplan.org/details/mlfamilyworkshop-2021-papers/5/A-metalanguage-for-multi-phase-modularity},
  year = {2021},
  month = aug,
  note = {ML 2021 abstract and talk},
  title = {A metalanguage for multi-phase modularity},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-harper-2021-mlw.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5kWS-umBA7k</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">ML Family Workshop</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Type abstraction, the phase distinction, and computational effects all play an important role in the design and implementation of ML-style module systems. We propose a simple type theoretic metalanguage <fr:strong>φML</fr:strong> for multi-phase modularity in which these concepts are treated individually, supporting the definition of high-level modular constructs such as generative and applicative functors, as well as all extant forms of structure sharing.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11853</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-angiuli-2021-ct</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-angiuli-2021-ct.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for cubical type theory">Normalization for cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="carloangiuli.xml"
addr="carloangiuli"
title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-angiuli-2021-ct.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AhivFjnBakE</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Category Theory 2021</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>


  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11856</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#289</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-289.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Seminar talks">Seminar talks</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11858</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2022-pps</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2022-pps.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability">Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>9</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Proofs, Programs and Systems seminar (IRIF PPS)</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <fr:em>positive</fr:em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <fr:em>non-syntactic</fr:em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <fr:em>Naïve Set Theory</fr:em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <fr:em>synthetic Tait computability</fr:em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11860</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2022-bu-popv</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2022-bu-popv.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Intrinsic semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">Intrinsic semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>4</fr:month><fr:day>26</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-2022-bu-popv.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Boston University POPV Seminar</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Security-typed programming languages aim to control the flow of high-security information to low security clients. Starting with Abadi et al.'s dependency core calculus, the denotational semantics of such languages has been dominated by an <fr:strong>extrinsic</fr:strong> approach in which an existing insecure model of computation (e.g. ordinary domains) is restricted by a logical relation of "indistinguishability" to prevent low-security outputs from depending on high-security inputs (noninterference). Thus in the extrinsic approach, security properties are bolted onto an insecure model by brute force, as it were. A more refined information flow policy called termination-insensitive noninterference allows high-security bits to be leaked through termination channels but not through return values; unfortunately, the adaptation of the extrinsic/relational semantics to this more relaxed policy is incompatible with the transitivity of the logical relation, contradicting the intuition of "indistinguishability".</fr:p><fr:p>In contrast, an <fr:strong>intrinsic</fr:strong> semantics of security typing would involve a new computational model that evinces secure information flow and noninterference properties directly without any post hoc restriction by a logical relation. We contribute the first such intrinsic semantics of security typing in this sense by considering sheaves of dcpos on a space of abstract behaviors on which security classes arise as open/closed partitions; the security monads then arise as the <fr:em>closed modalities</fr:em> of topos theory that restrict a sheaf to its component over a closed subspace.</fr:p><fr:p>An advantage of our intrinsic semantics is that termination-insensitive noninterference arises automatically from our computational model, namely the fact that the Sierpiński domain is not a constant sheaf; a further advantage is that our semantics is an instance of standard domain theoretic denotational semantics, albeit over a richer category of domains.</fr:p><fr:p>(j.w.w. <fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">R. Harper</fr:link>)</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11862</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">harper-2021-topos-institute</fr:addr><fr:route>harper-2021-topos-institute.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Phase distinctions in type theory">Phase distinctions in type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>12</fr:month><fr:day>9</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7DYkyB1Rm3I</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="toposinstitute.xml"
addr="toposinstitute"
title="Topos Institute">Topos Institute</fr:link> Colloquium</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>(Joint work with <fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="yueniu.xml"
addr="yueniu"
title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:link>)</fr:p><fr:p>The informal phase distinction between compile-time and run-time in programming languages is formally manifested by the distinction between kinds, which classify types, and types, which classify code. The distinction underpins standard programming methodology whereby code is first type-checked for consistency before being compiled for execution. When used effectively, types help eliminate bugs before they occur.</fr:p><fr:p>Program modules, in even the most rudimentary form, threaten the distinction, comprising as they do both types and programs in a single unit. Matters worsen when considerating “open” modules, with free module variables standing for its imports. To maintain the separation in their presence it is necessary to limit the dependency of types, the static parts of a module, to their imported types. Such restrictions are fundamental for using dependent types to express modular structure, as originally suggested by MacQueen.</fr:p><fr:p>To address this question <fr:link
type="local"
href="moggi-1989.xml"
addr="moggi-1989"
title="A category-theoretic account of program modules">Moggi</fr:link> gave an “analytic” formulation of program modules in which modules are explicitly separated into their static and dynamic components using tools from category theory. Recent work by Dreyer, Rossberg, and Russo develops this approach fully in their account of ML-like module systems. In this talk we consider instead a “synthetic” formulation using a proposition to segregate the static from the dynamic, in particular to define static equivalence to manage type sharing and type dependency.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11864</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-ccl</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-ccl.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Towards a geometry for syntax">Towards a geometry for syntax</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>11</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-2021-ccl.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
type="local"
href="camcl.xml"
addr="camcl"
title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory">Cambridge Computer Laboratory</fr:link></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The purpose of this talk is to pose the question, “What are the Euclid’s postulates for syntactic metatheory?”</fr:p><fr:p>In the fourth century B.C.E., the Greek mathematician Euclid set down his famous postulates for plane geometry, explaining geometric shapes in terms of rules that govern their construction and incidence. The dialectical relationship between theories (axioms) and their models (coordinate systems) has been the driving force in the last two millennia of geometrical investigation.</fr:p><fr:p>In logic and computer science, workers in the “syntactic metatheory” investigate questions that lie on the fringe between a theory and its models — definability, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, parametricity, type safety, etc. Dominant methods attack these questions by means of explicit computations (e.g. Kripke logical relations) which practitioners have found to be both reliable and somewhat opaque. In this talk, I introduce <fr:em>Synthetic Tait computability</fr:em> — a new system of axioms that transforms these explicit computations into synthetic manipulations; classical Kripke logical relations can be seen as models or “coordinate systems” for the new geometry of syntax that is beginning to unfold.</fr:p><fr:p>Synthetic Tait computability has already been employed to positively resolve the normalization and decidability conjectures for cubical type theory, as well as a number of other recent results.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11866</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-logsem</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-logsem.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Between abstraction and composition...">Between abstraction and composition...</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>11</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-2021-logsem.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">Logic and Semantics Seminar, <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GC.xml"
addr="jms-00GC"
title="Aarhus University">Aarhus University</fr:link></fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The fundamental contradiction of programming and program verification can be located in the tension between abstraction and composition. We make programs more abstract in order to prevent bad interactions between components; on the other side of the coin, we impede the composition of components when we abstract them. Modern programming practice evinces many distinct levels of abstraction that must be considered at the same time — for instance, compilers break module boundaries during linking, complexity analysis breaks the abstraction of extensional equivalence, and logical relations proofs break the abstraction of closure under substitution. What is needed to meet this challenge is linguistic tools that smoothly interpolate between these different levels of abstraction. Building on <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis"
title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">my doctoral dissertation</fr:link> and <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">joint work with Bob Harper</fr:link>, I introduce a new plan for modal programming languages and logics that treat the transition between different abstraction levels as a first-class notion.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11868</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-cmu-ss</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-cmu-ss.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Abstraction, composition, and the phase distinction">Abstraction, composition, and the phase distinction</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>8</fr:month><fr:day>24</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-2021-cmu-ss.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">CMU Speakers Club</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Programmers use abstraction to hide representation details from ourselves: either to avoid mistakes (e.g. confusing a list index with a length) or to exploit representation invariants (e.g. two implementations of the QUEUE interface are indistinguishable). These abstraction boundaries can unfortunately impede the linking of smaller program units into efficient composite programs, because compilers must exploit representation details in order to produce efficient code.  Sometimes seen as the "waterloo of separate compilation", the need to break abstraction is answered by whole-program analysis techniques that break all abstractions (as in the MLton compiler for Standard ML). Separate compilation, however, has a number of advantages including speed, parallelization, and elegance.</fr:p><fr:p>We present an alternative type theoretic account of abstraction-breaking during compilation based on the famous phase distinction of ML languages; rather than distinguishing between compiletime and runtime, we focus on separating "devtime" from compiletime. Our framework allows the programmer to selectively reveal representation details to the compiler without giving up the representation independence properties guaranteed by "devtime" type correctness.  We also describe an application to the problem of printf-debugging, which is ordinarily obstructed by abstraction.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11870</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-angiuli-2021-padova</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-angiuli-2021-padova.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for cubical type theory">Normalization for cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>5</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="carloangiuli.xml"
addr="carloangiuli"
title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Padova Logic Seminar</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We prove normalization for (univalent, Cartesian) cubical type theory, closing the last major open problem in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory. The main difficulty in comparison to conventional type theory is located in a new feature of cubical type theories, the absence of a stable notion of neutral term: for instance, the path application <fr:code>(p @ i)</fr:code> ceases to be neutral within its “locus of instability” <fr:code>∂(i)</fr:code> and must compute to an endpoint. We introduce a new, geometrically-inspired generalization of the notion of neutral term, stabilizing neutrals by gluing them together with partial computability data along their loci of instability — when the locus of instability is nowhere, a stabilized neutral is a conventional neutral, and when the locus of instability is everywhere, a stabilized neutral is just computability data. Our normalization result is based on a reduction-free Artin gluing argument, and yields an injective function from equivalence classes of terms in context to a tractable language of beta/eta-normal forms. As corollaries we obtain both decidability of judgmental equality, as well as injectivity of type constructors in contexts formed by assuming variables <fr:code>x : A</fr:code> and dimensions <fr:code>i : 𝕀</fr:code>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11873</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-au-ccs</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-au-ccs.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Logical relations as types">Logical relations as types</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>4</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="slides">slides/sterling-2021-au-ccs.pdf</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AEthjg2k718</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">CCS Colloquium, Augusta University</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p><fr:em>This is joint work with <fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link>.</fr:em></fr:p><fr:p>How do you prove that two implementations of an abstract type behave the same in all configurations? Reynolds famously employed logical relations to establish such results; roughly, a logical relation is a structure-respecting relation between two interpretations of a theory that evinces, in the base case, a desirable invariant.</fr:p><fr:p>We present a synthetic way to understand and interact with logical relations, related to classical logical relations in the same way that Euclidean geometry relates to point-sets. Previously a logical relation was defined in terms of the (complicated) details of how it is constructed as a certain kind of relation over syntax. We instead take the simpler view that everything in sight is a logical relation, and then use modalities to isolate those logical relations that are degenerate in either the syntactic or the semantic direction.</fr:p><fr:p>Our “logical relations as types” principle has led to a new account of modules and representation independence <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-harper-2021"
title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">(S., Harper)</fr:link>, as well as the first proofs of normalization for cubical type theory <fr:link
type="local"
href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml"
addr="sterling-angiuli-2021"
title="Normalization for cubical type theory">(S., Angiuli)</fr:link> and general multi-modal dependent type theory <fr:link
type="local"
href="gratzer-2022.xml"
addr="gratzer-2022"
title="Normalization for multimodal type theory">(Gratzer)</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11875</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2021-cmu-hott</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2021-cmu-hott.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Normalization for cubical type theory">Normalization for cubical type theory</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>2</fr:month></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="carloangiuli.xml"
addr="carloangiuli"
title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Pittsburgh's HoTT Seminar</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>We prove normalization for (univalent, Cartesian) cubical type theory, closing the last major open problem in the syntactic metatheory of cubical type theory. The main difficulty in comparison to conventional type theory is located in a new feature of cubical type theories, the absence of a stable notion of neutral term: for instance, the path application p(i) ceases to be neutral within its “locus of instability” ∂(i) and must compute to an endpoint. We introduce a new, geometrically-inspired generalization of the notion of neutral term, stabilizing neutrals by gluing them together with partial computability data along their loci of instability — when the locus of instability is nowhere, a stabilized neutral is a conventional neutral, and when the locus of instability is everywhere, a stabilized neutral is just computability data. Our normalization result is based on a reduction-free Artin gluing argument, and yields an injective function from equivalence classes of terms in context to a tractable language of beta/eta-normal forms. As corollaries we obtain both decidability of judgmental equality, as well as injectivity of type constructors in contexts formed by assuming variables x : A and dimensions i : 𝕀.</fr:p><fr:p>(j.w.w. <fr:link
type="local"
href="carloangiuli.xml"
addr="carloangiuli"
title="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:link>.)</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>

  <fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11878</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="machine">#290</fr:addr><fr:route>unstable-290.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Roladex">Roladex</fr:title><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11880</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">carloangiuli</fr:addr><fr:route>carloangiuli.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Carlo Angiuli">Carlo Angiuli</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">https://carloangiuli.com/</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution">Indiana University</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">Assistant Professor</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="postdoc-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0002-9590-3303</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11881</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">danielgratzer</fr:addr><fr:route>danielgratzer.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Daniel Gratzer">Daniel Gratzer</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">http://www.danielgratzer.com/</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GC.xml"
addr="jms-00GC"
title="Aarhus University">Aarhus University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">PhD Student</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">larsbirkedal</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0003-1944-0789</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:blockquote>I study programming languages, type theories, and logics. I am particularly interested in applying semantic methods to prove syntactic properties of modal type theories and programming languages. I am also involved in the development of program logics for concurrent programming languages through the <fr:link
type="external"
href="https://iris-project.org/">Iris project</fr:link>.</fr:blockquote></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11882</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">harrisongrodin</fr:addr><fr:route>harrisongrodin.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Harrison Grodin">Harrison Grodin</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">https://www.harrisongrodin.com/</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">PhD Student</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0002-0947-3520</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11883</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">jonmsterling</fr:addr><fr:route>jonmsterling.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="camcl.xml"
addr="camcl"
title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory">Cambridge Computer Laboratory</fr:link>; <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GP.xml"
addr="jms-00GP"
title="Clare College">Clare College</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0002-0585-5564</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">Associate Professor</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="postdoc-advisor">larsbirkedal</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Associate Professor in Logical Foundations and Formal Methods at University of Cambridge. Formerly a <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-0061.xml"
addr="jms-0061"
title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">Marie Skłodowska-Curie Postdoctoral Fellow</fr:link> hosted at <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GC.xml"
addr="jms-00GC"
title="Aarhus University">Aarhus University</fr:link> by <fr:link
type="local"
href="larsbirkedal.xml"
addr="larsbirkedal"
title="Lars Birkedal">Lars Birkedal</fr:link>, and before this a PhD student of <fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link>.</fr:p><fr:p>I am a Bye-Fellow of <fr:link
type="local"
href="jms-00GP.xml"
addr="jms-00GP"
title="Clare College">Clare College</fr:link> from February 2024, and have been elected a Fellow for the coming year.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11884</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">robertharper</fr:addr><fr:route>robertharper.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">Professor</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0002-9400-2941</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="external">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~rwh</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11885</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">taichiuemura</fr:addr><fr:route>taichiuemura.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Taichi Uemura">Taichi Uemura</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="external">https://uemurax.github.io/</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution">Stockholm University</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="position">Postdoc</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0003-4930-1384</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:blockquote>I am a postdoc at the Department of Mathematics at Stockholm University. My main research interests are in <fr:link
type="local"
href="hottbook.xml"
addr="hottbook"
title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">Homotopy Type Theory</fr:link>, in particular its semantics using (higher) category theory. I am also interested in type theory in general and pure category theory.</fr:blockquote></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>11886</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">yueniu</fr:addr><fr:route>yueniu.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</fr:title><fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon><fr:authors /><fr:meta
name="position">PhD Student</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="phd-advisor">robertharper</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="institution"><fr:link
type="local"
href="cmu.xml"
addr="cmu"
title="Carnegie Mellon University">Carnegie Mellon University</fr:link></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="orcid">0000-0003-4888-6042</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>PhD student of <fr:link
type="local"
href="robertharper.xml"
addr="robertharper"
title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>
</fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>