<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Changelog"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>jms-005V</addr>  <route>jms-005V.xml</route> <date>July 17, 2023</date>  <title>Forester 2.2</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This major release adds support for generating subsections from transclusions obtained by a query; this can be used to produce topical bibliographies. For example, the following code will generate a subsection entitled “featured talks” containing the appropriate items as collapsed subtrees:</p><code><pre>\query{featured talks}{
  \query/and{
    \query/author{jonmsterling}
    \query/taxon{reference}
    \query/tag{featured}
  }
}
</pre></code>As always, existing forests can be upgraded by copying <code>forest.xsl</code> and <code>style.css</code> into their <code>assets</code> directory. 
</mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail/> <addr>jms-005P</addr>  <route>jms-005P.xml</route> <date>June 1, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Forester</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A tool for tending <link href="tfmt-000V.xml" type="local">forests of evergreen notes</link>.</p><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Changelog"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <addr>jms-005V</addr>  <route>jms-005V.xml</route> <date>July 17, 2023</date>  <title>Forester 2.2</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This major release adds support for generating subsections from transclusions obtained by a query; this can be used to produce topical bibliographies. For example, the following code will generate a subsection entitled “featured talks” containing the appropriate items as collapsed subtrees:</p><code><pre>\query{featured talks}{
  \query/and{
    \query/author{jonmsterling}
    \query/taxon{reference}
    \query/tag{featured}
  }
}
</pre></code>As always, existing forests can be upgraded by copying <code>forest.xsl</code> and <code>style.css</code> into their <code>assets</code> directory. 
</mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Changelog"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <addr>jms-005O</addr>  <route>jms-005O.xml</route> <date>June 1, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Forester 2.1</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This is a major release that breaks compatibility of the XML format for trees; existing forests can be upgraded by copying <code>forest.xsl</code> and <code>style.css</code> into their <code>assets</code> directory.</p><ul>  <li><b>Development mode and edit button.</b> A <code>--dev</code> option has been added to the <code>forester</code> executable; when this option is enabled, absolute paths will be embedded into tree metadata and an <b>edit button</b> is added to the top of the command palette.</li>  
  <li><b>Your own TeX preamble.</b> There is no longer a hardcoded LaTeX preamble used for compiling graphics; instead, you can store your own <code>.sty</code> files in the <code>assets</code> directory and import them locally in a specific tree using the new <code>\texpackage{...}</code> frontmatter command.</li>  
  <li><b>Fluid binding constructs.</b> Macros in the forester language have functional semantics, which means that they capture their environment at the time of definition; this differs from the stacks of dynamic scopes that are familiar from the TeX model. This release adds support for  <b>fluid bindings</b> via <code>\alloc, \put, \get</code> in order to simulate this behavior of TeX where desired; a scope can be delimited using <code>\scope{...}</code>. This can be useful for providing flexible configurations to macros.</li>  
  <li><b>Tables of contents.</b> Tables of contents are now rendered by the default <code>forest.xsl</code> stylesheet.</li>  
  <li><b>LaTeX output.</b> LaTeX output with full bibliography support is now available; this feature is still experimental, and may not work properly with some constructs (e.g. code blocks, etc.).</li>  
  <li><b>Name resolution.</b> The behavior of name resolution was highly erratic in the prior release, and this has been corrected by adopting the <link href="https://redprl.org/yuujinchou/yuujinchou/index.html" type="external">yuujinchou</link> library. This change may break trees that depended on the prior behavior.</li>  
  <li><b>Namespaces and hierarchical identifiers.</b> Identifiers in the forester language are now hierarchical, with components delimited by <code>/</code>. Namespaces can be created using <code>\namespace\foo{...}</code>, outside which all exported identifiers are prefixed by <code>foo/</code>. Namespaces can be opened into the current scope using <code>\open\foo</code>.</li></ul></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></context> <related/> <backlinks/> <references/></backmatter></tree>