<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>5610</anchor>  <addr>jms-000I</addr>  <route>jms-000I.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Synthesis, analysis, and the axiomatic method</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The axiomatic method in mathematics is a tug of war between analysis and synthesis: analysis studies an object by modeling it with some substance that reliably behaves like the object in question, whereas synthesis takes stock of the competing models for an object and proceeds from an axiomatization of their essential properties. Analysis is important because it allows scientists to distinguish between empty fantasies and concepts that are grounded in reality by proceeding from the general to the particular; synthesis is no less important because it sharpens our view of the objects we study by summating our historical (analytical) experience in the form of axioms.</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>5611</anchor> <taxon>Example</taxon> <addr>jms-000L</addr>  <route>jms-000L.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Euclid’s synthetic plane geometry</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The canonical example of the synthetic method is the ancient Greek mathematician Euclid’s plane geometry, which starts from an axiomatization of the properties of points, lines, circles, and angles as primitive notions. For instance:</p><ol>  <li>A straight line can be drawn between any two points.</li>  <li>A line segment can be extended to a straight line.</li>  <li>There exists a circle with any center and radius.</li>  <li>All right angles are equal to each other.</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>The postulates above are descriptive of many <strong>different</strong> “models” for the concept of a line: this can be seen by considering the <link href="jms-000J.xml" type="local" title="Euclid’s parallel postulate">parallel postulate</link>, whose affirmation and negation are both consistent with the four postulates above. The revolution in modern mathematics brought on by the introduction of <em>analytic</em> (coordinate-based) methods under Descartes and Fermat should be understood as affirming the need for a plurality of models given that useful axiomatic systems can almost never uniquely determine their subject matter.</p><p>Analytic methods have been utterly dominant in recent mathematics: today, almost no mathematics is done purely synthetically, i.e. without reference whatsoever to a model. The modern viewpoint however accommodates (and greatly relies upon) the summation of analytic experience in the form of axioms, e.g. the <link href="lawvere-1964-etcs.xml" type="local" title="An elementary theory of the category of sets">axioms of set theory</link>, the <link href="grothendieck-1957-tohoku.xml" type="local" title="Sur quelques points d’algèbre homologique, I.">axioms of abelian categories</link>, or the <link href="eilenberg-steenrod-1945.xml" type="local" title="Axiomatic approach to homology theory">axioms of homology theories</link>.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>5612</anchor>  <addr>jms-000P</addr>  <route>jms-000P.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving positive properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with non-syntactic objects that are parameretized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos’ <link href="halmos-1974.xml" type="local" title="Naïve set theory"><em>Naïve Set Theory</em></link>, we advance a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <link href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory"><strong>synthetic Tait computability</strong></link>, an internal language for categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>5613</anchor>  <addr>jms-000I</addr>  <route>jms-000I.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Synthesis, analysis, and the axiomatic method</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The axiomatic method in mathematics is a tug of war between analysis and synthesis: analysis studies an object by modeling it with some substance that reliably behaves like the object in question, whereas synthesis takes stock of the competing models for an object and proceeds from an axiomatization of their essential properties. Analysis is important because it allows scientists to distinguish between empty fantasies and concepts that are grounded in reality by proceeding from the general to the particular; synthesis is no less important because it sharpens our view of the objects we study by summating our historical (analytical) experience in the form of axioms.</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb> <crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>5614</anchor> <taxon>Example</taxon> <addr>jms-000L</addr>  <route>jms-000L.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Euclid’s synthetic plane geometry</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The canonical example of the synthetic method is the ancient Greek mathematician Euclid’s plane geometry, which starts from an axiomatization of the properties of points, lines, circles, and angles as primitive notions. For instance:</p><ol>  <li>A straight line can be drawn between any two points.</li>  <li>A line segment can be extended to a straight line.</li>  <li>There exists a circle with any center and radius.</li>  <li>All right angles are equal to each other.</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>The postulates above are descriptive of many <strong>different</strong> “models” for the concept of a line: this can be seen by considering the <link href="jms-000J.xml" type="local" title="Euclid’s parallel postulate">parallel postulate</link>, whose affirmation and negation are both consistent with the four postulates above. The revolution in modern mathematics brought on by the introduction of <em>analytic</em> (coordinate-based) methods under Descartes and Fermat should be understood as affirming the need for a plurality of models given that useful axiomatic systems can almost never uniquely determine their subject matter.</p><p>Analytic methods have been utterly dominant in recent mathematics: today, almost no mathematics is done purely synthetically, i.e. without reference whatsoever to a model. The modern viewpoint however accommodates (and greatly relies upon) the summation of analytic experience in the form of axioms, e.g. the <link href="lawvere-1964-etcs.xml" type="local" title="An elementary theory of the category of sets">axioms of set theory</link>, the <link href="grothendieck-1957-tohoku.xml" type="local" title="Sur quelques points d’algèbre homologique, I.">axioms of abelian categories</link>, or the <link href="eilenberg-steenrod-1945.xml" type="local" title="Axiomatic approach to homology theory">axioms of homology theories</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>3</crumb></trail> <anchor>5615</anchor>  <addr>jms-000K</addr>  <route>jms-000K.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>The relationship between internal and external language</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The development of axiomatic set theory followed by the discovery of <em>sheaves</em> and <em>forcing</em> has led to a new style of synthetic mathematics that differs somewhat from <link href="jms-000L.xml" type="local" title="Euclid’s synthetic plane geometry">Euclid’s</link>. In the new synthetic method, we start from a concrete domain concept (such as <strong>topological spaces</strong>, <strong>smooth manifolds</strong>, <strong>computational datatypes</strong>, <strong>homotopy types</strong>, etc.) and summon as if from the void a new kind of set theory in which instances of the original domain concept are treated <em>naïvely</em> as though they were just special sets.</p><p>The advantage of this approach is that we can completely do away with the complexities of checking the well-definedness (e.g. continuity, computability, etc.) of <em>functions</em> between domain objects, because these become just ordinary functions between sets. For instance, in ordinary topology we must be careful to ensure that functions are continuous; a special case of this arises in computer science, where we must constantly check that a function between <em>domains</em> (e.g. directed-complete partial orders, <tex>\omega</tex>-cpos, Scott domains, etc.) preserves the appropriate directed suprema, an essentially bureaucratic task whose derilication can nonetheless lead to serious mistakes. Likewise in the context of theory of computation, we likewise have to check that a function between datatypes is tracked by a Turing machine.</p><p>In contrast, when (spaces, domains, datatypes, etc.) are viewed synthetically as if they were simply sets, any function between them will do. Obviously this sounds too good to be true, so there must be something that we have to give up in return for this simplicity; indeed, we must give up in many cases the unrestricted use of <em>classical logic</em>, in particular the law of the excluded middle and the axiom of choice. Thus the “set theory” generated by a given domain concept must be in general an <strong>intuitionistic</strong> set theory.</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>3</crumb> <crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>5616</anchor>  <addr>jms-000M</addr>  <route>jms-000M.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Well-pointedness vs. function extensionality</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>One of the consequences of passing to an intuitionistic set theory is that we must deal with distinctions that did not have significance in the classical setting, such as the <strong>failure of well-pointedness</strong>. In classical set theory, well-pointedness means that a function <tex>f : A  \to  B</tex> is completely determined by its behavior on global elements <tex>x \in  A</tex> (i.e. functions <tex>x : 1 \to  A</tex>), whereas in intuitionistic set theory this need not hold (indeed, well-pointedness in this sense implies the law of the excluded middle).</p><p>In an intuitionistic setting, we must instead consider the composition of <tex>f : A  \to  B</tex> with <em>arbitrary</em> functions <tex>a : I  \to  A</tex> in order to fully characterize its behavior. (In some cases, the domains <tex>I</tex> of these functions that we must probe by can be drawn from a more restricted class (or even a set) of distinguished set.) In such a setting, therefore, it is convenient to think of a function <tex>a : I  \to  A</tex> as a <strong>generalized element</strong> of <tex>A</tex>; then we are saying that <tex>f : A  \to  B</tex> is determined by its behavior on not only global elements but also generalized elements.</p><p>The new significance of generalized elements in intuitionistic set theories gives rise to a distinction between two kinds of language: <strong>internal</strong> and <strong>external</strong> language. External language is just ordinary mathematics, where we are explicit about the domains of generalized elements; external language thus allows us to distinguish between a global element and a parameterized element. In contrast, internal language expresses only that which applies to arbitrary generalized elements; internal statements can always be translated mechanically to external ones by explicitly reparameterizing all variable elements as generalized elements (this is called Kripke-Joyal semantics).</p><p>For example, even though the external statement of well-pointedness may not hold, the internal one does hold because its externalization is trivial:</p><blockquote><p><strong>Internal:</strong> for any functions <tex>f,g:A \to  B</tex>, if for all <tex>x:A</tex> we have <tex>fx=gx</tex>, then <tex>f=g</tex>.</p></blockquote><blockquote><p><strong>Externalization:</strong> for any set <tex>I</tex> and functions <tex>f,g:I \times  A  \to  B</tex>, if for all <tex>i:J \to  I</tex> and <tex>a:J \to  A</tex> we have <tex>f  \circ   { \left \langle   i,a   \right \rangle }  = g \circ { \left \langle   i,a   \right \rangle }</tex>, then <tex>f=g</tex>.</p></blockquote><p>The two statements above are nothing more than the (equivalent) internal and external formulations of the <strong>function extensionality</strong> principle, which is always true in any adequate foundation for mathematics. If the internal statement is read directly as if it were external already, it would be exactly the statement of <strong>well-pointedness</strong>, which is much stronger than function extensionality.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>3</crumb> <crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>5617</anchor>  <addr>jms-000N</addr>  <route>jms-000N.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Category theory vs. type theory</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong>Category theory</strong> is the language that is best equipped to express external statements and arguments, because category theory is explicit about the “domain of definition” of a given (generalized) element. In contrast, <strong>type theory</strong> is the language of internal mathematics; in type theory one works naïvely with “elements” <tex>x:A</tex>, and the constraints of the language ensure that everything you do is compatible with these formal elements being realized by <em>generalized</em> elements <tex>x:I \to  A</tex>.</p><p>Many aspects of synthetic mathematics are best realized in the internal / type theoretic manner, as it is natural for many objects to vary over a “domain of definition”; for instance, in computer science, a program <tex>\Gamma \vdash  M : A</tex> can be thought of as a generalized element <tex>M: \Gamma \to  A</tex>, but it is often useful to speak simply of “elements of type <tex>A</tex>” without intending to make any assumptions about whether these “elements” are closed or not.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>4</crumb></trail> <anchor>5618</anchor>  <addr>jms-000O</addr>  <route>jms-000O.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Using synthetic methods to prove analytical facts</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Today when synthetic methods are employed, it is usually with the intention of proving something about a concrete (analytically constituted) object. For instance, <link href="kock-2006.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic differential geometry">synthetic differential geometry</link> is used to prove things about actual smooth manifolds; synthetic domain theory <link href="fiore-plotkin-1997.xml" type="local" title="An extension of models of Axiomatic Domain Theory to models of Synthetic Domain Theory">can be used</link> to prove things about actual <tex>\omega</tex>-cpos. Likewise, <link href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">synthetic Tait computability</link> can be used to prove things about the actual syntax of actual programming languages!</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></context> <related><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>5619</anchor> <taxon>Postulate</taxon> <addr>jms-000J</addr>  <route>jms-000J.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Euclid’s parallel postulate</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>“If a straight line falling on two straight lines make the interior angles on the same side less than two right angles, the two straight lines, if produced indefinitely, meet on that side on which the angles are less than two right angles.”</p></mainmatter> </tree></related> <backlinks/> <references><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>5620</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>lawvere-1964-etcs</addr>  <route>lawvere-1964-etcs.xml</route> <date><year>1964</year> <month>10</month> <day>26</day></date> <authors><author>F. William Lawvere</author> </authors> <title>An elementary theory of the category of sets</title> <meta name="doi">10.1073/pnas.52.6.1506</meta><meta name="bibtex">@article{lawvere-1964-etcs,
  author = {F. William Lawvere},
  doi = {10.1073/pnas.52.6.1506},
  journal = {Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences},
  number = {6},
  pages = {1506-1511},
  title = {An Elementary Theory of the Category of Sets},
  volume = {52},
  year = {1964},
}
</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>5621</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>grothendieck-1957-tohoku</addr>  <route>grothendieck-1957-tohoku.xml</route> <date><year>1957</year> <month>3</month> <day>1</day></date> <authors><author>Alexander Grothendieck</author> </authors> <title>Sur quelques points d’algèbre homologique, I.</title> <meta name="doi">10.2748/tmj/1178244839</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>5622</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>eilenberg-steenrod-1945</addr>  <route>eilenberg-steenrod-1945.xml</route> <date><year>1945</year> <month>2</month> <day>21</day></date> <authors><author>Samuel Eilenberg</author><author>Norman E. Steenrod</author> </authors> <title>Axiomatic approach to homology theory</title> <meta name="doi">10.1073/pnas.31.4.117</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree></references></backmatter></tree>