<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>10051</anchor> <addr>jms-001B</addr>  <route>jms-001B.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <em>refinement types</em> and <em>program extraction</em> via a phase distinction between <em>computation</em> and <em>specification</em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when <tex>{ \phi } \sqsubset{A}</tex> and <tex>{ \psi } \sqsubset{B}</tex> are refinements of types <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> respectively, then <tex>\phi \to \psi</tex> refines <tex>A \to  B</tex>. In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>10053</anchor> <addr>jms-0019</addr>  <route>jms-0019.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Chapter 8: a plan for PL</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This dissertation has focused almost solely on the development and applications of synthetic Tait computability in the context of pure type theory, but the author originally invented synthetic Tait computability to solve problems in core programming languages, as part of <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>’s re-analysis of the <em>phase distinction</em> in <link href="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990.xml" type="local">ML-style</link> <link href="moggi-1989.xml" type="local">module systems</link> between static (compiletime) and dynamic (runtime) code. The purpose of this chapter is to identify several applications of synthetic Tait computability to core programming languages, and set an agenda for future work — some of which has been executed and published following the completion of this dissertation</p><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>10055</anchor> <addr>jms-001A</addr>  <route>jms-001A.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A brief overview is given of the applications of synthetic Tait computability to program modules, material that is published in the <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">Journal of the ACM</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>10057</anchor> <addr>jms-001B</addr>  <route>jms-001B.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <em>refinement types</em> and <em>program extraction</em> via a phase distinction between <em>computation</em> and <em>specification</em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when <tex>{ \phi } \sqsubset{A}</tex> and <tex>{ \psi } \sqsubset{B}</tex> are refinements of types <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> respectively, then <tex>\phi \to \psi</tex> refines <tex>A \to  B</tex>. In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>3</crumb></trail> <anchor>10059</anchor> <addr>jms-001C</addr>  <route>jms-001C.xml</route> <date>January 20, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.3: information-flow and noninterference</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Finally, an application of synthetic Tait computability to <em>security</em> and <em>information flow control</em> is identified: a security class is a phase distinction between low and high security. The preliminary results presented in this section have been substantially improved upon by <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>, adding support for general recursion and termination-insensitive noninterference by combining synthetic Tait computability with <link href="hyland-1991.xml" type="local">synthetic domain theory</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></context> <related/> <backlinks/> <references><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>10061</anchor> <addr>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022</addr>  <route>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml</route> <date>January 1, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="yueniu.xml" type="local">Yue Niu</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="harrisongrodin.xml" type="local">Harrison Grodin</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author> </authors> <title>A cost-aware logical framework</title> <meta name="venue">Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages, Volume 6, Issue POPL</meta><meta name="doi">10.1145/3498670</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present calf, a cost-aware logical framework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs. Taking inspiration from recent work that reconstructs traditional aspects of programming languages in terms of a modal account of phase distinctions, we argue that the cost structure of programs motivates a phase distinction between intension and extension. Armed with this technology, we contribute a synthetic account of cost structure as a computational effect in which cost-aware programs enjoy an internal noninterference property: input/output behavior cannot depend on cost. As a full-spectrum dependent type theory, calf presents a unified language for programming and specification of both cost and behavior that can be integrated smoothly with existing mathematical libraries available in type theoretic proof assistants.</p><p>We evaluate calf as a general framework for cost analysis by implementing two fundamental techniques for algorithm analysis: the method of recurrence relations and physicist’s method for amortized analysis. We deploy these techniques on a variety of case studies: we prove a tight, closed bound for Euclid’s algorithm, verify the amortized complexity of batched queues, and derive tight, closed bounds for the sequential and parallel complexity of merge sort, all fully mechanized in the Agda proof assistant. Lastly we substantiate the soundness of quantitative reasoning in calf by means of a model construction.</p></mainmatter> </tree></references></backmatter></tree>