<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>24587</anchor> <addr>kerodon</addr>  <route>kerodon.xml</route> <date>2023</date> <authors><author>Jacob Lurie</author> </authors> <title>Kerodon</title> <meta name="external">https://kerodon.net</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Kerodon is an online textbook on categorical homotopy theory and related mathematics. It currently consists of a handful of chapters, but should grow (slowly) over time. It is modeled on the <link href="stacks-project.xml" type="local">Stacks project</link>, and is maintained by Jacob Lurie.</p><p>Its infrastructure uses <link href="gerby.xml" type="local">Gerby</link>, which is maintained by Pieter Belmans. The design was created by Opus Design.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>24589</anchor> <addr>jms-0052</addr>  <route>jms-0052.xml</route> <date>May 14, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>How to create your own Stacks Project in 10 minutes</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><link href="stacks-project.xml" type="local">The Stacks project</link> is the most successful hypertext mathematics project in history. Its mathematical goal is to lay the foundations for the theory of algebraic stacks; to facilitate its scalable and sustainable development, several important innovations have been introduced, with the <em>tags</em> system being the most striking.</p><blockquote>  Each tag refers to a unique item (section, lemma, theorem, etc.) in order for this project to be referenceable. These tags don't change even if the item moves within the text. (<link href="https://stacks.math.columbia.edu/tags" type="external">Tags explained</link>, <link href="stacks-project.xml" type="local">The Stacks Project</link>).
</blockquote><p>Many working mathematicians and students have wished to create their own tag-based hypertext mathematical portal, but the combination of tools historically required to make this happen are extremely daunting. Both the <link href="stacks-project.xml" type="local">Stacks project</link> and <link href="kerodon.xml" type="local">Kerodon</link> use a cluster of software called <link href="gerby.xml" type="local">Gerby</link>, but bitrot has set in and it is <link href="https://github.com/gerby-project/plastex/issues/60" type="external">no longer possible</link> to build its dependencies on a modern environment without significant difficulty, raising questions of longevity.</p><p>Moreover, <link href="gerby.xml" type="local">Gerby</link>’s deployment involves running a database on a server (in spite of the fact that almost the entire functionality is static HTML), an architecture that is incompatible with the constraints of the everyday working mathematician or student who knows <em>at most</em> how to upload static files to their university-provided public storage. The recent experience of the <link href="https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/HomePage" type="external">nLab</link>’s pandemic-era hiatus and near death experience has demonstrated with some urgency the pracarity faced by any project relying heavily on volunteer system administrators.</p><tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>24591</anchor> <addr>jms-0053</addr>  <route>jms-0053.xml</route> <date>May 14, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Introducing <link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local"><em>forester</em></link>: a <link href="tfmt-0002.xml" type="local">tool for mathematical thought</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>After spending two years exploring the <link href="tfmt-0001.xml" type="local">design of tools for mathematical thought</link> that meet the unique needs of real, scalable mathematical writing in hypertext, I have created a tool called <strong><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">forester</link></strong> which has the following benefits:</p><ol>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> is tag-based like <link href="gerby.xml" type="local">Gerby</link>, and can therefore power large-scale generational projects like <link href="stacks-project.xml" type="local">Stacks</link> and <link href="kerodon.xml" type="local">Kerodon</link>.</li>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> produces static content that can be uploaded to any web hosting service without needing to run or install any serverside software.</li>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> is easy to install on your own machine.</li>  <li>To prevent bitrot, <link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> is a single tool rather than a composition of several tools.</li>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> satisfies <em>all</em> the <link href="tfmt-000E.xml" type="local">requirements of serious mathematical writing</link>, including sophisticated notational macros, typesetting of diagrams, etc.</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>24593</anchor> <addr>jms-0053</addr>  <route>jms-0053.xml</route> <date>May 14, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Introducing <link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local"><em>forester</em></link>: a <link href="tfmt-0002.xml" type="local">tool for mathematical thought</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>After spending two years exploring the <link href="tfmt-0001.xml" type="local">design of tools for mathematical thought</link> that meet the unique needs of real, scalable mathematical writing in hypertext, I have created a tool called <strong><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">forester</link></strong> which has the following benefits:</p><ol>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> is tag-based like <link href="gerby.xml" type="local">Gerby</link>, and can therefore power large-scale generational projects like <link href="stacks-project.xml" type="local">Stacks</link> and <link href="kerodon.xml" type="local">Kerodon</link>.</li>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> produces static content that can be uploaded to any web hosting service without needing to run or install any serverside software.</li>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> is easy to install on your own machine.</li>  <li>To prevent bitrot, <link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> is a single tool rather than a composition of several tools.</li>  <li><link href="jms-005P.xml" type="local">Forester</link> satisfies <em>all</em> the <link href="tfmt-000E.xml" type="local">requirements of serious mathematical writing</link>, including sophisticated notational macros, typesetting of diagrams, etc.</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>24595</anchor> <addr>stacks-project</addr>  <route>stacks-project.xml</route> <date>2018</date> <authors><author>The Stacks Project Authors</author> </authors> <title>The Stacks project</title> <meta name="external">https://stacks.math.columbia.edu</meta><meta name="bibtex">@misc{stacks-project,
    shorthand    = {Stacks},
    author       = {The {Stacks Project Authors}},
    title        = {\textit{Stacks Project}},
    howpublished = {\url{https://stacks.math.columbia.edu}},
    year         = {2018},
  }
</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The Stacks project is an ever growing open source textbook and reference work on algebraic stacks and the algebraic geometry needed to define them. Here are some quick facts:</p><ol>  <li>The Stacks project is not an introductory text. It is written for graduate students and researchers in algebraic geometry.</li>  <li>The aim is to build algebraic geometry and use this in laying the foundations for algebraic stacks. The theory of commutative algebra, schemes, varieties, and algebraic spaces forms an integral part of the Stacks project.</li>  <li>The Stacks project has a maintainer (currently Aise Johan de Jong) who accepts changes etc. proposed by contributors. Everyone is encouraged to participate.</li>  <li>The Stacks project is meant to be read online. Consequently we do not worry about length of the chapters, etc. With hyperlinks and the search function it is possible to quickly browse through the chapters to find the lemmas, theorems, etc. that a given result depends on.</li>  <li>We use tags to identify results, which are permanent identifiers for a result. You can read more about this on the tags explained page.</li></ol><p>For a longer discussion, please read the blog post <link href="https://www.math.columbia.edu/~dejong/wordpress/?p=866" type="external">What is the stacks project?</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>24597</anchor> <addr>gerby</addr>  <route>gerby.xml</route>  <authors><author>Pieter Belmans</author><author>Raymond Cheng</author><author>Johan de Jong</author> </authors> <title>Gerby</title> <meta name="external">https://gerby-project.github.io/</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>If you have a LaTeX document which</p><ul>  <li>is large (probably several hundreds of pages at least)</li>  <li>is regularly updated</li>  <li>needs to be externally referenced often</li></ul><p>you will run into the problem that</p><ol>  <li>large PDFs are not easily navigable</li>  <li>PDFs of any size are not very searchable</li>  <li>the internal numbering changes often, making external references outdated</li></ol><p>Gerby addresses these problems by providing an online tag-based view, instead of just having a big PDF. Gerby is tailored towards making large online textbooks and reference works more accessible.</p><p>In case you were wondering, a gerbe is a kind of stack (in the mathematical sense), and the software was originally meant for the <link href="stacks-project.xml" type="local">Stacks project</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree></references></backmatter></tree>