<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>19549</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:addr>kock-2006</fr:addr><fr:route>kock-2006.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Synthetic differential geometry</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2006</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>Anders Kock</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1017/CBO9780511550812</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Synthetic Differential Geometry is a method of reasoning in differential geometry and differential calculus, based on the assumption of sufficiently many nilpotent elements on the number line, in particular numbers <fr:tex>d</fr:tex> such that <fr:tex>d^2=0</fr:tex>. The use of nilpotent elements allows one to replace the limit processes of calculus by purely algebraic calculations and notions. For the first half of the book, first published in 2006, familiarity with differential calculus and abstract algebra is presupposed during the development of results in calculus and differential geometry on a purely axiomatic/synthetic basis. In the second half basic notions of category theory are presumed in the construction of suitable Cartesian closed categories and the interpretation of logical formulae within them. This is a second edition of Kock’s classical text from 1981. Many notes have been included, with comments on developments in the field from the intermediate years, and almost 100 new bibliographic entries have been added.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:contributions></fr:contributions><fr:context></fr:context><fr:related></fr:related><fr:backlinks><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>19547</fr:anchor><fr:addr>jms-000O</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-000O.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Using synthetic methods to prove analytical facts</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="jonmsterling.xml"
type="local"
addr="jonmsterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Today when synthetic methods are employed, it is usually with the intention of proving something about a concrete (analytically constituted) object. For instance, <fr:link
href="kock-2006.xml"
type="local"
addr="kock-2006">synthetic differential geometry</fr:link> is used to prove things about actual smooth manifolds; synthetic domain theory <fr:link
href="fiore-plotkin-1997.xml"
type="local"
addr="fiore-plotkin-1997">can be used</fr:link> to prove things about actual <html:span
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
style="white-space: nowrap"><fr:tex>\omega-cpos</fr:tex></html:span>. Likewise, <fr:link
href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml"
type="local"
addr="sterling-2021-thesis">synthetic Tait computability</fr:link> can be used to prove things about the actual syntax of actual programming languages!</fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree></fr:backlinks><fr:references></fr:references></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>