<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><addr>lawvere-1964-etcs</addr>  <route>lawvere-1964-etcs.xml</route> <date>October 26, 1964</date> <authors><author>F. William Lawvere</author> </authors> <title>An Elementary Theory of the Category of Sets</title> <meta name="doi">10.1073/pnas.52.6.1506</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Remark"><frontmatter><addr>frct-003K</addr>  <route>frct-003K.xml</route>   <title>Cartesian Closure of the Meta-category of all Categories</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Consequently there exists a meta-category \(\boldsymbol{\mathfrak{Cat}}\) of all categories. Following <a href="http://rfcwalters.blogspot.com/2010/10/old-post-why-are-we-concerned-fw.html" class="external">Lawvere</a> (but deviating from some other authors that ground the notion of meta-categories in <em>classes</em>) we notice that \(\boldsymbol{\mathfrak{Cat}}\) is cartesian closed; in other words, all functor categories exist regardless of size.</p><p><strong>Assumption.</strong> At times we may assume that there exists a <em>category</em> \(\mathbf{Set} \subseteq \boldsymbol{\mathfrak{Coll}}\) of collections that we will refer to as sets, such that \(\mathbf{Set}\) is closed under the axioms of <a href="lawvere-1964-etcs.xml" class="local">ETCS</a>. Rather than work with \(\mathbf{Set}\) at all times, our approach is to use the tools of relative category theory to objectify the notions of “small” and “locally small” category over any category \(B\), generalizing the role of \(\mathbf{Set}\) from classical category theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Remark"><frontmatter><addr>frct-003J</addr>  <route>frct-003J.xml</route>   <title>Collections</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>In the definition of <a href="frct-001F.xml" class="local">meta-categories</a>, we have not imposed any restrictions on what kinds of things the objects and morphisms are; our definition is pre-mathematical, so we do not assume beforehand that there is a such thing as a collection of “all” meta-categories.</p><p>We may define analogous notions of meta-functor, etc. But we do not
assume that the notion of “all meta-functors \(\mathfrak{C} \to \mathfrak{D}\)” is well-defined; the notion is entirely schematic.</p><p><strong>Assumption.</strong> We assume a meta-category \(\boldsymbol{\mathfrak{Coll}}\) whose objects we will refer to as “collections”. We assume that the meta-category of all collections satisfies the axioms of Lawvere’s <a href="lawvere-1964-etcs.xml" class="local">ETCS</a>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Remark"><frontmatter><addr>frct-002O</addr>  <route>frct-002O.xml</route>   <title>Frct-002O</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Let \(\mathscr{M}\) be a model of <a href="lawvere-1964-etcs.xml" class="local">ETCS</a>; and let \(\mathfrak{C}\) be a class of families of sets in \(\mathscr{M}\). Then \(\mathfrak{C}\) is a class of objects in the fundamental self-indexing \(\underline{\mathscr{M}}\) over \(\mathscr{M}\). Furthermore, \(\mathscr{M}\) a <a href="frct-002W.xml" class="local">definable class</a> in \(\underline{\mathscr{M}}\) if and only if it is a <a href="frct-002P.xml" class="local">definable class of families of sets</a>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><addr>jms-000I</addr>  <route>jms-000I.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><a href="jonmsterling.xml" class="local" rel="author">Jonathan Sterling</a></author> </authors> <title>Synthesis, Analysis, and the Axiomatic Method</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The axiomatic method in mathematics is a tug of war between analysis and synthesis: analysis studies an object by modeling it with some substance that reliably behaves like the object in question, whereas synthesis takes stock of the competing models for an object and proceeds from an axiomatization of their essential properties. Analysis is important because it allows scientists to distinguish between empty fantasies and concepts that are grounded in reality by proceeding from the general to the particular; synthesis is no less important because it sharpens our view of the objects we study by summating our historical (analytical) experience in the form of axioms.</p><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Example"><frontmatter><addr>jms-000L</addr>  <route>jms-000L.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><a href="jonmsterling.xml" class="local" rel="author">Jonathan Sterling</a></author> </authors> <title>Euclid’s Synthetic Plane Geometry</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The canonical example of the synthetic method is the ancient Greek mathematician Euclid’s plane geometry, which starts from an axiomatization of the properties of points, lines, circles, and angles as primitive notions. For instance:</p><ol>  <li>A straight line can be drawn between any two points.</li>  <li>A line segment can be extended to a straight line.</li>  <li>There exists a circle with any center and radius.</li>  <li>All right angles are equal to each other.</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>The postulates above are descriptive of many <strong>different</strong> “models” for the concept of a line: this can be seen by considering the <a href="jms-000J.xml" class="local">parallel postulate</a>, whose affirmation and negation are both consistent with the four postulates above. The revolution in modern mathematics brought on by the introduction of <em>analytic</em> (coordinate-based) methods under Descartes and Fermat should be understood as affirming the need for a plurality of models given that useful axiomatic systems can almost never uniquely determine their subject matter.</p><p>Analytic methods have been utterly dominant in recent mathematics: today, almost no mathematics is done purely synthetically, i.e. without reference whatsoever to a model. The modern viewpoint however accommodates (and greatly relies upon) the summation of analytic experience in the form of axioms, e.g. the <a href="lawvere-1964-etcs.xml" class="local">axioms of set theory</a>, the <a href="grothendieck-1957-tohoku.xml" class="local">axioms of abelian categories</a>, or the <a href="eilenberg-steenrod-1945.xml" class="local">axioms of homology theories</a>.</p></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>