<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>18996</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:addr>moggi-1989</fr:addr><fr:route>moggi-1989.xml</fr:route><fr:title>A category-theoretic account of program modules</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>1989</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="eugeniomoggi.xml"
type="local"
addr="eugeniomoggi">Eugenio Moggi</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.1007/BFb0018347</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The type-theoretic explanation of modules proposed to date (for programming languages like ML) is unsatisfactory, in that it fails to reflect the distinction between compile-time, when type-expressions are evaluated, and run-time, when value-expressions are evaluated. This paper proposes a new explanation based on “programming languages as indexed categories” and illustrates, as an application, how ML should be extended to support higher order modules. The paper also outlines a methodology for a modular approach to programming languages, where programming languages (of a certain kind) are identified with objects in a 2-category and features are viewed as 2-categorical notions.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:contributions></fr:contributions><fr:context></fr:context><fr:related></fr:related><fr:backlinks><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>18992</fr:anchor><fr:addr>jms-0019</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0019.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Chapter 8: a plan for PL</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="jonmsterling.xml"
type="local"
addr="jonmsterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This dissertation has focused almost solely on the development and applications of synthetic Tait computability in the context of pure type theory, but the author originally invented synthetic Tait computability to solve problems in core programming languages, as part of <fr:link
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
type="local"
addr="sterling-harper-2021">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>’s re-analysis of the <fr:em>phase distinction</fr:em> in <fr:link
href="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990.xml"
type="local"
addr="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990">ML-style</fr:link> <fr:link
href="moggi-1989.xml"
type="local"
addr="moggi-1989">module systems</fr:link> between static (compiletime) and dynamic (runtime) code. The purpose of this chapter is to identify several applications of synthetic Tait computability to core programming languages, and set an agenda for future work — some of which has been executed and published following the completion of this dissertation</fr:p><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16362</fr:anchor><fr:addr>jms-001A</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001A.xml</fr:route><fr:title>§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="jonmsterling.xml"
type="local"
addr="jonmsterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>A brief overview is given of the applications of synthetic Tait computability to program modules, material that is published in the <fr:link
href="sterling-harper-2021.xml"
type="local"
addr="sterling-harper-2021">Journal of the ACM</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16364</fr:anchor><fr:addr>jms-001B</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001B.xml</fr:route><fr:title>§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="jonmsterling.xml"
type="local"
addr="jonmsterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <fr:em>refinement types</fr:em> and <fr:em>program extraction</fr:em> via a phase distinction between <fr:em>computation</fr:em> and <fr:em>specification</fr:em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when <fr:tex>{ \phi } \sqsubset { A }</fr:tex> and <fr:tex>{ \psi } \sqsubset { B }</fr:tex> are refinements of types <fr:tex>A</fr:tex> and <fr:tex>B</fr:tex> respectively, then <fr:tex>\phi \to \psi</fr:tex> refines <fr:tex>A \to  B</fr:tex>. In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <fr:link
href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml"
type="local"
addr="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</fr:link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>16366</fr:anchor><fr:addr>jms-001C</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-001C.xml</fr:route><fr:title>§ 8.3: information-flow and noninterference</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>20</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="jonmsterling.xml"
type="local"
addr="jonmsterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Finally, an application of synthetic Tait computability to <fr:em>security</fr:em> and <fr:em>information flow control</fr:em> is identified: a security class is a phase distinction between low and high security. The preliminary results presented in this section have been substantially improved upon by <fr:link
href="sterling-harper-2022.xml"
type="local"
addr="sterling-harper-2022">Sterling and Harper</fr:link>, adding support for general recursion and termination-insensitive noninterference by combining synthetic Tait computability with <fr:link
href="hyland-1991.xml"
type="local"
addr="hyland-1991">synthetic domain theory</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>18994</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:addr>harper-2021-topos-institute</fr:addr><fr:route>harper-2021-topos-institute.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Phase distinctions in type theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2021</fr:year><fr:month>12</fr:month><fr:day>9</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="robertharper.xml"
type="local"
addr="robertharper">Robert Harper</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7DYkyB1Rm3I</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:link
href="toposinstitute.xml"
type="local"
addr="toposinstitute">Topos Institute</fr:link> Colloquium</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>(Joint work with <fr:link
href="jonmsterling.xml"
type="local"
addr="jonmsterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link> and <fr:link
href="yueniu.xml"
type="local"
addr="yueniu">Yue Niu</fr:link>)</fr:p><fr:p>The informal phase distinction between compile-time and run-time in programming languages is formally manifested by the distinction between kinds, which classify types, and types, which classify code. The distinction underpins standard programming methodology whereby code is first type-checked for consistency before being compiled for execution. When used effectively, types help eliminate bugs before they occur.</fr:p><fr:p>Program modules, in even the most rudimentary form, threaten the distinction, comprising as they do both types and programs in a single unit. Matters worsen when considerating “open” modules, with free module variables standing for its imports. To maintain the separation in their presence it is necessary to limit the dependency of types, the static parts of a module, to their imported types. Such restrictions are fundamental for using dependent types to express modular structure, as originally suggested by MacQueen.</fr:p><fr:p>To address this question <fr:link
href="moggi-1989.xml"
type="local"
addr="moggi-1989">Moggi</fr:link> gave an “analytic” formulation of program modules in which modules are explicitly separated into their static and dynamic components using tools from category theory. Recent work by Dreyer, Rossberg, and Russo develops this approach fully in their account of ML-like module systems. In this talk we consider instead a “synthetic” formulation using a proposition to segregate the static from the dynamic, in particular to define static equivalence to manage type sharing and type dependency.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree></fr:backlinks><fr:references></fr:references></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>