<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>22804</anchor> <addr>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022</addr>  <route>niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml</route> <date>January 1, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="yueniu.xml" type="local">Yue Niu</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="harrisongrodin.xml" type="local">Harrison Grodin</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author> </authors> <title>A cost-aware logical framework</title> <meta name="venue">Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages, Volume 6, Issue POPL</meta><meta name="doi">10.1145/3498670</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present calf, a cost-aware logical framework for studying quantitative aspects of functional programs. Taking inspiration from recent work that reconstructs traditional aspects of programming languages in terms of a modal account of phase distinctions, we argue that the cost structure of programs motivates a phase distinction between intension and extension. Armed with this technology, we contribute a synthetic account of cost structure as a computational effect in which cost-aware programs enjoy an internal noninterference property: input/output behavior cannot depend on cost. As a full-spectrum dependent type theory, calf presents a unified language for programming and specification of both cost and behavior that can be integrated smoothly with existing mathematical libraries available in type theoretic proof assistants.</p><p>We evaluate calf as a general framework for cost analysis by implementing two fundamental techniques for algorithm analysis: the method of recurrence relations and physicist’s method for amortized analysis. We deploy these techniques on a variety of case studies: we prove a tight, closed bound for Euclid’s algorithm, verify the amortized complexity of batched queues, and derive tight, closed bounds for the sequential and parallel complexity of merge sort, all fully mechanized in the Agda proof assistant. Lastly we substantiate the soundness of quantitative reasoning in calf by means of a model construction.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree mode="full" root="false"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>22806</anchor> <addr>jms-001B</addr>  <route>jms-001B.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <em>refinement types</em> and <em>program extraction</em> via a phase distinction between <em>computation</em> and <em>specification</em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when <tex>{ \phi } \sqsubset{A}</tex> and <tex>{ \psi } \sqsubset{B}</tex> are refinements of types <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> respectively, then <tex>\phi \to \psi</tex> refines <tex>A \to  B</tex>. In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>22808</anchor> <addr>sterling-harper-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2022.xml</route> <date>2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author> </authors> <title>Sheaf Semantics of Termination-Insensitive Noninterference</title> <meta name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.5</meta><meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-harper-2022.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">7th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2022)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We propose a new sheaf semantics for secure information flow over a space of abstract behaviors, based on synthetic domain theory: security classes are open/closed partitions, types are sheaves, and redaction of sensitive information corresponds to restricting a sheaf to a closed subspace. Our security-aware computational model satisfies termination-insensitive noninterference automatically, and therefore constitutes an intrinsic alternative to state of the art extrinsic/relational models of noninterference. Our semantics is the latest application of <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Harper</link>’s recent re-interpretation of phase distinctions and noninterference in programming languages in terms of Artin gluing and topos-theoretic open/closed modalities. Prior applications include <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local">parametricity for ML modules</link>, the proof of normalization for cubical type theory by <link href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml" type="local">Sterling and Angiuli</link>, and the cost-aware logical framework of <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local">Niu et al</link>. In this paper we employ the phase distinction perspective twice: first to reconstruct the syntax and semantics of secure information flow as a lattice of phase distinctions between “higher” and “lower” security, and second to verify the computational adequacy of our sheaf semantics with respect to a version of Abadi et al.’s dependency core calculus to which we have added a construct for declassifying termination channels.</p><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Erratum"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>22810</anchor> <addr>jms-005Y</addr>  <route>jms-005Y.xml</route> <date>2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Minor mistakes in <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local">sheaf semantics of noninterference</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>In the published version of this paper, there were a few mistakes that have been corrected in the local copy hosted here.</p><ol>  <li>In the <em>Critique of relational semantics for information flow</em>, our discussion of the <em>Failure of monotonicity</em> stated incorrectly that algebras for the sealing monad at a higher security level could not be transformed into algebras for the sealing monad at a lower security level in the semantics of Abadi et al. This is not true, as pointed out to us privately by Carlos Tomé Cortiñas. What we meant to say was that it is not the case that a type whose component at a high security level is trivial shall always remain trivial at a lower security level.</li>  <li>The original version of the extended edition of this paper, we claimed that the constructive existence of tensor products on pointed dcpos was obvious; in fact, tensor products do exist, but their construction involves a reflexive coequalizer of pointed dcpos.</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Erratum"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>22812</anchor> <addr>jms-005Z</addr>  <route>jms-005Z.xml</route> <date>July 17, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Adequacy of <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local">sheaf semantics of noninterference</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A serious (and as-yet unfixed) problem was discovered in July of 2023 by <link href="yue-niu" type="external">Yue Niu</link>, which undermines the proof of adequacy given; in particular, the proof that the logical relation on free algebras is admissible is not correct. I believe there is a different proof of adequacy for the calculus described, but it will have a different structure from what currently appears in the paper. We thank <link href="yue-niu" type="external">Yue Niu</link> for his attention to detail and careful reading of this paper.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>