<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>22816</anchor> <addr>palombi-sterling-2023</addr>  <route>palombi-sterling-2023.xml</route> <date>February 22, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="danielepalombi.xml" type="local">Daniele Palombi</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Classifying topoi in synthetic guarded domain theory: the universal property of multi-clock guarded recursion</title> <meta name="bibtex">
 @inproceedings{palombi-sterling:2023,
  author = {Palombi, Daniele and Sterling, Jonathan},
  booktitle = {Proceedings 38th Conference on Mathematical Foundations of Programming Semantics, {MFPS} 2022},
  year = {2023},
  month = feb,
  title = {Classifying topoi in synthetic guarded domain theory},
  doi = {10.46298/entics.10323},
}
 </meta><meta name="doi">10.46298/entics.10323</meta><meta name="venue">38th International Conference on Mathematical Foundations of Programming Semantics</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Several different topoi have played an important role in the development and applications of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em> (SGDT), a new kind of synthetic domain theory that abstracts the concept of <em>guarded recursion</em> frequently employed in the semantics of programming languages. In order to unify the accounts of guarded recursion and coinduction, several authors have enriched SGDT with multiple “clocks” parameterizing different time-streams, leading to more complex and difficult to understand topos models. Until now these topoi have been understood very concretely <em>qua</em> categories of presheaves, and the logico-geometrical question of what theories these topoi classify has remained open. We show that several important topos models of SGDT classify very simple geometric theories, and that the passage to various forms of multi-clock guarded recursion can be rephrased more compositionally in terms of the lower bagtopos construction of Vickers and variations thereon due to <link href="johnstone-1994.xml" type="local">Johnstone</link>. We contribute to the consolidation of SGDT by isolating the universal property of multi-clock guarded recursion as a modular construction that applies to any topos model of single-clock guarded recursion.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks/> <references><tree mode="full" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter><trail/> <anchor>22818</anchor> <addr>johnstone-1994</addr>  <route>johnstone-1994.xml</route> <date>December 19, 1994</date> <authors><author><link href="peterjohnstone.xml" type="local">Peter T. Johnstone</link></author> </authors> <title>Variations on the bagdomain theme</title> <meta name="venue">Theoretical Computer Science</meta><meta name="doi">10.1016/0304-3975(94)00120-8</meta><meta name="bibtex">
@article{johnstone:1994,
  author = {Johnstone, Peter T.},
  year = {1994},
  doi = {10.1016/0304-3975(94)00120-8},
  issn = {0304-3975},
  journal = {Theoretical Computer Science},
  number = {1},
  pages = {3--20},
  title = {Variations on the bagdomain theme},
  volume = {136},
}
</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The notion of bagdomain was first introduced by Vickers, (1992) and further studied by the present author in (Johnstone, 1992). In these papers, attention was focused on one particular version of the bagdomain construction, the “bag” analogue of the lower (Hoare) powerdomain; but there are many other possibilities. The purpose of the present paper is to introduce some of these possibilities and to describe their basic properties, using the theory of fibrations and partial products developed in (Johnstone, 1993).</p></mainmatter> </tree></references></backmatter></tree>