<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16184</anchor> <taxon>Person</taxon> <addr>paulblainlevy</addr>  <route>paulblainlevy.xml</route>   <title>Paul Blain Levy</title> <meta name="external">https://www.cs.bham.ac.uk/~pbl/</meta><meta name="position">Reader</meta><meta name="institution">University of Birmingham</meta><meta name="orcid">0000-0003-0864-1876</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> <backmatter><contributions><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16185</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>kammar-levy-moss-staton-2017</addr>  <route>kammar-levy-moss-staton-2017.xml</route> <date><year>2017</year>  </date> <authors><author><link href="ohadkammar.xml" type="local">Ohad Kammar</link></author><author><link href="paulblainlevy.xml" type="local">Paul Blain Levy</link></author><author>Sean K. Moss</author><author>Sam Staton</author> </authors> <title>A monad for full ground reference cells</title> <meta name="venue">Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science</meta><meta name="doi">10.1109/LICS.2017.8005109</meta><meta name="bibtex">@inproceedings{kammar-levy-moss-staton:2017,
  author = {Kammar, Ohad and Levy, Paul B. and Moss, Sean K. and Staton, Sam},
  address = {Reykjavik, Iceland},
  publisher = {IEEE Press},
  booktitle = {Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science},
  year = {2017},
  month = jun,
  doi = {10.1109/LICS.2017.8005109},
  isbn = {978-1-5090-3018-7},
  title = {A Monad for Full Ground Reference Cells},
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We present a denotational account of dynamic allocation of potentially cyclic memory cells using a monad on a functor category. We identify the collection of heaps as an object in a different functor category equipped with a monad for adding hiding/encapsulation capabilities to the heaps. We derive a monad for full ground references supporting effect masking by applying a state monad transformer to the encapsulation monad. To evaluate the monad, we present a denotational semantics for a call-by-value calculus with full ground references, and validate associated code transformations.</p></mainmatter> </tree></contributions> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16186</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date><year>2022</year> <month>10</month> <day>6</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</meta><meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on <em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational reasoning based on the <em>logical relations as types</em> principle, in which equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value adjunction with higher-order store, improving on <link href="paulblainlevy.xml" type="local" title="Paul Blain Levy">Levy</link>'s possible worlds model construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>