<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml" root="false">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="leonipugh.xml" title="Leoni Pugh" addr="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="jonmsterling.xml" title="Jon Sterling" addr="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>1</fr:month>
      <fr:day>31</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:anchor>28278</fr:anchor>
    <fr:addr type="user">pugh-sterling-2025</fr:addr>
    <fr:route>pugh-sterling-2025.xml</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?">When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?</fr:title>
    <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
    <fr:meta name="external">hash-bafkrmieq5fjyugdubhiwodva367dtq2l5celvnxocyd4n3wqxjhk3jt56e.pdf</fr:meta>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <fr:p>Interval objects in a category of spaces can act as parameterising shapes for “arrows” drawn in a given space. <fr:link href="riehl-shulman-2017.xml" title="A type theory for synthetic ∞-categories" addr="riehl-shulman-2017" type="local">Riehl and Shulman</fr:link> have shown that in homotopy type theory extended by a linear interval, internal orthogonality laws can be imposed to isolate the types that behave like (higher) categories with respect to the induced notion of arrow, leading to a synthetic theory of higher categories. This idea of isolating internal orthogonality classes of types via an interval has its origin in the synthetic domain theory of the 1990s. The latter has revealed additional axioms on the interval that cause such orthogonal classes to behave more or less like full internal subcategories of predomains in the spirit of Scott.</fr:p>
    <fr:p>In this paper, we study the relationship between partial map classifiers, Sierpiński cones, and axioms for synthetic higher category and domain theory within Voevodsky’s <fr:link href="hottbook.xml" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics" addr="hottbook" type="local">univalent foundations</fr:link>. In particular, we show that the Phoa principle ensures that synthetic ∞-categories are closed under partial map classifiers, and we isolate a reflective subuniverse of types within which the Sierpiński cone (a lax colimit) can be computed as a partial map classifier by strengthening the Segal condition.</fr:p>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:anchor>28273</fr:anchor>
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="emilyriehl.xml" title="Emily Riehl" addr="emilyriehl" type="local">Emily Riehl</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="mikeshulman.xml" title="Mike Shulman" addr="mikeshulman" type="local">Mike Shulman</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2017</fr:year>
              <fr:month>12</fr:month>
              <fr:day>22</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:anchor>28271</fr:anchor>
            <fr:addr type="user">riehl-shulman-2017</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>riehl-shulman-2017.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="A type theory for synthetic ∞-categories">A type theory for synthetic ∞-categories</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
            <fr:meta name="doi">10.21136/HS.2017.06</fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="venue">Higher Structures</fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@article{riehl-shulman-2017,
  author = {Riehl, Emily and Shulman, Michael},
  url = {https://journals.mq.edu.au/index.php/higher_structures/article/view/36},
  year = {2017},
  eprint = {1705.07442},
  eprintclass = {math.CT},
  eprinttype = {arXiv},
  issue = {1},
  journal = {Higher Structures},
  pages = {147--224},
  title = {A type theory for synthetic $\infty$-categories},
  volume = {1},
}]]></fr:meta>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>We propose foundations for a synthetic theory of (∞,1)-categories within homotopy type theory. We axiomatize a directed interval type, then define higher simplices from it and use them to probe the internal categorical structures of arbitrary types. We define Segal types, in which binary composites exist uniquely up to homotopy; this automatically ensures composition is coherently associative and unital at all dimensions. We define Rezk types, in which the categorical isomorphisms are additionally equivalent to the type-theoretic identities - a “local univalence” condition. And we define covariant fibrations, which are type families varying functorially over a Segal type, and prove a “dependent Yoneda lemma” that can be viewed as a directed form of the usual elimination rule for identity types. We conclude by studying homotopically correct adjunctions between Segal types, and showing that for a functor between Rezk types to have an adjoint is a mere proposition.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>To make the bookkeeping in such proofs manageable, we use a three-layered type theory with shapes, whose contexts are extended by polytopes within directed cubes, which can be abstracted over using “extension types” that generalize the path-types of cubical type theory. In an appendix, we describe the motivating semantics in the Reedy model structure on bisimplicial sets, in which our Segal and Rezk types correspond to Segal spaces and complete Segal spaces.</fr:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>The Univalent Foundations Program</fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2013</fr:year>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:anchor>28272</fr:anchor>
            <fr:addr type="user">hottbook</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>hottbook.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
            <fr:meta name="external">https://homotopytypetheory.org/book</fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="venue">
              <fr:link href="ias-special-year.xml" title="IAS Special Year on Univalent Foundations" addr="ias-special-year" type="local">IAS Special Year on Univalent Foundations</fr:link>
            </fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@book{hottbook,
  author = {{Univalent Foundations Program}, The},
  address = {Institute for Advanced Study},
  publisher = {\url{https://homotopytypetheory.org/book}},
  year = {2013},
  title = {Homotopy Type Theory: Univalent Foundations of Mathematics},
}]]></fr:meta>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>Homotopy type theory is a new branch of mathematics that combines aspects of several different fields in a surprising way. It is based on a recently discovered connection between homotopy theory and type theory. It touches on topics as seemingly distant as the homotopy groups of spheres, the algorithms for type checking, and the definition of weak <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[\infty ]]></fr:tex>-groupoids. Homotopy type theory offers a new “univalent” foundation of mathematics, in which a central role is played by <fr:link href="vladimirvoevodsky.xml" title="Vladimir Voevodsky" addr="vladimirvoevodsky" type="local">Voevodsky</fr:link>’s univalence axiom and higher inductive types. The present book is intended as a first systematic exposition of the basics of univalent foundations, and a collection of examples of this new style of reasoning — but without requiring the reader to know or learn any formal logic, or to use any computer proof assistant. We believe that univalent foundations will eventually become a viable alternative to set theory as the “implicit foundation” for the unformalized mathematics done by most mathematicians.</fr:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:anchor>28274</fr:anchor>
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:anchor>28275</fr:anchor>
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:anchor>28276</fr:anchor>
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:anchor>28277</fr:anchor>
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
