<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>29850</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml</route> <date>October 6, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2210.02169</meta><meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan and Gratzer, Daniel and Birkedal, Lars},
  year = {2022},
  month = jul,
  note = {Unpublished manuscript},
  title = {Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism},
}</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We contribute the first denotational semantics of polymorphic dependent type theory extended by an equational theory for general (higher-order) reference types and recursive types, based on a combination of guarded recursion and impredicative polymorphism; because our model is based on <em>recursively defined semantic worlds</em>, it is compatible with polymorphism and relational reasoning about stateful abstract datatypes. We then extend our language with modal constructs for proof-relevant relational reasoning based on the <em>logical relations as types</em> principle, in which equivalences between imperative abstract datatypes can be established synthetically. Finally we develop a decomposition of the store model as a general construction that extends an arbitrary polymorphic call-by-push-value adjunction with higher-order store, improving on <link href="paulblainlevy.xml" type="local" title="Paul Blain Levy">Levy</link>'s possible worlds model construction; what is new in relation to prior typed denotational models of higher-order store is that our Kripke worlds need not be syntactically definable, and are thus compatible with relational reasoning in the heap. Our work combines recent advances in the operational semantics of state with the purely denotational viewpoint of <em>synthetic guarded domain theory</em>.</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Person"><frontmatter> <anchor>29852</anchor> <addr>paulblainlevy</addr>  <route>paulblainlevy.xml</route>   <title>Paul Blain Levy</title> <meta name="external">https://www.cs.bham.ac.uk/~pbl/</meta><meta name="position">Reader</meta><meta name="institution">University of Birmingham</meta><meta name="orcid">0000-0003-0864-1876</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> </tree></related> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>29854</anchor> <addr>jms-0078</addr>  <route>jms-0078.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Denotational semantics of higher-order store</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> plan to develop denotational semantics of higher-order store had two components: the first was to develop a practical semantic model of polymorphic higher-order store without garbage collection, and the second was to extend this model to support the equational theory of garbage collection. For the former, the results have greatly outstripped expectations: I have succeeded in constructing not only the indended model of store with polymorphism, but in fact a <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">model of full dependent type theory with higher-order store</link> — posing the prospect for being able to write and verify the correctness of programs in the same language. This result is the first of its kind for higher-order store, and is a significant advance. In the final months of the project, we have also gone further beyond this result in a different direction, and constructed a version of the model of higher-order store satisfying a new gamut of compelling representation independence equations which I refer to as the theory of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml" type="local" title="Free theorems from univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</link>: in short, two programs can be considered equal even if they allocate memory cells of different types, so long as the two types are in bijection and programs' interaction with the memory cell respects this bijection.</p><p>I have begun to extend these results to include the equational theory of garbage collection, but as the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project has been terminated nearly one year early (due to my recent appointment as Associate Professor at University of Cambridge), this further exploitation of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> methodology will continue beyond the conclusion of the project.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>29856</anchor> <addr>jms-007A</addr>  <route>jms-007A.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Effectful <link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">synthetic Tait computability</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A third achievement of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project was to extend the highly successful “<link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">Synthetic Tait Computability</link>” method, developed in my <link href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">doctoral thesis</link>, to the case of realistic programming languages with computational effects. The purpose of this extension was to achieve strong representation independence results, by which we can show the computational indistinguishability of even two programs that allocate memory cells of different types that are linked not by a bijection but by a mere relation, in contrast to univalent reference types. We have gone quite a bit beyond our expectations, as our account of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism"><link href="jms-005T.xml" type="local" title="Synthetic Tait computability">STC</link> for higher-order store</link> applies not only to the simple polymorphic store model, but also to the full dependent type theory. This allows many classic results from the literature that previously required very complicated reasoning with the semantic model to be reconstructed in a simpler and more direct fashion.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>29858</anchor> <addr>jms-0079</addr>  <route>jms-0079.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Equational higher-order separation logic for higher-order store</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>In collaboration with my colleagues <link href="flaagaard.xml" type="local" title="Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard">Frederik Ljerbjerg Aagaard</link> and <link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local" title="Lars Birkedal">Professor Lars Birkedal</link>, I have developed a <link href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml" type="local" title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">guarded higher-order separation logic called TULIP</link> over the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational model of higher-order store</link>. This logic represents a significant step forward in the march toward simple, abstract, and compositional reasoning about higher-order stateful programs. Prior program logics (such as Iris and the Verified Software Toolchain) interact with computer programs only indirectly, by verifying properties of a specific “transition function” that simulates the steps that a (highly idealized) computer would take when executing a program; this style is called “operational”. Unfortunately, the important structural properties of programs are highly unnatural to express at the level of transition steps, and as such, existing operationally-based program logics impose a great deal of bureaucracy by forcing those verifying programs to manually mediate the mismatch between the viewpoint of the machine (which cannot see program structure), and the viewpoint of the programmer (which is entirely based on program structure). An equational, or &quot;denotationally-based&quot;, program logic like <link href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml" type="local" title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</link> instead treats programs directly without needing to pass through an encoding in terms of machine transitions. An immediate benefit of the equational approach is that program equivalences can be glued together directly in any context, a kind of practical compositionality that is unique to equational and denotationally-based program logics. Our development of the <link href="aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml" type="local" title="A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store">TULIP</link> logic is a strong first step in this direction.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>29860</anchor> <addr>jms-007B</addr>  <route>jms-007B.xml</route> <date>August 15, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Results beyond the state of the art</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The results of the <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> project have gone significantly beyond the state of the art in denotational semantics for computational effects: not only is ours the first typed denotational model of higher-order store compatible with parametric polymorphism, but we have shown that the same construction also gives rise to a model of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">full dependent type theory with higher-order store</link> — a long sought-after result whose implications we have not yet fully exploited. Our model of <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml" type="local" title="Free theorems from univalent reference types">“univalent reference types”</link> is also a significant break with the state of the art, and points the way to a new and more fruitful interaction between the fields of programming languages on the one hand, and homotopy type theory and algebraic topology on the other hand.</p><p>The <link href="jms-0077.xml" type="local" title="Work performed and main achievements">technical achievements</link> of <link href="jms-0061.xml" type="local" title="TypeSynth: synthetic methods in program verification">TypeSynth</link> point to healthy growth in the long-neglected area of denotational semantics and equational program logics, but there is an urgent need for further research to bring these superior but comparatively less-developed methods to practical parity with the more established operational paradigm, which currently achieves stronger results in program verification — which we believe can be accounted for by the twenty-year headstart enjoyed by teams favoring operational methods during the relative dormancy of semantic and categorical methods in programming languages. </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>29862</anchor> <addr>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent</addr>  <route>sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2023-univalent.xml</route> <date>July 23, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="danielgratzer.xml" type="local">Daniel Gratzer</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>Free theorems from univalent reference types</title> <meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2307.16608</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We develop a denotational semantics for general reference types in an <link href="awodey-frey-speight-2018.xml" type="local" title="Impredicative encodings of (higher) inductive types">impredicative version</link> of <link href="bbcgsv-2019.xml" type="local" title="Guarded cubical type theory"><b><em>guarded homotopy type theory</em></b></link>, an adaptation of <link href="bmss-2011.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic guarded domain theory: step-indexing in the topos of trees">synthetic guarded domain theory</link> to Voevodsky’s <link href="hottbook.xml" type="local" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics">univalent foundations</link>. We observe for the first time the profound impact of univalence on the <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">denotational semantics of mutable state</link>. Univalence automatically ensures that all computations are invariant under symmetries of the heap—a bountiful source of <link href="wadler-1989.xml" type="local" title="Theorems for free!">free theorems</link>. In particular, even the most simplistic univalent model enjoys many new program equivalences that do not hold when the same constructions are carried out in the universes of traditional set-level (extensional) type theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>29864</anchor> <addr>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023</addr>  <route>aagaard-sterling-birkedal-2023.xml</route> <date>April 8, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="flaagaard.xml" type="local">Frederik Lerbjerg Aagaard</link></author><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="larsbirkedal.xml" type="local">Lars Birkedal</link></author> </authors> <title>A denotationally-based program logic for higher-order store</title> <meta name="external">https://www.cs.au.dk/~birke/papers/tulip.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">39th International Conference on Mathematical Foundations of Programming Semantics</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Separation logic is used to reason locally about stateful programs. State of the art program logics for higher-order store are usually built on top of untyped operational semantics, in part because traditional denotational methods have struggled to simultaneously account for general references and parametric polymorphism. The <link href="sterling-gratzer-birkedal-2022.xml" type="local" title="Denotational semantics of general store and polymorphism">recent discovery</link> of simple denotational semantics for general references and polymorphism in synthetic guarded domain theory has enabled us to develop <b>Tulip</b>, a higher-order separation logic over the typed equational theory of higher-order store for a monadic version of System <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex>. The <b>Tulip</b> logic differs from operationally-based program logics in two ways: predicates range over the meanings of typed terms rather than over the raw code of untyped terms, and they are automatically invariant under the equational congruence of higher-order store, which applies even underneath a binder. As a result, “pure” proof steps that conventionally require focusing the Hoare triple on an operational redex are replaced by a simple equational rewrite in <b>Tulip</b>. We have evaluated <b>Tulip</b> against standard examples involving linked lists in the heap, comparing our abstract equational reasoning with more familiar operational-style reasoning. Our main result is the soundness of <b>Tulip</b>, which we establish by constructing a BI-hyperdoctrine over the denotational semantics of <tex>\textbf{F} ^{ \mu , \textit{ref} }</tex> in an impredicative version of synthetic guarded domain theory.</p></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>