<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16698</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>sterling-harper-2021</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2021.xml</route> <date><year>2021</year> <month>12</month> <day>1</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author> </authors> <title>Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules</title> <meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-harper-2021.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Journal of the ACM, Volume 68, Issue 6</meta><meta name="doi">10.1145/3474834</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The theory of program modules is of interest to language designers not only for its practical importance to programming, but also because it lies at the nexus of three fundamental concerns in language design: the <em>phase distinction</em>, <em>computational effects</em>, and <em>type abstraction</em>. We contribute a fresh “synthetic” take on program modules that treats modules as the fundamental constructs, in which the usual suspects of prior module calculi (kinds, constructors, dynamic programs) are rendered as derived notions in terms of a modal type-theoretic account of the phase distinction. We simplify the account of type abstraction (embodied in the generativity of module functors) through a <em>lax modality</em> that encapsulates computational effects, placing <em>projectibility</em> of module expressions on a type-theoretic basis.</p><p>Our main result is a (significant) proof-relevant and phase-sensitive generalization of the Reynolds abstraction theorem for a calculus of program modules, based on a new kind of logical relation called a <em>parametricity structure</em>. Parametricity structures generalize the proof-irrelevant relations of classical parametricity to proof-<em>relevant</em> families, where there may be non-trivial evidence witnessing the relatedness of two programs—simplifying the metatheory of strong sums over the collection of types, for although there can be no “relation classifying relations,” one easily accommodates a “family classifying small families.”</p><p>Using the insight that logical relations/parametricity is itself a form of phase distinction between the syntactic and the semantic, we contribute a new synthetic approach to phase separated parametricity based on the slogan <em>logical relations as types</em>, by iterating our modal account of the phase distinction. We axiomatize a dependent type theory of parametricity structures using two pairs of complementary modalities (syntactic, semantic) and (static, dynamic), substantiated using the topos theoretic <em>Artin gluing</em> construction. Then, to construct a simulation between two implementations of an abstract type, one simply programs a third implementation whose type component carries the representation invariant.</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>1</crumb></trail> <anchor>16699</anchor> <taxon>Erratum</taxon> <addr>jms-0060</addr>  <route>jms-0060.xml</route> <date><year>2021</year>  </date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Minor mistakes in <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">logical relations as types</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>After going to press, we have fixed the following mistakes:</p><ol>  <li>In the definition of a logos, we mistakenly said that &quot;colimits commute with finite limits&quot; but we meant to say that they are preserved by pullback. We thank Sarah Rovner-Frydman for noticing this mistake.</li>  <li>In Remark 5.15, we used the notation for the closed immersion prior to introducing it.</li>  <li>We have fixed a few broken links in the bibliography.</li></ol><p>The local copy hosted here has the corrections implemented</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16700</anchor>  <addr>jms-0019</addr>  <route>jms-0019.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Chapter 8: a plan for PL</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>This dissertation has focused almost solely on the development and applications of synthetic Tait computability in the context of pure type theory, but the author originally invented synthetic Tait computability to solve problems in core programming languages, as part of <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</link>’s re-analysis of the <em>phase distinction</em> in <link href="harper-mitchell-moggi-1990.xml" type="local" title="Higher-order modules and the phase distinction">ML-style</link> <link href="moggi-1989.xml" type="local" title="A category-theoretic account of program modules">module systems</link> between static (compiletime) and dynamic (runtime) code. The purpose of this chapter is to identify several applications of synthetic Tait computability to core programming languages, and set an agenda for future work — some of which has been executed and published following the completion of this dissertation</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>2</crumb></trail> <anchor>16701</anchor>  <addr>jms-001A</addr>  <route>jms-001A.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A brief overview is given of the applications of synthetic Tait computability to program modules, material that is published in the <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Journal of the ACM</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>3</crumb></trail> <anchor>16702</anchor>  <addr>jms-001B</addr>  <route>jms-001B.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.2: type refinements and program extraction</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The modal language of synthetic Tait computability promises a new and more abstract account of <em>refinement types</em> and <em>program extraction</em> via a phase distinction between <em>computation</em> and <em>specification</em>. Refinement types are often thought of as a kind of subtype, but there is a fundamental difference: when <tex>{ \phi } \sqsubset{A}</tex> and <tex>{ \psi } \sqsubset{B}</tex> are refinements of types <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> respectively, then <tex>\phi \to \psi</tex> refines <tex>A \to  B</tex>. In contrast, subtyping laws for function spaces are contravariant in the domain. The refinements available in synthetic Tait computability are moreover proof-relevant in the sense that specification-level code can contain data in addition to properties. The application to proof-relevant refinement types is employed by <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local" title="A cost-aware logical framework">Niu, Sterling, Grodin, and Harper</link> to develop a logical framework for simultaneously verifying behavior and complexity of functional programs.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>4</crumb></trail> <anchor>16703</anchor>  <addr>jms-001C</addr>  <route>jms-001C.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>20</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.3: information-flow and noninterference</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Finally, an application of synthetic Tait computability to <em>security</em> and <em>information flow control</em> is identified: a security class is a phase distinction between low and high security. The preliminary results presented in this section have been substantially improved upon by <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local" title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">Sterling and Harper</link>, adding support for general recursion and termination-insensitive noninterference by combining synthetic Tait computability with <link href="hyland-1991.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic domain theory">synthetic domain theory</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16704</anchor>  <addr>jms-001A</addr>  <route>jms-001A.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>1</month> <day>19</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>§ 8.1: two phase distinctions for program modules</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A brief overview is given of the applications of synthetic Tait computability to program modules, material that is published in the <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Journal of the ACM</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16705</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>sterling-harper-2022</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2022.xml</route> <date><year>2022</year>  </date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author> </authors> <title>Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference</title> <meta name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.FSCD.2022.5</meta><meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-harper-2022.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">7th International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD 2022)</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>We propose a new sheaf semantics for secure information flow over a space of abstract behaviors, based on synthetic domain theory: security classes are open/closed partitions, types are sheaves, and redaction of sensitive information corresponds to restricting a sheaf to a closed subspace. Our security-aware computational model satisfies termination-insensitive noninterference automatically, and therefore constitutes an intrinsic alternative to state of the art extrinsic/relational models of noninterference. Our semantics is the latest application of <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">Sterling and Harper</link>’s recent re-interpretation of phase distinctions and noninterference in programming languages in terms of Artin gluing and topos-theoretic open/closed modalities. Prior applications include <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">parametricity for ML modules</link>, the proof of normalization for cubical type theory by <link href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml" type="local" title="Normalization for cubical type theory">Sterling and Angiuli</link>, and the cost-aware logical framework of <link href="niu-sterling-grodin-harper-2022.xml" type="local" title="A cost-aware logical framework">Niu et al</link>. In this paper we employ the phase distinction perspective twice: first to reconstruct the syntax and semantics of secure information flow as a lattice of phase distinctions between “higher” and “lower” security, and second to verify the computational adequacy of our sheaf semantics with respect to a version of Abadi et al.’s dependency core calculus to which we have added a construct for declassifying termination channels.</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>5</crumb></trail> <anchor>16706</anchor> <taxon>Erratum</taxon> <addr>jms-005Y</addr>  <route>jms-005Y.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year>  </date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Minor mistakes in <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local" title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">sheaf semantics of noninterference</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>In the published version of this paper, there were a few mistakes that have been corrected in the local copy hosted here.</p><ol>  <li>In the <em>Critique of relational semantics for information flow</em>, our discussion of the <em>Failure of monotonicity</em> stated incorrectly that algebras for the sealing monad at a higher security level could not be transformed into algebras for the sealing monad at a lower security level in the semantics of Abadi et al. This is not true, as pointed out to us privately by Carlos Tomé Cortiñas. What we meant to say was that it is not the case that a type whose component at a high security level is trivial shall always remain trivial at a lower security level.</li>  <li>The original version of the extended edition of this paper, we claimed that the constructive existence of tensor products on pointed dcpos was obvious; in fact, tensor products do exist, but their construction involves a reflexive coequalizer of pointed dcpos.</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>6</crumb></trail> <anchor>16707</anchor> <taxon>Erratum</taxon> <addr>jms-005Z</addr>  <route>jms-005Z.xml</route> <date><year>2023</year> <month>7</month> <day>17</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Adequacy of <link href="sterling-harper-2022.xml" type="local" title="Sheaf semantics of termination-insensitive noninterference">sheaf semantics of noninterference</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>A serious (and as-yet unfixed) problem was discovered in July of 2023 by <link href="yueniu.xml" type="local" title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</link>, which undermines the proof of adequacy given; in particular, the proof that the logical relation on free algebras is admissible is not correct. I believe there is a different proof of adequacy for the calculus described, but it will have a different structure from what currently appears in the paper. We thank <link href="yueniu.xml" type="local" title="Yue Niu">Yue Niu</link> for his attention to detail and careful reading of this paper.</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16708</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>sterling-2021-logsem</addr>  <route>sterling-2021-logsem.xml</route> <date><year>2021</year> <month>11</month> <day>1</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Between abstraction and composition...</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2021-logsem.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Logic and Semantics Seminar, Aarhus University</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The fundamental contradiction of programming and program verification can be located in the tension between abstraction and composition. We make programs more abstract in order to prevent bad interactions between components; on the other side of the coin, we impede the composition of components when we abstract them. Modern programming practice evinces many distinct levels of abstraction that must be considered at the same time — for instance, compilers break module boundaries during linking, complexity analysis breaks the abstraction of extensional equivalence, and logical relations proofs break the abstraction of closure under substitution. What is needed to meet this challenge is linguistic tools that smoothly interpolate between these different levels of abstraction. Building on <link href="sterling-2021-thesis.xml" type="local" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory">my doctoral dissertation</link> and <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">joint work with Bob Harper</link>, I introduce a new plan for modal programming languages and logics that treat the transition between different abstraction levels as a first-class notion.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16709</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>sterling-2021-au-ccs</addr>  <route>sterling-2021-au-ccs.xml</route> <date><year>2021</year> <month>4</month> </date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Logical relations as types</title> <meta name="slides">https://www.jonmsterling.com/slides/sterling-2021-au-ccs.pdf</meta><meta name="video">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AEthjg2k718</meta><meta name="venue">CCS Colloquium, Augusta University</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><em>This is joint work with <link href="robertharper.xml" type="local" title="Robert Harper">Robert Harper</link>.</em></p><p>How do you prove that two implementations of an abstract type behave the same in all configurations? Reynolds famously employed logical relations to establish such results; roughly, a logical relation is a structure-respecting relation between two interpretations of a theory that evinces, in the base case, a desirable invariant.</p><p>We present a synthetic way to understand and interact with logical relations, related to classical logical relations in the same way that Euclidean geometry relates to point-sets. Previously a logical relation was defined in terms of the (complicated) details of how it is constructed as a certain kind of relation over syntax. We instead take the simpler view that everything in sight is a logical relation, and then use modalities to isolate those logical relations that are degenerate in either the syntactic or the semantic direction.</p><p>Our “logical relations as types” principle has led to a new account of modules and representation independence <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">(S., Harper)</link>, as well as the first proofs of normalization for cubical type theory <link href="sterling-angiuli-2021.xml" type="local" title="Normalization for cubical type theory">(S., Angiuli)</link> and general multi-modal dependent type theory <link href="gratzer-2022.xml" type="local" title="Normalization for multimodal type theory">(Gratzer)</link>.</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16710</anchor> <taxon>Erratum</taxon> <addr>jms-0060</addr>  <route>jms-0060.xml</route> <date><year>2021</year>  </date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Minor mistakes in <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">logical relations as types</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>After going to press, we have fixed the following mistakes:</p><ol>  <li>In the definition of a logos, we mistakenly said that &quot;colimits commute with finite limits&quot; but we meant to say that they are preserved by pullback. We thank Sarah Rovner-Frydman for noticing this mistake.</li>  <li>In Remark 5.15, we used the notation for the closed immersion prior to introducing it.</li>  <li>We have fixed a few broken links in the bibliography.</li></ol><p>The local copy hosted here has the corrections implemented</p></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>16711</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>sterling-harper-2021</addr>  <route>sterling-harper-2021.xml</route> <date><year>2021</year> <month>12</month> <day>1</day></date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author><author><link href="robertharper.xml" type="local">Robert Harper</link></author> </authors> <title>Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules</title> <meta name="external">https://www.jonmsterling.com/papers/sterling-harper-2021.pdf</meta><meta name="venue">Journal of the ACM, Volume 68, Issue 6</meta><meta name="doi">10.1145/3474834</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>The theory of program modules is of interest to language designers not only for its practical importance to programming, but also because it lies at the nexus of three fundamental concerns in language design: the <em>phase distinction</em>, <em>computational effects</em>, and <em>type abstraction</em>. We contribute a fresh “synthetic” take on program modules that treats modules as the fundamental constructs, in which the usual suspects of prior module calculi (kinds, constructors, dynamic programs) are rendered as derived notions in terms of a modal type-theoretic account of the phase distinction. We simplify the account of type abstraction (embodied in the generativity of module functors) through a <em>lax modality</em> that encapsulates computational effects, placing <em>projectibility</em> of module expressions on a type-theoretic basis.</p><p>Our main result is a (significant) proof-relevant and phase-sensitive generalization of the Reynolds abstraction theorem for a calculus of program modules, based on a new kind of logical relation called a <em>parametricity structure</em>. Parametricity structures generalize the proof-irrelevant relations of classical parametricity to proof-<em>relevant</em> families, where there may be non-trivial evidence witnessing the relatedness of two programs—simplifying the metatheory of strong sums over the collection of types, for although there can be no “relation classifying relations,” one easily accommodates a “family classifying small families.”</p><p>Using the insight that logical relations/parametricity is itself a form of phase distinction between the syntactic and the semantic, we contribute a new synthetic approach to phase separated parametricity based on the slogan <em>logical relations as types</em>, by iterating our modal account of the phase distinction. We axiomatize a dependent type theory of parametricity structures using two pairs of complementary modalities (syntactic, semantic) and (static, dynamic), substantiated using the topos theoretic <em>Artin gluing</em> construction. Then, to construct a simulation between two implementations of an abstract type, one simply programs a third implementation whose type component carries the representation invariant.</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" root="false"><frontmatter><trail><crumb>7</crumb></trail> <anchor>16712</anchor> <taxon>Erratum</taxon> <addr>jms-0060</addr>  <route>jms-0060.xml</route> <date><year>2021</year>  </date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Minor mistakes in <link href="sterling-harper-2021.xml" type="local" title="Logical relations as types: proof-relevant parametricity for program modules">logical relations as types</link></title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>After going to press, we have fixed the following mistakes:</p><ol>  <li>In the definition of a logos, we mistakenly said that &quot;colimits commute with finite limits&quot; but we meant to say that they are preserved by pullback. We thank Sarah Rovner-Frydman for noticing this mistake.</li>  <li>In Remark 5.15, we used the notation for the closed immersion prior to introducing it.</li>  <li>We have fixed a few broken links in the bibliography.</li></ol><p>The local copy hosted here has the corrections implemented</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></references></backmatter></tree>