<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>17645</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">sterling-2022-wg6</fr:addr><fr:route>sterling-2022-wg6.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability">Naïve logical relations in synthetic Tait computability</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2022</fr:year><fr:month>5</fr:month><fr:day>20</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="jonmsterling.xml"
addr="jonmsterling"
title="Jon Sterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@misc{sterling-2022-wg6,
  author = {Sterling, Jonathan},
  year = {2022},
  month = may,
  note = {WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories (Invited Talk)},
  title = {Na\"{i}ve logical relations in synthetic {Tait} computability},
}]]></fr:meta><fr:meta
name="venue">WG6 kick-off meeting: Syntax and Semantics of Type Theories</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Logical relations are the main tool for proving <fr:em>positive</fr:em> properties of logics, type theories, and programming languages: canonicity, normalization, decidability, conservativity, computational adequacy, and more. Logical relations combine pure syntax with <fr:em>non-syntactic</fr:em> objects that are parameterized in syntax in a somewhat complex way; the sophistication of possible parameterizations makes logical relations a tool that is primarily accessible to specialists. In the spirit of Halmos' book <fr:em>Naïve Set Theory</fr:em>, I advocate for a new viewpoint on logical relations based on <fr:em>synthetic Tait computability</fr:em>, the internal language of categories of logical relations. In synthetic Tait computability, logical relations are manipulated as if they were sets, making the essence of many complex logical relations arguments accessible to non-specialists.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree>