<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jms-forest.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>19854</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:addr>tait-1967</fr:addr><fr:route>tait-1967.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Intensional interpretations of functionals of finite type I</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>1967</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>1</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>William W. Tait</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="doi">10.2307/2271658</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:contributions></fr:contributions><fr:context></fr:context><fr:related></fr:related><fr:backlinks><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>19852</fr:anchor><fr:addr>jms-0015</fr:addr><fr:route>jms-0015.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Chapter 5: synthetic normalization by evaluation</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>2023</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>19</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
href="jonmsterling.xml"
type="local"
addr="jonmsterling">Jon Sterling</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>This chapter develops a more sophisticated application of synthetic Tait computability, the proof of normalization and decidability of Martin-Löf’s type theory with a cumulative hierarchy of universes. The synthetic argument contained in this chapter builds on the work of <fr:link
href="fiore-2002.xml"
type="local"
addr="fiore-2002">Fiore</fr:link> on categorical normalization by gluing for simply typed λ-calculus, and that of <fr:link
href="coquand-2019.xml"
type="local"
addr="coquand-2019">Coquand</fr:link> on a presheaf-theoretic version of normalization by evaluation for dependent types. Analogous to the external argument of <fr:link
href="fiore-2002.xml"
type="local"
addr="fiore-2002">Fiore</fr:link>, we construe the syntax of normal and neutral forms as the initial algebra for an internal inductive definition in the language of synthetic Tait computability. The influence of <fr:link
href="coquand-2019.xml"
type="local"
addr="coquand-2019">Coquand</fr:link> is visible in the definition of the <fr:em>Tait saturation yoga</fr:em> for dependent types in the synthetic setting, an important closure condition for logical predicates that comprised one of the main innovations of <fr:link
href="tait-1967.xml"
type="local"
addr="tait-1967">Tait</fr:link> in the context of simply typed combinators. Although this chapter is intended only as “dry run” for the main result (to be exposed in <fr:link
href="jms-0014.xml"
type="local"
addr="jms-0014">Chapter 7</fr:link>), the normalization argument presented here has intrinsic value: it is the simplest and most direct proof of normalization and decidability for Martin-Löf type theory with <fr:tex>\eta</fr:tex>-laws and cumulative universes that has appeared in the literature so far.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree></fr:backlinks><fr:references></fr:references></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>