<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Person"><frontmatter> <anchor>28050</anchor> <addr>thomasstreicher</addr>  <route>thomasstreicher.xml</route>   <title>Thomas Streicher</title> <meta name="position">Professor</meta><meta name="institution">Technische Universität Darmstadt</meta><meta name="external">https://www2.mathematik.tu-darmstadt.de/~streicher/</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter/> <backmatter><contributions><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false" taxon="Reference"><frontmatter> <anchor>28052</anchor> <addr>streicher-fcjb</addr>  <route>streicher-fcjb.xml</route> <date>December 16, 2022</date> <authors><author><link href="thomasstreicher.xml" type="local">Thomas Streicher</link></author> </authors> <title>Fibred categories à la <link href="jeanbénabou.xml" type="local">Jean Bénabou</link></title> <meta name="bibtex">@unpublished{streicher-fcjb,
  author = {Streicher, Thomas},
  year = {2021},
  eprint = {1801.02927},
  eprintclass = {math.CT},
  eprinttype = {arXiv},
  title = {Fibered Categories \`{a} la {Jean B\'{e}nabou}},
}
</meta><meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.1801.02927</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>These are notes about the theory of Fibred Categories as I have learned it from <link href="jeanbénabou.xml" type="local">Jean Bénabou</link>. I also have used results from the Thesis of Jean-Luc Moens from 1982 in those sections where I discuss the fibered view of geometric morphisms. Thus, almost all of the contents is not due to me but most of it cannot be found in the literature since <link href="jeanbénabou.xml" type="local">Bénabou</link> has given many talks on it but most of his work on fibered categories is unpublished. But I am solely responsible for the mistakes and for misrepresentations of his views. And certainly these notes do not cover all the work he has done on fibered categories. I just try to explain the most important notions he has come up with in a way trying to be as close as possible to his intentions and intuitions. I started these notes in 1999 when I gave a course on some of the material at a workshop in Munich. They have developed quite a lot over the years and I have tried to include most of the things I want to remember.</p></mainmatter> </tree></contributions> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show_heading="true" show_metadata="true" toc="false" root="false"><frontmatter> <anchor>28054</anchor> <addr>jms-0011</addr>  <route>jms-0011.xml</route> <date>January 19, 2023</date> <authors><author><link href="jonmsterling.xml" type="local">Jon Sterling</link></author> </authors> <title>Chapter 3: the theory of universes</title> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>Universes started their life in the <link href="sga-4.xml" type="local">Grothendieck school of algebraic geometry</link> as a technical device to circumvent the annoyance that there cannot be a “set of all sets”; a universe is a set of enough sets, and whilst a universe cannot contain itself, it may nonetheless lie within an even bigger universe. Several important developments in the theory of universes from the 1970s onward by <link href="jeanbénabou.xml" type="local">Bénabou</link>, Martin-Löf, Dybjer, Hofmann, <link href="thomasstreicher.xml" type="local">Streicher</link>, <link href="steveawodey.xml" type="local">Awodey</link>, and others have collided to deliver the present-day understanding of the centrality of universes in semantics: a model of type theory is just a special kind of universe in a special kind of category. This chapter provides expository background on the theory of universes, including a novel account of open and closed subuniverses to reflect the recollement theory of topoi from <link href="jms-0010.xml" type="local">Chapter 2</link>. These open and closed subuniverses will play a critical role in the development of synthetic Tait computability in subsequent chapters.</p></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>