<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors />
    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/wesleyphoa/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>wesleyphoa</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/wesleyphoa/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Wesley Phoa">Wesley Phoa</fr:title>
    <fr:taxon>Person</fr:taxon>
    <fr:meta name="institution">Capital Group</fr:meta>
    <fr:meta name="position">Portfolio Manager</fr:meta>
    <fr:meta name="external">https://www.capitalgroup.com/institutional/about-us/our-people/investment-professionals/wesley-k-phoa.html</fr:meta>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <html:blockquote>Wesley K. Phoa is a solutions portfolio manager at Capital Group. His focus is on fund-of-funds and multi-asset solutions. Wesley serves on the Target Date Solutions Committee, the Portfolio Solutions Committee and the Custom Solutions Committee. He has 29 years of investment experience and has been with Capital Group for 24 years. Earlier in his career at Capital, Wesley served as a fixed income portfolio manager with a focus on rates-driven and long duration strategies. His areas of research responsibility included interest rates, monetary policy and financial economics. He has also been involved in the development of several fund-of-funds strategies and custom solutions for institutional clients. Prior to joining Capital, he was director of research with Capital Management Sciences and a quantitative analyst with Deutsche Bank in Australia. He holds a PhD in pure mathematics from Trinity College at the University of Cambridge and a bachelor’s degree with honors from the Australian National University. He is an elected member of the Conference of Business Economists and the International Conference of Commercial Bank Economists. He sits on the editorial board of The Journal of Portfolio Management. Wesley is based in Los Angeles. Los Angeles.</html:blockquote>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2023</fr:year>
              <fr:month>10</fr:month>
              <fr:day>11</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00AD/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-00AD</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-00AD/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Phoa’s principle"><fr:link href="/wesleyphoa/" title="Wesley Phoa" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/wesleyphoa/" display-uri="wesleyphoa" type="local">Phoa</fr:link>’s principle</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Axiom</fr:taxon>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>The map <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[\Sigma ^\Sigma \to  \Sigma \times \Sigma ]]></fr:tex> sending <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[f]]></fr:tex> to the pair <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[{\mathopen {}\left (f\bot ,f\top \right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex> is an embedding and its image is the subset of <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[\Sigma \times \Sigma ]]></fr:tex> spanned by pairs <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[{\mathopen {}\left (p,q\right )\mathclose {}}]]></fr:tex> such that <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[p=\top ]]></fr:tex> implies <fr:tex display="inline"><![CDATA[q=\top ]]></fr:tex>.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/wesleyphoa/" title="Wesley Phoa" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/wesleyphoa/" display-uri="wesleyphoa" type="local">Wesley Phoa</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>1991</fr:year>
              <fr:month>7</fr:month>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/phoa-1991/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>phoa-1991</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/phoa-1991/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Domain theory in realizability toposes">Domain theory in realizability toposes</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
            <fr:meta name="external">http://www.lfcs.inf.ed.ac.uk/reports/91/ECS-LFCS-91-171/</fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@phdthesis{phoa-1991,
  author = {Phoa, Wesley},
  school = {University of Edinburgh},
  date = {1991-07},
  number = {LFCS-91-171},
  title = {Domain Theory in Realizability Toposes},
}]]></fr:meta>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>This thesis describes some new categories of domains. These categories have two novel, and important, features:</html:p>
            <html:ul><html:li>They are full subcategories of certain toposes. A topos can be regarded as a model of constructive set theory; so our domains are simply sets, with no extra structure. This makes it much simpler to describe constructions on domains: for instance, exponentials are ordinary set-theoretic function spaces.</html:li>
  <html:li>They are small complete categories (in an appropriate sense). This makes it simple to define polymorphic types; it also means that convex powerdomains, for example, exist for quite trivial reasons. The use of category theory, and the internal language of a topos, makes most of the results quite easy to formulate and prove.</html:li></html:ul>
            <html:p>The first part of the thesis is a brief review of Hyland's theory of realizability toposes - in particular, the effective topos, the world of recursive mathematics. Inside each realizability topos is the small compelte category of modest sets, the counterpart of the PER model. We can use it to model various polymorphic typed lambda-calculi, including ones with subtyping.</html:p>
            <html:p>In the next few chapters, we study domains in the effective topos. Following Scott and Rosolini, we base the theory on the notion of r.e. subobject; we use it to define an intrinsic preorder on every object of the topos. Our predomains are the complete Sigma-spaces: the objects for which this preorder is a chain-complete partial order. Every map between two complete Sigma-spaces is automatically monotone and preserves suprema of chains; they form a complete full subcategory for the modest sets.</html:p>
            <html:p>There is a natural notion of lifting for predomains, namely the ‘computable partial map classifier’; this defines a monad on the category, whose algebras are the complete Sigma-spaces with a bottom element - the domains. The categories of predomains and domains have many other attractive properties.</html:p>
            <html:p>In the last couple of chapters, we find categories of domains in other realizability toposes: those based on the Plotkin/Scott graph models, and on the term model of the untyped lambda-calculus in which two terms are identified if they have the same Böhm tree. The methods used are rather different, and the results here are still a little mysterious.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
