<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>Harry Harrison</fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>1984</fr:year>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1984/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>harrison-1984</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/harrison-1984/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="West of Eden">West of Eden</fr:title>
    <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter />
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>3</fr:month>
              <fr:day>23</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019O/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-019O</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-019O/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Winter in Eden and Return to Eden: an imperfect conclusion"><fr:link href="/harrison-1986/" title="Winter in Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1986/" display-uri="harrison-1986" type="local">Winter in Eden</fr:link> and <fr:link href="/harrison-1988/" title="Return to Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1988/" display-uri="harrison-1988" type="local">Return to Eden</fr:link>: an imperfect conclusion</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>Two months ago I <fr:link href="/jms-015W/" title="West of Eden: you can judge a book by its cover" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-015W/" display-uri="jms-015W" type="local">reviewed</fr:link> Harry Harrison’s delightful <fr:link href="/harrison-1984/" title="West of Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1984/" display-uri="harrison-1984" type="local">West of Eden</fr:link>, a piece of speculative fiction that considers a world in which the Cretaceous–Paleogene extinction event never occurred, and one species of dinosaur went on to evolve over the subsequent 66 million years into a highly sophisticated society stratified by uneven linguistic abilities. The most intelligent stratum of this species calls itself <html:em>Yilanè</html:em>, which is at once an ethnonym and a classification of linguistic ability.</html:p>
            <html:p>In Harrison’s Eden, reptiles of all kinds dominate Africa (<html:em>Entoban</html:em> in Yilanè) whereas mankind (<html:em>Tanu</html:em> and <html:em>Sasku</html:em> in their languages) and other mammals live in North America (<html:em>Gendasi</html:em> in Yilanè), confined at first mainly to its colder northern reaches. The icy winds of climate change blow across Entoban and northern Gendasi alike, which leads mankind to migrate south just as the Yilanè begin to colonise southern Gendasi. The encounter of Tanu and Yilanè is predictably violent—when the Tanu encounter the torpid Yilanè males basking on the birthing beaches of Alpèasak (the new Yilanè colony in our own Florida), they slay them immediately and spark a war of the species that shapes the entire trilogy.</html:p>
            <html:figure><html:img height="200px" src="/bafkrmiabjfjguelr6ayscwbzqonts26dkvhmephxe2g5gy5dvjbxuctjem.jpg" />
  <html:img height="200px" src="/bafkrmiacwpt7ky5yniefejcq7nqp7cdlphmvu6ka6zrxgnn63p4t7g4dwi.jpg" />
  <html:img height="200px" src="/bafkrmih7i2jw3w4f353s2sotl3ywcssizf5crvycejoxcuvwlinmax5u7a.jpg" />

 <html:figcaption>Covers of the Eden Trilogy.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
            <html:p>That is the premise of <fr:link href="/harrison-1984/" title="West of Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1984/" display-uri="harrison-1984" type="local">West of Eden</fr:link>, the first book of the Eden Trilogy, which tells the story of a young Tanu man named Kerrick who is kidnapped and raised by Yilanè in Alpèasak. The next two books, <fr:link href="/harrison-1986/" title="Winter in Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1986/" display-uri="harrison-1986" type="local">Winter in Eden</fr:link> and <fr:link href="/harrison-1988/" title="Return to Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1988/" display-uri="harrison-1988" type="local">Return to Eden</fr:link>, concern the continuing struggle of Tanu and their Sasku allies to survive in the South while being pursued by a genocidal Yilanè expedition, and of the minority faction of Yilanè called the <html:em>Daughters of Life</html:em> who aim to establish a peaceful city in South America.</html:p>
            <html:p>Although <fr:link href="/harrison-1986/" title="Winter in Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1986/" display-uri="harrison-1986" type="local">Winter in Eden</fr:link> and <fr:link href="/harrison-1988/" title="Return to Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1988/" display-uri="harrison-1988" type="local">Return to Eden</fr:link> share the charm of the <fr:link href="/harrison-1984/" title="West of Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1984/" display-uri="harrison-1984" type="local">first book</fr:link>, they do not quite live up to its promise. Without revealing anything that might spoil the Trilogy (which I do still recommend), there are several imperfections that give a reader the distinct impression of rushed writing—especially in <fr:link href="/harrison-1988/" title="Return to Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1988/" display-uri="harrison-1988" type="local">Return</fr:link>.</html:p>
            <html:ul><html:li>Throughout <fr:link href="/harrison-1988/" title="Return to Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1988/" display-uri="harrison-1988" type="local">Return to Eden</fr:link> the toponyms <html:em>Gendasi</html:em> and <html:em>Entoban</html:em> are frequently mixed up, leading to a great deal of confusion. For example, Vaintè says “But Entoban is large, most of it unknown to us, warm and filled with good meat” but this could only refer to Gendasi in the context of the novel. I am apparently not the only person to notice this oversight, as can be seen by perusing the <fr:link href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Return-Eden-Harry-Harrison/dp/0246126132" type="external">Amazon reviews</fr:link>.</html:li>
 <html:li>Relatedly, there is no explicit toponym for South America, which plays an important role in the story. Indeed, South America appears to be referred to as part of Gendasi, which makes sense considering the land bridge that joins it to North America, but in that case it is surprising that Gendasi is glossed as North America rather than The Americas.</html:li>
 <html:li>Several interesting story-lines appear to be dropped on the floor. What of the scientist Ambalasei’s fate, and will the radical city <html:em>Ambalasokei</html:em> survive?</html:li></html:ul>
            <html:p>Perhaps what was needed most was more time. Despite these imperfections, I don’t regret my time in Eden—and I dream of returning there one day.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>1</fr:month>
              <fr:day>25</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-015W/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-015W</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-015W/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="West of Eden: you can judge a book by its cover"><fr:link href="/harrison-1984/" title="West of Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1984/" display-uri="harrison-1984" type="local">West of Eden</fr:link>: you <html:em>can</html:em> judge a book by its cover</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>I have found that one could do far worse than perusing the <fr:link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/CoolSciFiCovers/" type="external">r/CoolSciFiCovers</fr:link> subreddit and picking things to read at random. This week I chose <fr:link href="/harrison-1984/" title="West of Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1984/" display-uri="harrison-1984" type="local">West of Eden</fr:link> based on its outstanding cover art, and it turned out to be a very enjoyable read.</html:p>
            <html:figure><html:img width="200px" src="/bafkrmiabjfjguelr6ayscwbzqonts26dkvhmephxe2g5gy5dvjbxuctjem.jpg" />
 <html:figcaption>The cover of <fr:link href="/harrison-1984/" title="West of Eden" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/harrison-1984/" display-uri="harrison-1984" type="local">West of Eden</fr:link>, by Harry Harrison and illustrated by Bill Sanderson.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
            <html:p>The premise is that the impact causing the mass extinction of non-avian dinosaurs never occurred, and neolithic Man unknowingly shares the Earth with a very advanced and highly stratified female-dominated race of intelligent lizards whose males have two penises (<html:del>don’t ask me why!</html:del> <html:ins>apparently this is common in nature</html:ins>). When climate change threatens both the human and lizard civilisations, they are forced to migrate and, in doing so, discover each other’s presence and clash violently.</html:p>
            <html:p>Some aspects of the story are a little old-fashioned—I barely need to discuss the instinctive disgust and “racial hatred” felt by the humans and the lizards for each other, but the narrative ultimately challenges this feeling by revealing each culture to be civilised in its own terms, if not in terms that would lead to a cooperative multi-species stewardship of the Earth.</html:p>
            <html:p>The initial inability of the intelligent lizards to fathom that the “filthy ustuzou”—the lizard phrase for humans and other mammalian creatures—may be sentient and even conscious entities of moral force is challenged by their experience, and by a religious extremist trend within their society that recognises the intrinsic value of all forms of conscious life. In a time where current science continues to reveal, bit by bit, the overconfident ignorance and moral wickedness of those who have insisted that the “lower forms of life” on our own Earth are without sentience, value, moral force (the octopus, the elephant, etc.), it is hard to read this without thinking about our own “filthy ustuzou” and the future consequences of our vicious behaviour toward them.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
