<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AJ/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AJ</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/jms-01AJ/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work › With a little love, everything has a use"><fr:link href="/jms-01AH/" title="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/" display-uri="jms-01AH" type="local">Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work</fr:link> › With a little love, <html:em>everything</html:em> has a use</fr:title>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <html:p>Last week I finally realised that there is a lot I can still do with this machine. I turned it on when I had a bit of free time, and found that it remains very snappy—software opens instantly without hanging, and in fact the built-in programs are significantly less bug-ridden than they were in subsequent versions of Mac OS X and its (unworthy) successor macOS. To put this into perspective, the “outdated” iMac’s performance was far better than that of my last Intel iMac from 2020 with sixteen times the RAM and several times the processor cores.</html:p>
    <html:p>It is well-known that hardware capabilities get better and better each year, but this did not translate into improved performance for users until after the Apple Silicon transition—when the hardware improvement was so great that it was able to outpace the deathmarch of inefficient software, for a time. Don’t worry, the “transition to AI” is going to destroy all those gains soon and we’ll be back where we started.</html:p>
    <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiaaxhqvbslbd3sb6mafhlrxswbdbwipj4bzhuewlg7il73mhq7l7y.jpeg" />

    <html:figcaption>Mac OS X Tiger is still King—with the peak versions of Finder, Preview, and iTunes.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
    <html:p>But I digress. Even if you can’t use the Web, there are many things that a 19 year old iMac running Mac OS X Tiger is better at than a more recently manufactured machine. For example, Tiger was the last version of Mac OS X in which Preview.app (the PDF and image viewer) had a working search interface; from the subsequent version (Leopard) all the way until the present day, searching is somehow both too fuzzy and not fuzzy enough, and there seems to be no combination of quotation marks that will lead to reasonable results appearing in the search pane. (Same with Mail.app, which has somehow got <html:em>even worse</html:em> in the past year; you can’t connect to email on such an old machine anyway, so the point is moot.)</html:p>
    <html:p>Similarly, iTunes 7 was the functional peak for Apple’s music management and playback software (although iTunes 6 was visually superior), and people who have only used Apple’s current “Music” app will not be able to understand what they are missing. Likewise, the version of Finder shipped with Tiger was the most polished and least buggy version they ever produced; it is really amazing to switch back and forth between macOS 15.3 and Mac OS X 10.4, and find that most of the bugs or usability problems I have encountered on a daily basis for the past decade or so are actually <html:em>regressions</html:em>.</html:p>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AK/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AK</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/jms-01AK/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="The perfect music and PDF reading workstation">The perfect music and PDF reading workstation</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:p>So I transferred my music and PDF libraries to the iMac—this was easy to do by creating a local WiFi network from the iMac, a functionality that has been removed in macOS(!). Indeed, modern macOS has replaced some (but not all) aspects of this functionality with what is called “Internet Sharing”, but this feature does not work reliably and in many cases the needful functionalities are unpredictably grayed out and disabled without any message explaining why. Death by a thousand papercuts... But I digress: I set up a local WiFi network with a file server easily using the old <html:em>System Preferences</html:em> application (don’t get me started on the bizarre redesign of System Settings introduced in macOS Ventura), and easily transferred everything I wanted to the iMac and then I was off to the races.</html:p>
        <html:p>I listen to music and study papers on this machine, and it gives me so much joy to <html:em>use</html:em> this masterpiece of practical industrial design every day—I even write referee reports on it using an ancient version of <fr:link href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnioutliner/" type="external">OmniOutliner</fr:link>, a venerable piece of software that I have to say has not improved much in the past two decades. After installing a copy of <fr:link href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/scrivener" type="external">Scrivener 2.5</fr:link> (don’t worry, I own a license for <fr:link href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/" type="external">Scrivener 3.0</fr:link> and you should too!), I find myself creative writing in my free time like it’s 2006.</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AL/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AL</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/jms-01AL/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="What about my iPod Classic?">What about my iPod Classic?</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:p>Some of you may be aware that I use an iPod Classic every day. The thing is a godsend—the best mobile device I own. I bought it with a fresh battery and SSD, and the damn battery lasts for months before I have to recharge it. That is the kind of technology that was taken from us and replaced by resource-intensive devices governed by the logic of planned obsolescence. But I have it back—my world is not the same as your world, but it is a world I am glad to have returned to.</html:p>
        <html:p>Naturally, the first thing I wanted to do was use the iMac as a hub for synchronising the iPod with iTunes. This will work, but what I did not anticipate is that one of my main uses of the iPod is to listen to podcasts, and podcasts cannot be downloaded on the iMac because of the vicious imposition of TLS on all parts of the web that didn’t need it (<fr:link href="https://letsencrypt.org/" type="external">Let’s Encrypt</fr:link> really ought to have been called <html:em>Let’s Kill The Open Web</html:em>). So I continue synchronising my iPod with my modern day MacBook Air—and it is a testament to Apple’s historical approach to backward compatibility that this is still possible (and even integrated with the otherwise terrible Podcasts app!).</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AH</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-01AH/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work">Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>Over the Christmas holiday, I bought an iMac off eBay for £50. Why was it so cheap? Because it is a 2006 model firing on a single gigabyte of RAM with an Intel Core 2 Duo processor, running Mac OS X Tiger. When I was a kid, I dreamed of having a computer like this—for me, the white plastic era will always be peak Apple design, and Tiger’s version of Aqua was the most polished and refined form of the design language that they ever managed to produce. My first Macintosh was a white polycarbonate unibody MacBook running Leopard—and at the time I greatly regretted having just missed the Tiger era for the gaudy and overly darkened feel of Leopard with its sinister-coloured window controls. I did not know at the time how much worse things would get…</html:p>
            <html:p>My excuse for purchasing this machine was that I “needed” to run Mac OS X Tiger as “research” for my experimental project <fr:link href="https://github.com/jonsterling/aquaui" type="external">AquaUI</fr:link>, which imagines how the Aqua design language could have evolved if it had been allowed to. But really, I wanted to relive my rare trips to Apple retailers as a kid, where I would spend minutes doing nothing but just moving the scrollbar while watching its stationary “wave” texture, or highlighting buttons to see them burst with blue radiance.</html:p>
            <html:p>(I spoke about many of the topics covered in this post in my appearance on the <fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/" type="external">Kodsnack podcast</fr:link> hosted by Fredrik Björeman: <html:em><fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/international/626/" type="external">Episode 626, “The great flattening of everything”</fr:link></html:em>.)</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AI/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AI</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AI/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?">Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>When the delivery came, I took the machine gingerly out of its battered and taped over original packaging and turned it on to a feeling of great excitement, which quickly gave way to loss and melancholy: so much of what computers are “for” involves the World Wide Web, and the forced transition to HTTPS/TLS has stolen access to the Web from users of many working computers of access to the Web (unless they gut the machine by downgrading to a modern but severely less polished operating system, like Linux). The old Intel Macs are a prime example of this loss—although some <fr:link href="https://tenfourfox.blogspot.com/" type="external">volunteer projects exist</fr:link> to enable safe access to the Web for PowerPC machines, older Intel Macintoshes have received comparatively less attention. Capitalist forced obsolescence comes to all, however, and there will no doubt come a time when the “necessary” “security” routines will simply not be executable with the kinds of hardware resources that could be mustered in 2006, no matter the system architecture. After playing around and finding much of the functionality crippled due to being barred from the Internet, I had to ask myself, <html:strong>What should I even do with this thing?</html:strong></html:p>
                <html:p>The iMac lay dormant in my <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> room for the next few months while I figured out an answer to that question.</html:p>
                <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiejjxl32uo7vfhgpkbkxuiww4vabuu745bhajcrleqi7uz4blqjay.gif" />

    <html:figcaption>My iMac sleeping peacefully in my office at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">Clare College</fr:link> Memorial Court, connected to a vintage A1048 keyboard and Apple Pro Mouse (as it should be!). Nearby is my iPod Classic, which I use for about an hour each day and charge once every 6-8 weeks.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AJ/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AJ</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AJ/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="With a little love, everything has a use">With a little love, <html:em>everything</html:em> has a use</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Last week I finally realised that there is a lot I can still do with this machine. I turned it on when I had a bit of free time, and found that it remains very snappy—software opens instantly without hanging, and in fact the built-in programs are significantly less bug-ridden than they were in subsequent versions of Mac OS X and its (unworthy) successor macOS. To put this into perspective, the “outdated” iMac’s performance was far better than that of my last Intel iMac from 2020 with sixteen times the RAM and several times the processor cores.</html:p>
                <html:p>It is well-known that hardware capabilities get better and better each year, but this did not translate into improved performance for users until after the Apple Silicon transition—when the hardware improvement was so great that it was able to outpace the deathmarch of inefficient software, for a time. Don’t worry, the “transition to AI” is going to destroy all those gains soon and we’ll be back where we started.</html:p>
                <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiaaxhqvbslbd3sb6mafhlrxswbdbwipj4bzhuewlg7il73mhq7l7y.jpeg" />

    <html:figcaption>Mac OS X Tiger is still King—with the peak versions of Finder, Preview, and iTunes.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
                <html:p>But I digress. Even if you can’t use the Web, there are many things that a 19 year old iMac running Mac OS X Tiger is better at than a more recently manufactured machine. For example, Tiger was the last version of Mac OS X in which Preview.app (the PDF and image viewer) had a working search interface; from the subsequent version (Leopard) all the way until the present day, searching is somehow both too fuzzy and not fuzzy enough, and there seems to be no combination of quotation marks that will lead to reasonable results appearing in the search pane. (Same with Mail.app, which has somehow got <html:em>even worse</html:em> in the past year; you can’t connect to email on such an old machine anyway, so the point is moot.)</html:p>
                <html:p>Similarly, iTunes 7 was the functional peak for Apple’s music management and playback software (although iTunes 6 was visually superior), and people who have only used Apple’s current “Music” app will not be able to understand what they are missing. Likewise, the version of Finder shipped with Tiger was the most polished and least buggy version they ever produced; it is really amazing to switch back and forth between macOS 15.3 and Mac OS X 10.4, and find that most of the bugs or usability problems I have encountered on a daily basis for the past decade or so are actually <html:em>regressions</html:em>.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AK/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AK</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AK/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="The perfect music and PDF reading workstation">The perfect music and PDF reading workstation</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>So I transferred my music and PDF libraries to the iMac—this was easy to do by creating a local WiFi network from the iMac, a functionality that has been removed in macOS(!). Indeed, modern macOS has replaced some (but not all) aspects of this functionality with what is called “Internet Sharing”, but this feature does not work reliably and in many cases the needful functionalities are unpredictably grayed out and disabled without any message explaining why. Death by a thousand papercuts... But I digress: I set up a local WiFi network with a file server easily using the old <html:em>System Preferences</html:em> application (don’t get me started on the bizarre redesign of System Settings introduced in macOS Ventura), and easily transferred everything I wanted to the iMac and then I was off to the races.</html:p>
                    <html:p>I listen to music and study papers on this machine, and it gives me so much joy to <html:em>use</html:em> this masterpiece of practical industrial design every day—I even write referee reports on it using an ancient version of <fr:link href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnioutliner/" type="external">OmniOutliner</fr:link>, a venerable piece of software that I have to say has not improved much in the past two decades. After installing a copy of <fr:link href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/scrivener" type="external">Scrivener 2.5</fr:link> (don’t worry, I own a license for <fr:link href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/" type="external">Scrivener 3.0</fr:link> and you should too!), I find myself creative writing in my free time like it’s 2006.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AL/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AL</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AL/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="What about my iPod Classic?">What about my iPod Classic?</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Some of you may be aware that I use an iPod Classic every day. The thing is a godsend—the best mobile device I own. I bought it with a fresh battery and SSD, and the damn battery lasts for months before I have to recharge it. That is the kind of technology that was taken from us and replaced by resource-intensive devices governed by the logic of planned obsolescence. But I have it back—my world is not the same as your world, but it is a world I am glad to have returned to.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Naturally, the first thing I wanted to do was use the iMac as a hub for synchronising the iPod with iTunes. This will work, but what I did not anticipate is that one of my main uses of the iPod is to listen to podcasts, and podcasts cannot be downloaded on the iMac because of the vicious imposition of TLS on all parts of the web that didn’t need it (<fr:link href="https://letsencrypt.org/" type="external">Let’s Encrypt</fr:link> really ought to have been called <html:em>Let’s Kill The Open Web</html:em>). So I continue synchronising my iPod with my modern day MacBook Air—and it is a testament to Apple’s historical approach to backward compatibility that this is still possible (and even integrated with the otherwise terrible Podcasts app!).</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AM/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AM</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AM/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Is retrocomputing sustainable?">Is retrocomputing sustainable?</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>I constantly feel a pang in the back of my throat when I think about retrocomputing over the long term. We are scrounging around for intact pieces of old technology, but there will come a time when these are too scarce, or when we have really lost the ability to repair them. It is like living in a post-apocalyptic film where a cataclysm has made all manufacturing impossible—but today the cataclysm is not a war or even a virus, but just the simple vicious logic of Capital and a technology industry that has hitched itself to the most ignorant and anti-human trends emanating from the most technologically ignorant people on Wall Street.</html:p>
                <html:p>Retrocomputing is decidedly <html:em>not</html:em> sustainable, in the same sense that living on a stash of canned foods that can no longer be manufactured cannot be sustainable. But also unsustainable is the present day technological treadmill of consumer goods containing precious metals and dangerous chemicals being produced in the billions and sent directly almost directly to the landfill.</html:p>
                <html:p>I think a better question to ask is whether retrocomputing is <html:em>progressive</html:em>. I think that retrocomputing can be progressive insofar as it is part of a practice of looking <html:em>forward</html:em>—how can we build sovereign technology that respects constrained resources as well as users of different abilities, and cannot be taken away or made useless by Capital and the irrational whims of the stock market. Such a project <html:em>must</html:em> have a significant design component, and this cannot be done amateurishly; looking to the iconic design languages of the past for inspiration and education is, then, deeply progressive in this environment.</html:p>
                <html:p>The tragedy of Mac OS X is not that Apple took it away and replaced it with something inferior: the tragedy is that free software communities have never managed to produce something even remotely approaching its level of fit and finish. Volunteer projects do not deserve my ire, which I reserve for our economic system in which nearly <html:em>all</html:em> competent design work is confined to corporate environments, and then wiped away when the wind shifts.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AN/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AN</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AN/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Bring back the joy in computing!">Bring back the joy in computing!</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Forget your troubles and find something that makes you smile, and reminds you of what is possible when a team brimming with talent comes together to build something beautiful.</html:p>
                <html:p>Write to me with any joyful and quirky projects, hardware or software, that you would like to share.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
