<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
      <fr:day>15</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W16/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>2025-W16</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/2025-W16/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W16">Weeknotes 2025-W16</fr:title>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <html:p>I thought I had less to say than <fr:link href="/2025-W15/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W15" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W15/" display-uri="2025-W15" type="local">last week</fr:link>, but then I started reflecting on my current experiments with retrocomputing and before I knew it, I had written an <fr:link href="/jms-01AH/" title="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/" display-uri="jms-01AH" type="local">entire blog post</fr:link> about it which I have transcluded below.</html:p>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AH</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/jms-01AH/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work">Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:p>Over the Christmas holiday, I bought an iMac off eBay for £50. Why was it so cheap? Because it is a 2006 model firing on a single gigabyte of RAM with an Intel Core 2 Duo processor, running Mac OS X Tiger. When I was a kid, I dreamed of having a computer like this—for me, the white plastic era will always be peak Apple design, and Tiger’s version of Aqua was the most polished and refined form of the design language that they ever managed to produce. My first Macintosh was a white polycarbonate unibody MacBook running Leopard—and at the time I greatly regretted having just missed the Tiger era for the gaudy and overly darkened feel of Leopard with its sinister-coloured window controls. I did not know at the time how much worse things would get…</html:p>
        <html:p>My excuse for purchasing this machine was that I “needed” to run Mac OS X Tiger as “research” for my experimental project <fr:link href="https://github.com/jonsterling/aquaui" type="external">AquaUI</fr:link>, which imagines how the Aqua design language could have evolved if it had been allowed to. But really, I wanted to relive my rare trips to Apple retailers as a kid, where I would spend minutes doing nothing but just moving the scrollbar while watching its stationary “wave” texture, or highlighting buttons to see them burst with blue radiance.</html:p>
        <html:p>(I spoke about many of the topics covered in this post in my appearance on the <fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/" type="external">Kodsnack podcast</fr:link> hosted by Fredrik Björeman: <html:em><fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/international/626/" type="external">Episode 626, “The great flattening of everything”</fr:link></html:em>.)</html:p>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AI/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AI</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-01AI/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?">Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>When the delivery came, I took the machine gingerly out of its battered and taped over original packaging and turned it on to a feeling of great excitement, which quickly gave way to loss and melancholy: so much of what computers are “for” involves the World Wide Web, and the forced transition to HTTPS/TLS has stolen access to the Web from users of many working computers of access to the Web (unless they gut the machine by downgrading to a modern but severely less polished operating system, like Linux). The old Intel Macs are a prime example of this loss—although some <fr:link href="https://tenfourfox.blogspot.com/" type="external">volunteer projects exist</fr:link> to enable safe access to the Web for PowerPC machines, older Intel Macintoshes have received comparatively less attention. Capitalist forced obsolescence comes to all, however, and there will no doubt come a time when the “necessary” “security” routines will simply not be executable with the kinds of hardware resources that could be mustered in 2006, no matter the system architecture. After playing around and finding much of the functionality crippled due to being barred from the Internet, I had to ask myself, <html:strong>What should I even do with this thing?</html:strong></html:p>
            <html:p>The iMac lay dormant in my <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> room for the next few months while I figured out an answer to that question.</html:p>
            <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiejjxl32uo7vfhgpkbkxuiww4vabuu745bhajcrleqi7uz4blqjay.gif" />

    <html:figcaption>My iMac sleeping peacefully in my office at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">Clare College</fr:link> Memorial Court, connected to a vintage A1048 keyboard and Apple Pro Mouse (as it should be!). Nearby is my iPod Classic, which I use for about an hour each day and charge once every 6-8 weeks.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AJ/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AJ</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-01AJ/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="With a little love, everything has a use">With a little love, <html:em>everything</html:em> has a use</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>Last week I finally realised that there is a lot I can still do with this machine. I turned it on when I had a bit of free time, and found that it remains very snappy—software opens instantly without hanging, and in fact the built-in programs are significantly less bug-ridden than they were in subsequent versions of Mac OS X and its (unworthy) successor macOS. To put this into perspective, the “outdated” iMac’s performance was far better than that of my last Intel iMac from 2020 with sixteen times the RAM and several times the processor cores.</html:p>
            <html:p>It is well-known that hardware capabilities get better and better each year, but this did not translate into improved performance for users until after the Apple Silicon transition—when the hardware improvement was so great that it was able to outpace the deathmarch of inefficient software, for a time. Don’t worry, the “transition to AI” is going to destroy all those gains soon and we’ll be back where we started.</html:p>
            <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiaaxhqvbslbd3sb6mafhlrxswbdbwipj4bzhuewlg7il73mhq7l7y.jpeg" />

    <html:figcaption>Mac OS X Tiger is still King—with the peak versions of Finder, Preview, and iTunes.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
            <html:p>But I digress. Even if you can’t use the Web, there are many things that a 19 year old iMac running Mac OS X Tiger is better at than a more recently manufactured machine. For example, Tiger was the last version of Mac OS X in which Preview.app (the PDF and image viewer) had a working search interface; from the subsequent version (Leopard) all the way until the present day, searching is somehow both too fuzzy and not fuzzy enough, and there seems to be no combination of quotation marks that will lead to reasonable results appearing in the search pane. (Same with Mail.app, which has somehow got <html:em>even worse</html:em> in the past year; you can’t connect to email on such an old machine anyway, so the point is moot.)</html:p>
            <html:p>Similarly, iTunes 7 was the functional peak for Apple’s music management and playback software (although iTunes 6 was visually superior), and people who have only used Apple’s current “Music” app will not be able to understand what they are missing. Likewise, the version of Finder shipped with Tiger was the most polished and least buggy version they ever produced; it is really amazing to switch back and forth between macOS 15.3 and Mac OS X 10.4, and find that most of the bugs or usability problems I have encountered on a daily basis for the past decade or so are actually <html:em>regressions</html:em>.</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AK/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AK</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AK/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="The perfect music and PDF reading workstation">The perfect music and PDF reading workstation</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>So I transferred my music and PDF libraries to the iMac—this was easy to do by creating a local WiFi network from the iMac, a functionality that has been removed in macOS(!). Indeed, modern macOS has replaced some (but not all) aspects of this functionality with what is called “Internet Sharing”, but this feature does not work reliably and in many cases the needful functionalities are unpredictably grayed out and disabled without any message explaining why. Death by a thousand papercuts... But I digress: I set up a local WiFi network with a file server easily using the old <html:em>System Preferences</html:em> application (don’t get me started on the bizarre redesign of System Settings introduced in macOS Ventura), and easily transferred everything I wanted to the iMac and then I was off to the races.</html:p>
                <html:p>I listen to music and study papers on this machine, and it gives me so much joy to <html:em>use</html:em> this masterpiece of practical industrial design every day—I even write referee reports on it using an ancient version of <fr:link href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnioutliner/" type="external">OmniOutliner</fr:link>, a venerable piece of software that I have to say has not improved much in the past two decades. After installing a copy of <fr:link href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/scrivener" type="external">Scrivener 2.5</fr:link> (don’t worry, I own a license for <fr:link href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/" type="external">Scrivener 3.0</fr:link> and you should too!), I find myself creative writing in my free time like it’s 2006.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AL/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AL</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AL/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="What about my iPod Classic?">What about my iPod Classic?</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Some of you may be aware that I use an iPod Classic every day. The thing is a godsend—the best mobile device I own. I bought it with a fresh battery and SSD, and the damn battery lasts for months before I have to recharge it. That is the kind of technology that was taken from us and replaced by resource-intensive devices governed by the logic of planned obsolescence. But I have it back—my world is not the same as your world, but it is a world I am glad to have returned to.</html:p>
                <html:p>Naturally, the first thing I wanted to do was use the iMac as a hub for synchronising the iPod with iTunes. This will work, but what I did not anticipate is that one of my main uses of the iPod is to listen to podcasts, and podcasts cannot be downloaded on the iMac because of the vicious imposition of TLS on all parts of the web that didn’t need it (<fr:link href="https://letsencrypt.org/" type="external">Let’s Encrypt</fr:link> really ought to have been called <html:em>Let’s Kill The Open Web</html:em>). So I continue synchronising my iPod with my modern day MacBook Air—and it is a testament to Apple’s historical approach to backward compatibility that this is still possible (and even integrated with the otherwise terrible Podcasts app!).</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AM/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AM</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-01AM/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Is retrocomputing sustainable?">Is retrocomputing sustainable?</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>I constantly feel a pang in the back of my throat when I think about retrocomputing over the long term. We are scrounging around for intact pieces of old technology, but there will come a time when these are too scarce, or when we have really lost the ability to repair them. It is like living in a post-apocalyptic film where a cataclysm has made all manufacturing impossible—but today the cataclysm is not a war or even a virus, but just the simple vicious logic of Capital and a technology industry that has hitched itself to the most ignorant and anti-human trends emanating from the most technologically ignorant people on Wall Street.</html:p>
            <html:p>Retrocomputing is decidedly <html:em>not</html:em> sustainable, in the same sense that living on a stash of canned foods that can no longer be manufactured cannot be sustainable. But also unsustainable is the present day technological treadmill of consumer goods containing precious metals and dangerous chemicals being produced in the billions and sent directly almost directly to the landfill.</html:p>
            <html:p>I think a better question to ask is whether retrocomputing is <html:em>progressive</html:em>. I think that retrocomputing can be progressive insofar as it is part of a practice of looking <html:em>forward</html:em>—how can we build sovereign technology that respects constrained resources as well as users of different abilities, and cannot be taken away or made useless by Capital and the irrational whims of the stock market. Such a project <html:em>must</html:em> have a significant design component, and this cannot be done amateurishly; looking to the iconic design languages of the past for inspiration and education is, then, deeply progressive in this environment.</html:p>
            <html:p>The tragedy of Mac OS X is not that Apple took it away and replaced it with something inferior: the tragedy is that free software communities have never managed to produce something even remotely approaching its level of fit and finish. Volunteer projects do not deserve my ire, which I reserve for our economic system in which nearly <html:em>all</html:em> competent design work is confined to corporate environments, and then wiped away when the wind shifts.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AN/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AN</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-01AN/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Bring back the joy in computing!">Bring back the joy in computing!</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>Forget your troubles and find something that makes you smile, and reminds you of what is possible when a team brimming with talent comes together to build something beautiful.</html:p>
            <html:p>Write to me with any joyful and quirky projects, hardware or software, that you would like to share.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>15</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>18</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AO/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AO</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/jms-01AO/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="Jem Lord at HoTT/UF in Genoa"><fr:link href="/jemlord/" title="Jem Lord" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jemlord/" display-uri="jemlord" type="local">Jem Lord</fr:link> at <fr:link href="/hott-uf-2025/" title="HoTT-UF ’25: Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory/ Univalent Foundations" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hott-uf-2025/" display-uri="hott-uf-2025" type="local">HoTT/UF</fr:link> in Genoa</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:p>My first-year PhD student <fr:link href="/jemlord/" title="Jem Lord" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jemlord/" display-uri="jemlord" type="local">Jem Lord</fr:link> presented <fr:link href="https://hott-uf.github.io/2025/abstracts/HoTTUF_2025_paper_21.pdf" type="external">their work on <html:em>Easy Parametricity</html:em></fr:link> at the <fr:link href="/hott-uf-2025/" title="HoTT-UF ’25: Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory/ Univalent Foundations" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hott-uf-2025/" display-uri="hott-uf-2025" type="local">HoTT/UF</fr:link> workshop in Genoa this week. Although I was not able to come in person, a little birdy told me that Jem gave a very good talk, so I’m proud of them for that. Congratulations, Jem!</html:p>
        <html:p>Jem’s work concerns a very simple parametricity axiom for a universe <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math> in type theory: namely, that every <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-small type <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> be <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-null in the sense of <fr:link href="/rijke-shulman-spitters-2020/" title="Modalities in homotopy type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/rijke-shulman-spitters-2020/" display-uri="rijke-shulman-spitters-2020" type="local">Rijke, Shulman and Spitters</fr:link>. This is a mathematical way to say that small types “cannot see” their universe; another way to phrase it is that every function <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">→</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> for <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> is constant. One of Jem’s results, which has a startling proof(!), is that when <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">C</mml:mi></mml:math> is a category that is complete with respect to certain <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-small diagrams and <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mml:mi></mml:math> is locally <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-small category, any “unnatural” transformation between functors <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">F</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">,</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">G</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">C</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">→</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> is automatically natural. Many similar results can be obtained in the same way.</html:p>
        <html:p>There are a variety of models of these axioms. One example is the impredicative universe of modest types within a category of assemblies, which is the “standard” categorical model of both System F and the original calculus of constructions. The same principle will work within <fr:link href="/uemura-2019-types/" title="Cubical assemblies, a univalent and impredicative universe and a failure of propositional resizing" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/uemura-2019-types/" display-uri="uemura-2019-types" type="local">cubical assemblies</fr:link>.</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>15</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>18</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AP/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AP</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/jms-01AP/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="Speaking at YaMCaTS 37 next week">Speaking at <fr:link href="/yamcats-37/" title="Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar 37" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/yamcats-37/" display-uri="yamcats-37" type="local">YaMCaTS 37</fr:link> next week</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:p>I am traveling to Sheffield on Tuesday, to speak at the <fr:link href="/yamcats-37/" title="Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar 37" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/yamcats-37/" display-uri="yamcats-37" type="local">Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar</fr:link> the following day. I haven’t prepared my talk yet, but I will be speaking about my <fr:link href="/pugh-sterling-2025/" title="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/pugh-sterling-2025/" display-uri="pugh-sterling-2025" type="local">joint work</fr:link> with <fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link> on the geometry of partial map classifiers, which <fr:link href="/jms-01A6/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W15 › Two papers to appear in LICS ’25 › With Leoni Pugh: When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A6/" display-uri="jms-01A6" type="local">I discussed in my previous weeknote</fr:link>. I’ll be returning to Cambridge on Thursday, in time to have a <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> lunch the following day with <fr:link href="/anilmadhavapeddy/" title="Anil Madhavapeddy" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/anilmadhavapeddy/" display-uri="anilmadhavapeddy" type="local">Anil</fr:link>’s student <fr:link href="/patrickferris/" title="Patrick Ferris" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/patrickferris/" display-uri="patrickferris" type="local">Patrick Ferris</fr:link>, who has been doing <fr:link href="https://patrick.sirref.org/weekly-2025-03-31/" type="external">very interesting things</fr:link> with <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/index/" title="Forester" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/index/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/index/" type="local">Forester</fr:link>.</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors>
          <fr:author>
            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
          </fr:author>
        </fr:authors>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>15</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:date>
          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
          <fr:day>18</fr:day>
        </fr:date>
        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AQ/</fr:uri>
        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AQ</fr:display-uri>
        <fr:route>/jms-01AQ/</fr:route>
        <fr:title text="Reading corner: Children of Time"><fr:link href="/jms-01AY/" title="Reading corner" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AY/" display-uri="jms-01AY" type="local">Reading corner</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2015/" title="Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2015" type="local">Children of Time</fr:link></fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <html:p><fr:link href="/mitchellriley/" title="Mitchell Riley" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/mitchellriley/" display-uri="mitchellriley" type="local">Mitchell Riley</fr:link> suggested I read <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2015/" title="Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2015" type="local">Children of Time</fr:link> by Adrian Tchaikovsky next, a more recent science fiction novel than <fr:link href="/jms-019W/" title="Ventriloquy of the Mid-Century Man" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019W/" display-uri="jms-019W" type="local">what I have been reading lately</fr:link>. I’ve haven’t gotten very deep into it yet, but so far I am enjoying it with a few reservations. The quality of writing, in the literary sense, is somehow still lower than my usual expectations—and the development of human characters is as flimsy and hackneyed as I have come to expect in this genre, but I have to say that the approach to characterising both sentient and non-sentient spiders is actually creative and engaging.</html:p>
        <html:p>Stay tuned for a future review in my <fr:link href="/jms-015X/" title="The Jon Sterling Review of Books" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-015X/" display-uri="jms-015X" type="local">culture blog</fr:link>!</html:p>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>1</fr:month>
              <fr:day>31</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>9</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>5</fr:month>
              <fr:day>6</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/pugh-sterling-2025/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>pugh-sterling-2025</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/pugh-sterling-2025/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?">When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
            <fr:meta name="venue">
              <fr:link href="/lics-2025/" title="LICS ’25: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lics-2025/" display-uri="lics-2025" type="local"><html:em>LICS ’25</html:em>: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science</fr:link>
            </fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2504.06789</fr:meta>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>We study the relationship between partial map classifiers, Sierpiński cones, and axioms for synthetic higher categories and domains within <fr:link href="/hottbook/" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hottbook/" display-uri="hottbook" type="local">univalent foundations</fr:link>. In particular, we show that synthetic ∞-categories are closed under partial map classifiers assuming Phoa's principle, and we isolate a new reflective subuniverse of types within which the Sierpiński cone (a lax colimit) can be computed as a partial map classifier by strengthening the Segal condition.</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>1</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>31</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>6</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:title text="Errata">Errata</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>The paper currently states that the alternative type theoretic computation of the scone uses the flattening lemma, but this is incorrect. In fact, we need only the fact the dependent sum functor preserves colimits (being left adjoint to base change). This will be corrected in the final version of the paper.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/egbertrijke/" title="Egbert Rijke" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/egbertrijke/" display-uri="egbertrijke" type="local">Egbert Rijke</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/mikeshulman/" title="Mike Shulman" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/mikeshulman/" display-uri="mikeshulman" type="local">Mike Shulman</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/basspitters/" title="Bas Spitters" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/basspitters/" display-uri="basspitters" type="local">Bas Spitters</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2020</fr:year>
              <fr:month>1</fr:month>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/rijke-shulman-spitters-2020/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>rijke-shulman-spitters-2020</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/rijke-shulman-spitters-2020/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Modalities in homotopy type theory">Modalities in homotopy type theory</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
            <fr:meta name="venue">
              <fr:link href="/lmcs/" title="Logical Methods in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lmcs/" display-uri="lmcs" type="local">Logical Methods in Computer Science</fr:link>
            </fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="doi">10.23638/LMCS-16(1:2)2020</fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@article{rijke-shulman-spitters-2020,
  author = {Rijke, Egbert and Shulman, Michael and Spitters, Bas},
  year = {2020},
  month = jan,
  doi = {10.23638/LMCS-16(1:2)2020},
  issue = {1},
  journal = {Logical Methods in Computer Science},
  title = {Modalities in homotopy type theory},
  volume = {16},
}]]></fr:meta>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter />
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/taichiuemura/" title="Taichi Uemura" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/taichiuemura/" display-uri="taichiuemura" type="local">Taichi Uemura</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2019</fr:year>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/uemura-2019-types/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>uemura-2019-types</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/uemura-2019-types/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Cubical assemblies, a univalent and impredicative universe and a failure of propositional resizing">Cubical assemblies, a univalent and impredicative universe and a failure of propositional resizing</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
            <fr:meta name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@inproceedings{uemura-2019-types,
  author = {Uemura, Taichi},
  editor = {Dybjer, Peter and Santo, Jos\'{e} Esp\'{i}rito and Pinto, Lu\'{i}s},
  location = {Dagstuhl, Germany},
  publisher = {Schloss Dagstuhl--Leibniz-Zentrum fuer Informatik},
  booktitle = {24th International Conference on Types for Proofs and Programs (TYPES 2018)},
  date = {2019},
  isbn = {978-3-95977-106-1},
  issn = {1868-8969},
  pages = {7:1--7:20},
  series = {Leibniz International Proceedings in Informatics (LIPIcs)},
  title = {{Cubical Assemblies, a Univalent and Impredicative Universe and a Failure of Propositional Resizing}},
  volume = {130},
}]]></fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="doi">10.4230/LIPIcs.TYPES.2018.7</fr:meta>
            <fr:meta name="venue">24th International Conference on Types for Proofs and Programs (TYPES 2018)</fr:meta>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter />
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/adrientchaikovsky/" title="Adrien Tchaikovsky" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/adrientchaikovsky/" display-uri="adrientchaikovsky" type="local">Adrien Tchaikovsky</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2015</fr:year>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>tchaikovsky-2015</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/tchaikovsky-2015/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Children of Time">Children of Time</fr:title>
            <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter />
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>9</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019X/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-019X</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-019X/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Jon Sterling › Weeknotes"><fr:link href="/index/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/index/" display-uri="index" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link> › Weeknotes</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>This page has an <fr:link href="/jms-019X/atom.xml" type="external">atom feed</fr:link>.</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" numbered="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>21</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>23</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W21/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>2025-W21</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/2025-W21/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W21">Weeknotes 2025-W21</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Another long week involving far less science than I would have liked…</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>21</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>23</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01BA/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01BA</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01BA/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Domains and Classifying Topoi">
                      <fr:link href="/sterling-ye-2025/" title="Domains and Classifying Topoi" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-ye-2025/" display-uri="sterling-ye-2025" type="local">Domains and Classifying Topoi</fr:link>
                    </fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p><fr:link href="/lingyuanye/" title="Lingyuan Ye" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lingyuanye/" display-uri="lingyuanye" type="local">Lingyuan</fr:link> and I have now uploaded our new <fr:link href="/sterling-ye-2025/" title="Domains and Classifying Topoi" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-ye-2025/" display-uri="sterling-ye-2025" type="local">manuscript</fr:link> to the arXiv. Do have a look!</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>21</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>23</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01BB/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01BB</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01BB/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Rowing at Clare College">Rowing at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">Clare College</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>After my third outing in the “tub” on Tuesday, <fr:link href="/nigelwoodcock/" title="Nigel Woodcock" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/nigelwoodcock/" display-uri="nigelwoodcock" type="local">Nigel</fr:link> tells me that I’m ready to join the eight. I won’t start until early June because the end of May is so busy for me.</html:p>
                    <html:p>By the way, after my <fr:link href="/jms-01B8/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W20 › Rowing at Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B8/" display-uri="jms-01B8" type="local">harrowing ride last time</fr:link>, I have switched to diverting through Jesus Green—which avoids the Roundabout From Hell, and also exposed me to an interesting beer festival. Thanks very much to <fr:link href="/davidallsopp/" title="David Allsopp" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/davidallsopp/" display-uri="davidallsopp" type="local">David Allsopp</fr:link> and <fr:link href="/ryangibb/" title="Ryan Gibb" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/ryangibb/" display-uri="ryangibb" type="local">Ryan Gibb</fr:link> for their helpful advice!</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>21</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>23</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01BC/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01BC</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01BC/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Do Cambridge students benefit from our assessment bureaucracy?">Do Cambridge students benefit from our assessment bureaucracy?</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Marking season begins… I must mark at a clip of approximately four Part II dissertations per day (including weekend) if I want to have any chance of making our extremely tight deadline. At Cambridge, we have an uncommonly cautious approach to assessment:</html:p>
                    <html:ol><html:li>For examination Papers, questions pass through several redundant layers of checking. Each question has a designated “checker” in addition to the setter. Then after the checker is happy with the question, it goes on to the Examiners, who check each Paper globally and send back suggestions and requests to the setter. After all this, it goes on to an External Examiner (from a different university!), who gives additional feedback.</html:li>
    <html:li>Part II project dissertations are marked not only by the UTO supervisor (who is either the actual supervisor or a “meta-supervisor-at-a-distance” of a non-UTO supervisor who is often a PhD student). They are also marked by a second assessor, who is often one of the Examiners but may also be brought onto the team to contribute to marking. For example, I am a Part IA Examiner but I am marking Part II dissertations in addition to my Examiners’ duties.</html:li></html:ol>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>21</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>23</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01BD/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01BD</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01BD/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Why do we have so much redundancy?">Why do we have so much redundancy?</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>Our fastidious approach to question setting has some definite advantages, but overall it is far too bureaucratic and has too many levels. An immense amount of time is burnt second-guessing question-setters, in the end leading to doubtful benefits. My colleagues at literally every university in the World except for Oxford are always shocked when I explain this process to them—at normal universities, you just set and mark an exam, and nobody else sees it (aside from the TAs you enlist to help you mark it—something else we don’t do here). This actually works fine at literally every university on the planet except for two.</html:p>
                        <html:p>On the other hand, the redundant marking of Part II dissertations is a bit more complex, and there are some stronger reasons for it. One reason is concern over conflicts of interest or supervisors’ natural overenthusiasm for their students’ projects, but I am not convinced by this one. I must comment that this level of redundant project marking is not seen as necessary at almost any other university. On the other hand, a slightly more convincing reason for having a non-supervisor mark the dissertation is that the latter will usually be an outsider to the topic of specialisation; this ensures that dissertations can be read by someone literate in general computer science who is not a specialist, and this legibility is actually one of the goals of the Part II programme. I am more convinced by this, but not entirely—computer science is not really one field anymore, and it is a bit of a shared delusion that it is <html:em>ever</html:em> possible anymore to write up a substantive project in such a way that “the average member of the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Computer Lab</fr:link>” would be able to assess its merits intelligently.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Anyway, I have a feeling that if we cut in half the amount of marking we do, and divided by three the amount of scrutiny we impose on question-setting for examinations, the outcomes for our students would be qualitatively similar to what they are now. It is always possible to raise “important” concerns about the integrity of the process whose “solution” is naturally ever-more layers of redundancy and checking-the-checkers-who-check-the-checkers-of-the-setter-checkers. <html:mark>At moments like this, it is a good idea to pause and reflect on whether it is better for our students that each faculty member spend a cumulative two months doing literally nothing but assessment and higher-order practices related to assessment, vs. other activities that could benefit our students more (<html:strong>including <html:em>actual teaching</html:em></html:strong>, of which we do astonishingly little at Cambridge).</html:mark></html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>21</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>23</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01BE/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01BE</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01BE/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Soliciting feedback on IA Examination processes…">Soliciting feedback on IA Examination processes…</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>Anyway, I believe I shall be Chair of Examiners for Part IA next year. Many of the actual questions of policy are naturally out of my hands in this role, but I hope to direct the examination and assessment process for IA in as anti-bureaucratic a way that can possibly be achieved whilst working within those policies. Any colleagues who have suggestions for practicable improvements to the process are very welcome to have a chat with me about it.</html:p>
                        <html:p>
                          <html:mark>One change I plan to make straightaway is to reform the Examiners’ interaction with setters to be more directly collaborative and less bureaucratic.</html:mark>
                        </html:p>
                        <html:p>Right now, Examiners read all the questions and try their best to come up with criticisms of them (despite our individual uncertain expertise in at least two-thirds of the Paper content). These criticisms are then collated and sent to each setter as a list of requested changes; I believe that a list of changes passed indirectly from the Examiners to the setters is not the most collaborative way to achieve a high quality exam paper. <html:strong><html:em>(I sincerely apologise to anyone who has been on the other end of an interaction like this recently: I have heard you, and I will fix it).</html:em></html:strong></html:p>
                        <html:p>A different approach, which I have heard was actually practised prior to the pandemic, was that Examiners would simply hold court and have walk-in chats with setters and iron things out in person without a bureaucratic back-and-forth. Count me in! We will do something like that next year, making necessary allowances for setters’ availability.</html:p>
                        <html:p>To be honest, every time I hear about how things used to be in the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Lab</fr:link> before the pandemic, I think to myself that we should simply look for every single policy or procedural change that occurred since that era began and simply reverse it and then potentially revisit with the benefit of hindsight. My proposal? <html:code>git checkout -b new-era; git reset --hard HEAD~2000</html:code> and Godspeed.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" numbered="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W20/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>2025-W20</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/2025-W20/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W20">Weeknotes 2025-W20</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>This had been a hectic week without a lot to show for it. Over the weekend, I wrapped up the last of my <fr:link href="/oopsla-2024-25/" title="OOPSLA 2024–25: Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages &amp; Applications" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/oopsla-2024-25/" display-uri="oopsla-2024-25" type="local">OOPSLA 2025–25</fr:link> reviews, just in time to get whacked with a couple dozen Part II dissertations to mark in the coming weeks.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B6/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B6</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B6/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Domains and Classifying Topoi">
                      <fr:link href="/sterling-ye-2025/" title="Domains and Classifying Topoi" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-ye-2025/" display-uri="sterling-ye-2025" type="local">Domains and Classifying Topoi</fr:link>
                    </fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Together with my PhD student <fr:link href="/lingyuanye/" title="Lingyuan Ye" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lingyuanye/" display-uri="lingyuanye" type="local">Lingyuan Ye</fr:link> I have been putting the finishing touches on a very exciting (to me) manuscript on a connection between synthetic domain theory and the theory of classifying toposes. I will say more about this after we have put our manuscript on the arXiv; for now, I will just say that this is the kind of work I had been hoping to do for a few years now and it has been a pleasure to work on it with Lingyuan, who comes to me week after week with deep insights and results.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B7/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B7</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B7/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Preparing for Forester 5.0: June?">Preparing for <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" title="Forester 5.0" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link>: June?</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I would like to get a “beta” release of <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" title="Forester 5.0" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link> out by the end of the month. What this would mean is that <html:em>advanced</html:em> users are invited to try it out and start using it without fear of huge changes wrecking their migration daily (which has been the status quo for several months unfortunately). To that end, <fr:link href="/kentookura/" title="Kento Okura" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/kentookura/" display-uri="kentookura" type="local">Kento</fr:link> and I have been polishing things up and fixing the long tail of issues that would block a release. Of course, I have been dog-fooding 5.0 for many months.</html:p>
                    <html:p>One improvement to the lightweight federation support is that when you federate with a <html:em>published</html:em> forest, you can choose to have links get routed directly to the published version rather than rendering those trees directly in your own forest. There are some trade-offs here, and obviously the current state of federation does not reflect what we will be doing in the future; the current version is meant only to “stem the bleeding” for certain institutional users of Forester while we come up with a better approach.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B8/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B8</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B8/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Rowing at Clare College">Rowing at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">Clare College</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>In the past two weeks I’ve been learning how to row under the patient tutelage of <fr:link href="/nigelwoodcock/" title="Nigel Woodcock" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/nigelwoodcock/" display-uri="nigelwoodcock" type="local">Nigel Woodcock</fr:link>, an Emeritus Fellow at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">Clare College</fr:link> who has been looking after our Boat Club for 25 years now. The motions of rowing are still unnatural for me, but I am improving (albeit slowly); as an arachnophobe, I do not relish the occasional spider in the boat, but otherwise I’m enjoying the experience.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Getting to the boathouse from the other side of the river is really dangerous—there is the round-a-bout from Hell guarding Midsummer Common, and there seems to be no way to cross any of the several connected streets without three different vehicles whipping past you in three different directions simultaneously. Somehow the whole thing works like clockwork—unless you are on foot or on a bicycle and don't have Alexander the Great–level self-confidence. Almost lost my life on Friday… It would be a great idea to have any kind of pedestrian-friendly crosswalk there. In the meanwhile, I think I want to try and find a different route to the Common.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B9/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B9</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B9/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="More on involuntary lighting in the Lab">More on <fr:link href="/jms-01B5/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W19 › Rethinking community in the Computer Lab" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B5/" display-uri="jms-01B5" type="local">involuntary lighting in the Lab</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Last week I commented on the deeply hostile lighting transition being imposed on the denizens of the Computer Lab. Although we appear to have inadvertently triggered this transition in the course of trying to get our lighting replaced in the lecture theatres (which really needed to be done!), it seems this change is coming from Heaven and short of dethroning God, we wouldn’t have been able to prevent it.</html:p>
                    <html:p>With that said, things are looking up. It has been communicated to us that we will be allowed to request light switches to manually control the lights; it remains to be seen whether these switches will fully override the automatic (mis)behaviour, or if it just means that we will have the privilege of getting up to switch the light back on when it goes off at random times, or of getting up to switch it off when it goes on at random times. Anyway, I’m sincerely hoping that the accommodation provided is a <html:em>traditional</html:em> light switch that totally disables the automatic functionality.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Some members of the faculty have complained about the quality of the light itself, pointing out that it induces migraine. I sincerely hope that this is not the case, and I would just say that the current flourescent lights that we have in our offices are so horrible in terms of the light they cast that it is hard to imagine something even worse. So maybe the LED will be better.</html:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:title text="How do we respond to fake “sustainability” drives?">How do we respond to fake “sustainability” drives?</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>Like I said, I hope the new lighting will be satisfactory. If not, I will request the whole thing be ripped out entirely, and I’ll install the most energy-intensive lamp I can find—something as powerful and expensive to run as the Sun itself. I want the whole Computer Lab to feel the dip when I switch on the power…</html:p>
                        <html:p>Someone has to learn that there will always be a way to maliciously comply with hostile “sustainability” updates that negates the supposed benefits entirely; and that this response is <html:em>guaranteed</html:em> when “sustainability” improvements are made without genuine consultation or regard for the required functionality and the basic rights of workers. Fake consultation, where we are given the opportunity to “offer our feedback” but no credible pathway toward this feedback having any impact on a decision that already has been made, is deeply insulting and we should respond appropriately whilst we still can.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" numbered="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>6</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W19/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>2025-W19</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/2025-W19/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W19">Weeknotes 2025-W19</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>6</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B2/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B2</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B2/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Hofmann–Streicher lifting and the biadjoint triangle theorem"><fr:link href="/slattery-sterling-2025/" title="Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/slattery-sterling-2025/" display-uri="slattery-sterling-2025" type="local">Hofmann–Streicher lifting</fr:link> and the biadjoint triangle theorem</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p><fr:link href="/andrewslattery/" title="Andrew Slattery" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/andrewslattery/" display-uri="andrewslattery" type="local">Andrew Slattery</fr:link> and I were preparing the camera-ready version of our accepted <fr:link href="/lics-2025/" title="LICS ’25: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lics-2025/" display-uri="lics-2025" type="local">LICS ’25</fr:link> <fr:link href="/slattery-sterling-2025/" title="Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/slattery-sterling-2025/" display-uri="slattery-sterling-2025" type="local">paper</fr:link> (which I <fr:link href="/jms-01A7/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W15 › Two papers to appear in LICS ’25 › With Andrew Slattery: Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A7/" display-uri="jms-01A7" type="local">summarised a few weeks ago</fr:link>) when we received a very interesting suggestion from <fr:link href="/nathanaelarkor/" title="Nathanael Arkor" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/nathanaelarkor/" display-uri="nathanaelarkor" type="local">Nathanael Arkor</fr:link>: at least the <html:em>existence</html:em> of the right pseudo-adjoint that we construct ought to be guaranteed by the 2-dimensional version of Dubuc’s <fr:link href="https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/adjoint+triangle+theorem" type="external">adjoint triangle lemma</fr:link>, which has been worked out by <fr:link href="/nunes-2016/" title="On biadjoint triangles" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/nunes-2016/" display-uri="nunes-2016" type="local">Nunes</fr:link>.</html:p>
                    <html:p>If we black-box <fr:link href="/nunes-2016/" title="On biadjoint triangles" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/nunes-2016/" display-uri="nunes-2016" type="local">Nunes</fr:link>’s results, it is fairly clear how to reconstruct Nathanael’s argument, which is really cool. To go deeper requires an understanding of 2-dimensional descent objects, about which the literature is unfortunately pretty poorly explained (there are many things that appear to be variants on simplicial shapes, or lax versions thereof, but lacking a number of degeneracies for reasons that nobody seems to explain). This is a forbidding area that seems to be understood by a small community of experts, but which would really benefit from some more systematic exposition. It is something I would really like to understand better.</html:p>
                    <html:p>As for our paper, our completely explicit computation of the pseudoadjoint seems to still be a contribution (as this is what allows us at the moment to conclude a connection to Hofmann–Streicher lifting), but it will be a very good thing indeed to show how the existence of the pseudoadjoint follows from purely formal manipulations. I’m excited to learn more—so thanks, <fr:link href="/nathanaelarkor/" title="Nathanael Arkor" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/nathanaelarkor/" display-uri="nathanaelarkor" type="local">Nathanael</fr:link>!</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>6</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B4/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B4</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B4/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Direction of studies and the community of teachers">Direction of studies and the community of teachers</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>One thing I’ve noticed during my first year as a director of studies is that we do not always provide adequate guidance to new supervisors. There is a mandatory training session run by the University, but course-specific guidance tends to be spotty and limited. In the worst cases (I’ve had more than one of these!), someone agrees to supervise some students and then forgets about it or tells us “Oh yeah, I can’t do that anymore, best of luck!” right as the term starts. Putting aside these extreme cases which happen far more often than I would like, I have started to find that a bit more of a hands-on approach to onboarding supervisors and communicating course expectations and learning objectives for our students is going to be useful.</html:p>
                    <html:p>To that end, I have started inviting new supervisors to have a coffee and a discussion toward the beginning of term. This is a simple practice that doesn’t take up too much time, but I believe it can solve a number of problems that stem from unclear expectations and ambiguous procedures (including providing clarity as to how many supervision-hours the College will actually pay for!). But perhaps more importantly, I am finding that these kinds of interactions may also have some potential for rebuilding community across the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Computer Lab</fr:link>—which I discuss in more detail <fr:link href="/jms-01B4/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W19 › Direction of studies and the community of teachers" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B4/" display-uri="jms-01B4" type="local">below</fr:link>.</html:p>
                    <html:p>We need to invest more in our supervisors; this obviously includes advocating for fair pay increases (which I sadly have no control over), but it also includes connecting and conspiring with supervisors as equals with a common goal—the integrated intellectual development of our undergraduates through high quality and inspiring teaching interactions. One thing my PhD advisor <fr:link href="/robertharper/" title="Robert Harper" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/robertharper/" display-uri="robertharper" type="local">Bob Harper</fr:link> always instilled in me is that some of the best research comes from figuring out how to teach something; in the context of strengthening the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Computer Lab</fr:link> as an intellectual community, it seems to me that breaking down the topical silos and having an earnest cross-field conversation about teaching <html:em>from the bottom up</html:em> is a good place to start.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>6</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B5/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B5</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B5/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Rethinking community in the Computer Lab">Rethinking community in the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Computer Lab</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I am told that our sense of community in the Lab historically relied on in-person faculty meetings and group seminars and impromptu hallway chats, but the reality today is (1) in the aftermath of the pandemic, not many of us are regularly in the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Lab</fr:link> anyway, and (2) seminars tend to be a waste of everyone’s time and do not facilitate connections outside narrow research specialisations.</html:p>
                    <html:p>The Faculty’s abandonment of the Lab will definitely get worse rather than better: the Lab is (illegally?) imposing automatic lighting on all offices, to be rolled out over the next year or two; <html:mark><html:em>this means that we will no longer be allowed to control whether our lights are turned on except by <html:strong>jumping up and down</html:strong> (when we wish them to be on) or <html:strong>keeping extremely still</html:strong> (when we wish them to be off)</html:em></html:mark>. As soon as this vicious “environmental update” ripples up to the First Floor, I will no longer come to the Lab at all except for once a week or so—if that.</html:p>
                    <html:p>In ‘light’ of all this (pun intended), I think that we need to be thinking about sustainable practices to make more direct and intentional connections with our colleagues, including both faculty and students. Adopting the <fr:link href="https://www.cst.cam.ac.uk/research/eeg" type="external">Energy and Environment Group</fr:link>’s culture of internal blogging and weeknotes has gone off like a bomb in my intellectual life, for example; this asynchronous practice has informed me far more about my colleagues’ work and goals than a dozen hours spent in seminars ever could. <html:mark>Blogging is not an alternative to meeting and talking in person; but I am starting to think that it is a <html:em>prerequisite</html:em> for the moments of serendipity that the latter can engender, because the ongoing dialogue of blogs and weeknotes makes me sufficiently <html:em>informed</html:em> to have a conversation that goes beyond the superficial.</html:mark></html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>6</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>8</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B3/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B3</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B3/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Reading corner: Children of Ruin and the OE Exodus"><fr:link href="/jms-01AY/" title="Reading corner" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AY/" display-uri="jms-01AY" type="local">Reading corner</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2019/" title="Children of Ruin" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2019/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2019" type="local">Children of Ruin</fr:link> and the OE <html:em>Exodus</html:em></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>As I mentioned <fr:link href="/jms-01AZ/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W18 › Reading corner: Children of Time, Children of Ruin" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AZ/" display-uri="jms-01AZ" type="local">last week</fr:link>, I’ve been making my way through <fr:link href="/adrientchaikovsky/" title="Adrien Tchaikovsky" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/adrientchaikovsky/" display-uri="adrientchaikovsky" type="local">Tchaikovsky</fr:link>’s <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2019/" title="Children of Ruin" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2019/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2019" type="local">Children of Ruin</fr:link>, the sequel to <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2015/" title="Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2015" type="local">Children of Time</fr:link>. It is getting better and better, and moving in directions that I had not anticipated. I will not say much today, but months ago when I <fr:link href="/jms-015W/" title="West of Eden: you can judge a book by its cover" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-015W/" display-uri="jms-015W" type="local">alluded to our ruinous and outrageous behaviour toward the octopus</fr:link>, I did not anticipate that I would be reading a novel featuring (even more) sentient octopodes.</html:p>
                    <html:p>I have also started dipping my toes back into the pool of my old love affair with dead languages. Last week on a whim, I picked up a copy of the <fr:link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_English" type="external">Old English</fr:link> <fr:link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exodus_(poem)" type="external"><html:em>Exodus</html:em></fr:link> at my <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> library and I finally started reading it this week. For those of you who don’t know, Old English is the ancestor of our current tongue but is as different from Modern English as the latter is from Swedish or Norwegian. At one time I was very good at Old English, and I hope to become so again.</html:p>
                    <html:figure><html:table style="text-align: left">
      <html:tr><html:td>Hwæt! We feor and neah   gefrigen hab[b]að</html:td></html:tr>
      <html:tr><html:td>ofer middangeard   Moyses domas,</html:td></html:tr>
      <html:tr><html:td>wræclico wordriht,   wera cneorissum,—</html:td></html:tr>
      <html:tr><html:td>in uprodor   eadigra gehwam</html:td></html:tr>
      <html:tr><html:td>æfter bealusiðe   bote lifes,</html:td></html:tr>
      <html:tr><html:td>lifigendra gehwam   langsumne ræd,—</html:td></html:tr>
      <html:tr><html:td>hæleðum secgan.   Gehyre se ðe wille!</html:td></html:tr>
    </html:table>

    <html:figcaption>The first seven lines of the OE <html:em>Exodus</html:em>.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
                    <html:p>There is a particular genre of Christian “cultural translation” literature to be found among the converted Germanic peoples that is extremely appealing. The idea is that the scripture of Christianity is rewrought into the artistic forms that are culturally familiar among the people, with a number of liberties taken—think about how some Churches today try to pick up engagement among the youth by portraying the acts of Christ in a more, shall we say, …“urban”… light.</html:p>
                    <html:p>In this case, however, the stories of the Bible are told in the form of epic verse (alliterative half-lines in the oldest Germanic tradition). The first examplar of this genre that I came into contact with many years ago was the <fr:link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heliand" type="external"><html:em>Heliand</html:em></fr:link>, an epic <fr:link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Saxon" type="external">Old Saxon</fr:link> re-telling of the New Testament in which Christ and his apostles take on the characteristics of a Germanic warlord and his retainers. The <html:em>Exodus</html:em> similarly casts Moses into a culturally appropriate role and retells the story of the Israelites’ liberation from bondage and acquisition of the Law in epic verse.</html:p>
                    <html:p>I have not got more than twenty lines in, because my Old English is so much slower than it was in the old days. But it has been very enjoyable to revisit this language and culture that I once knew so well.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" numbered="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>2</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W18/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>2025-W18</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/2025-W18/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W18">Weeknotes 2025-W18</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>I was a bit unwell over the weekend and hence much of my week was spent recuperating. I am feeling much better now, but becoming healthily aware of my limitations and need for rest.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>2</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B1/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B1</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B1/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="A jaunt through descriptive complexity theory!">A jaunt through descriptive complexity theory!</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I had the pleasure of reading a draft of a fascinating Part II project dissertation on computational aspects of descriptive complexity theory this week, written by a very talented student at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">my college</fr:link>. I won’t say much about it, of course, but it was one of those projects that goes far beyond the material we teach in the course—although I have opinions about the limitations of the Computer Science Tripos as a tool for actually teaching people computer science, I must say that it does a very good job getting <html:em>out of the way</html:em> from students who need space to run and learn.</html:p>
                    <html:p>By the way, I read the thesis on my <fr:link href="/jms-01AH/" title="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/" display-uri="jms-01AH" type="local">white plastic iMac</fr:link> and compiled my feedback using an ancient version of <fr:link href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnioutliner" type="external">OmniOutliner</fr:link>. Converting the outline to a PDF, moving it to my modern laptop by creating a local network, and sending it by email is a simple enough workflow. OmniOutliner can even read and write OMPL, which I can then feed into <fr:link href="/jms-0085/" title="Bike Outliner: Structured focused writing" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-0085/" display-uri="jms-0085" type="local">Bike</fr:link> if I like—or convert to any format I want using XSLT. That is the beauty of a standard: interop spanning decades.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>2</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01B0/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01B0</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01B0/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Difficult coherences for the Sierpiński cone">Difficult coherences for the Sierpiński cone</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Last week, I <fr:link href="/jms-01AT/" title="We have AI at home… › A pleasant surprise" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AT/" display-uri="jms-01AT" type="local">wrote about a pleasant surprise</fr:link> concerning the results of my <fr:link href="/pugh-sterling-2025/" title="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/pugh-sterling-2025/" display-uri="pugh-sterling-2025" type="local">LICS 2025 paper</fr:link>: one of two annoying side conditions from the main theorem can be dropped, and I conjectured that I could find a way to remove the other side condition. I spent much of the work working on the latter, and unfortunately I have come up a bit empty. There is some real difficulty with the higher coherences here, and although I have tried to attack them from several directions, they are not budging.</html:p>
                    <html:p>I am thinking that I will just make the one improvement prior to the camera-ready submission, and leave the other one for a future paper should I ever solve it.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>5</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>2</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AZ/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AZ</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AZ/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Reading corner: Children of Time, Children of Ruin"><fr:link href="/jms-01AY/" title="Reading corner" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AY/" display-uri="jms-01AY" type="local">Reading corner</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2015/" title="Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2015" type="local">Children of Time</fr:link>, <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2019/" title="Children of Ruin" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2019/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2019" type="local">Children of Ruin</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I finished <fr:link href="/adrientchaikovsky/" title="Adrien Tchaikovsky" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/adrientchaikovsky/" display-uri="adrientchaikovsky" type="local">Adrien Tchaikovsky</fr:link>’s science fiction debut <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2015/" title="Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2015" type="local">Children of Time</fr:link> last week—my <fr:link href="/jms-01AQ/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W16 › Reading corner: Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AQ/" display-uri="jms-01AQ" type="local">initial impressions</fr:link> were a little hesitant, but I have to say that the quality of the writing improved rapidly as I went onward. There is something a little strange about Tchaikovsky’s style that <html:em>takes you out</html:em> of the fictional world and makes you overly aware of reality: he is constantly make analogies that are sensible to you and me but would not make sense to the characters in the book. I don’t think this is necessary <html:em>even</html:em> when you are writing about spiders, but I suppose I am learning a bit about my own taste. In any case, I loved the book. I am completely terrified of spiders, but I can recommend this to any arachnophobe—I will write more in my actual review later.</html:p>
                    <html:p>I started reading the sequel, <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2019/" title="Children of Ruin" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2019/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2019" type="local">Children of Ruin</fr:link>, and straightaway I can say that the writing quality has improved at least by a factor of two. With <html:em>Ruin</html:em>, I find Tchaikovsky hitting a strong rhythm, and his depiction of the alien world <html:em>Nod</html:em> is as enchanting as his characterisation of humans (and their arachnid comrades) is compelling.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" numbered="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>24</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>25</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W17/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>2025-W17</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/2025-W17/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W17">Weeknotes 2025-W17</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>It has been a good but busy week. I have been moving more slowly than recently, as I did a tremendous number on my muscles and joints while working in my garden on the weekend. Hope to feel better soon.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>25</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AS/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AS</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AS/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="We have AI at home…">We have AI at home…</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>On Tuesday, I travelled by train to Sheffield to take part in the <fr:link href="/yamcats-37/" title="Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar 37" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/yamcats-37/" display-uri="yamcats-37" type="local">Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar 37</fr:link> meeting, where I would be <fr:link href="/sterling-2025-yamcats-37/" title="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-2025-yamcats-37/" display-uri="sterling-2025-yamcats-37" type="local">speaking</fr:link> about my <fr:link href="/pugh-sterling-2025/" title="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/pugh-sterling-2025/" display-uri="pugh-sterling-2025" type="local">paper</fr:link> that compares partial map classifiers with Sierpiński cones in synthetic (domain/category) theory, which I <fr:link href="/jms-01A6/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W15 › Two papers to appear in LICS ’25 › With Leoni Pugh: When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A6/" display-uri="jms-01A6" type="local">summarised previously</fr:link>.</html:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>25</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AT/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AT</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AT/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="A pleasant surprise">A pleasant surprise</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>I was preparing for my chalk talk when I realised that I could not remember the details of the proof of the main result and they couldn’t really be reconstructed from the abbreviated proof in the paper.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Luckily, I had actually formalised this result in Agda! I did not mention my formalisation in the paper because I do not think of formalisations as scientific contributions except in certain cases (that is a conversation for another day). But I did indeed formalise it because the proof was subtle enough that I needed computerised assistance back when I proved it the first time. The result I obtained was frustratingly weak, and seemed to require some annoying side conditions in order to go through; the formalisation helped me be certain that these side conditions were in fact sufficient.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Anyway, I was messing around with the code and what I realised was that I had missed a trick back then: <html:strong>one of the side conditions was actually unnecessary</html:strong>, and it seems kind of likely that the other one is unnecessary too. I am certain I would not have noticed this if I hadn't had the proof assistant, which made it easy for me to try something out and see if it worked. I should have time to update the paper to claim the strong result prior to the <fr:link href="/lics-2025/" title="LICS ’25: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lics-2025/" display-uri="lics-2025" type="local">LICS</fr:link> camera-ready deadline next month.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>25</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AU/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AU</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AU/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Arise, symbolic AI!">Arise, symbolic AI!</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>There is a lot of discussion lately of the impact that some current machine learning techniques, marketed as “Artificial Intelligence”, can have on formalisation of mathematics in proof assistants. Some of the <fr:link href="https://www.math.ucla.edu/~tao/" type="external">most esteemed</fr:link> members of the mathematical community have gone <html:em>all in</html:em> on this trend <html:span style="font-size: smaller">(is it a requirement of scientific fame and esteem that you begin to cause trouble in areas of research that you know nothing about?)</html:span>, but I think that evaluating LLMs on Olympiad questions is really missing the point of what computers can do to assist mathematicians. Olympiads are a good fit for LLMs, because kids who participate in Olympiads are behaving much more like LLMs than human mathematicians—the mathematics Olympiad is the ultimate feat of pattern-recognition without understanding, and they are certainly a good fit for the <html:em>Might Makes Right</html:em> approach being taken within AI today.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Agda (and Lean and Rocq and Isabelle) are “Artificial Intelligences” in the most progressive sense—they augment the limited context that a human can store in their mind at once, and are nimble tools for working mathematicians to check and verify their ideas, and (most importantly) they do not proceed by creating a fetish of illusion and misdirection that deceives the public. Their capabilities are limited, but well-circumscribed. I think often about how important it is to know in a definite sense what a tool can and cannot do, and I increasingly think that this is actually part of what makes something a <html:em>tool</html:em>. Some of my colleagues have compared LLMs to calculators, in order to make the case that we should get ready for them to be used as everyday tools; but LLMs are not simply tools in the sense that a calculator is a tool.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>24</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>25</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AV/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AV</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AV/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Progress on the Forester 5.0 Language Server">Progress on the <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" title="Forester 5.0" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link> Language Server</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p><fr:link href="/kentookura/" title="Kento Okura" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/kentookura/" display-uri="kentookura" type="local">Kento Okura</fr:link> has made a lot of progress over the past week in getting Forester’s language server to the point where it can be used. The first editor that we will support is Neovim, which has good LSP support built-in. I think, however, that Kento had not realised quite what a huge amount of work it is to get a working Neovim configuration from scratch that exercises the features of the language server and actually works out-of-the box on other people’s machines. To address this problem, we will be providing a complete working configuration for anyone who wants to use it; experienced users of Neovim will of course prefer to set things up in their own way. Some <fr:link href="https://github.com/kentookura/forester-nvim-config" type="external">preliminary code</fr:link> is available, but please stay tuned for further updates that take more advantage of the capabilities of Kento’s language server.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>24</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>25</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AW/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AW</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AW/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Lunch with Patrick Ferris">Lunch with <fr:link href="/patrickferris/" title="Patrick Ferris" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/patrickferris/" display-uri="patrickferris" type="local">Patrick Ferris</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I had a very pleasant lunch in <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> with <fr:link href="/patrickferris/" title="Patrick Ferris" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/patrickferris/" display-uri="patrickferris" type="local">Patrick Ferris</fr:link> as my guest; we discussed many things, including the future of Forester and the importance of <html:strong>interop</html:strong> between different authoring tools on the World Wide Web. After lunch, Patrick and I wandered over to Espresso Lane where we had a coffee and a chat with <fr:link href="/anilmadhavapeddy/" title="Anil Madhavapeddy" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/anilmadhavapeddy/" display-uri="anilmadhavapeddy" type="local">Anil Madhavapeddy</fr:link> and David Allsopp.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Conspiring about the Open Web with my colleagues in the <fr:link href="https://www.cst.cam.ac.uk/research/eeg" type="external">Energy and Environment Group</fr:link> here is making me feel scientifically alive again—there is much to do, and we intend to have fun doing it.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>24</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>25</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AX/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AX</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AX/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="De-enshittifying Computer Lab infrastructure">De-enshittifying <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Computer Lab</fr:link> infrastructure</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Not many people are aware that the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Computer Lab</fr:link> has an old supplier agreement with Fastmail, which has persisted even after the (ill-advised!) transition to Microsoft Office 365 a few years ago. <html:span style="font-size: smaller">(There is a certain kind of person whom you can always trust to make poor and irreversible technical decisions, and argue for them on the basis of maintainability or security or liability or all of the above! Whenever you refute their technical arguments, there is always an unbounded source of further reasons why it is <html:em>mandatory</html:em> and <html:em>inevitable</html:em> that we enshittify our own infrastructure, at great cost of course!)</html:span> Anyway, the savvier members of the <fr:link href="/camcl/" title="Cambridge Computer Laboratory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/camcl/" display-uri="camcl" type="local">Lab</fr:link> have been rocking Fastmail all this time while I have been suffering the constant outages and inconsistencies of Office 365, which is not only a horrible and unreliable product, but also interacts very poorly with standards-based clients other than Microsoft’s own unusable and bloated clients.</html:p>
                    <html:p>A month or two ago, <fr:link href="/anilmadhavapeddy/" title="Anil Madhavapeddy" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/anilmadhavapeddy/" display-uri="anilmadhavapeddy" type="local">Anil</fr:link> let me on the secret, and I quickly asked the Lab sysadmins to hook me up with a Fastmail account. The process was not completely trivial, as apparently nobody had asked to use this facility for a very long time. But in the end, Piete and Malcom were extremely helpful and I am now up and running with a Lab Fastmail account! <html:mark><html:strong>PhD students, postdocs, and faculty are <html:em>all</html:em> entitled to use Fastmail if they choose, and I strongly recommend it.</html:strong> If you are one of those people, then you have access to <fr:link href="https://www.cst.cam.ac.uk/local/sys/mail/fastmail" type="external">this internal page</fr:link>, which contains the instructions for getting an account.</html:mark></html:p>
                    <html:p>Although we will never be able to get professional services staff off of Office 365 and Teams (this is the sense in which such moves are irreversible), there is absolutely no reason why we have to use it too. I encourage everyone within the Lab to join me on Fastmail, which is extremely reliable and usable. And the more of us who depend on it, the stronger the insurance against forced enshittification in the future.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Fastmail is just the beginning. With <fr:link href="/anilmadhavapeddy/" title="Anil Madhavapeddy" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/anilmadhavapeddy/" display-uri="anilmadhavapeddy" type="local">Anil</fr:link> and other members of EEG, I am hoping that we can begin the process of taking back control of our internal infrastructure and making it work for us in the way it used to years before I arrived. I am spooked by recent proposals from University IT to drop <fr:link href="https://talks.cam.ac.uk/dates" type="external">talks.cam</fr:link>; it seems to me that taking over the administration and maintanance of such critical infrastructure would be a good fit for our capabilities, and I promise that we can do it for less than the millions that the University would pay a vendor to irrevocably enshittify this infrastructure.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" numbered="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>15</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W16/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>2025-W16</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/2025-W16/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W16">Weeknotes 2025-W16</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>I thought I had less to say than <fr:link href="/2025-W15/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W15" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W15/" display-uri="2025-W15" type="local">last week</fr:link>, but then I started reflecting on my current experiments with retrocomputing and before I knew it, I had written an <fr:link href="/jms-01AH/" title="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/" display-uri="jms-01AH" type="local">entire blog post</fr:link> about it which I have transcluded below.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AH</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AH/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work">Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Over the Christmas holiday, I bought an iMac off eBay for £50. Why was it so cheap? Because it is a 2006 model firing on a single gigabyte of RAM with an Intel Core 2 Duo processor, running Mac OS X Tiger. When I was a kid, I dreamed of having a computer like this—for me, the white plastic era will always be peak Apple design, and Tiger’s version of Aqua was the most polished and refined form of the design language that they ever managed to produce. My first Macintosh was a white polycarbonate unibody MacBook running Leopard—and at the time I greatly regretted having just missed the Tiger era for the gaudy and overly darkened feel of Leopard with its sinister-coloured window controls. I did not know at the time how much worse things would get…</html:p>
                    <html:p>My excuse for purchasing this machine was that I “needed” to run Mac OS X Tiger as “research” for my experimental project <fr:link href="https://github.com/jonsterling/aquaui" type="external">AquaUI</fr:link>, which imagines how the Aqua design language could have evolved if it had been allowed to. But really, I wanted to relive my rare trips to Apple retailers as a kid, where I would spend minutes doing nothing but just moving the scrollbar while watching its stationary “wave” texture, or highlighting buttons to see them burst with blue radiance.</html:p>
                    <html:p>(I spoke about many of the topics covered in this post in my appearance on the <fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/" type="external">Kodsnack podcast</fr:link> hosted by Fredrik Björeman: <html:em><fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/international/626/" type="external">Episode 626, “The great flattening of everything”</fr:link></html:em>.)</html:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AI/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AI</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AI/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?">Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>When the delivery came, I took the machine gingerly out of its battered and taped over original packaging and turned it on to a feeling of great excitement, which quickly gave way to loss and melancholy: so much of what computers are “for” involves the World Wide Web, and the forced transition to HTTPS/TLS has stolen access to the Web from users of many working computers of access to the Web (unless they gut the machine by downgrading to a modern but severely less polished operating system, like Linux). The old Intel Macs are a prime example of this loss—although some <fr:link href="https://tenfourfox.blogspot.com/" type="external">volunteer projects exist</fr:link> to enable safe access to the Web for PowerPC machines, older Intel Macintoshes have received comparatively less attention. Capitalist forced obsolescence comes to all, however, and there will no doubt come a time when the “necessary” “security” routines will simply not be executable with the kinds of hardware resources that could be mustered in 2006, no matter the system architecture. After playing around and finding much of the functionality crippled due to being barred from the Internet, I had to ask myself, <html:strong>What should I even do with this thing?</html:strong></html:p>
                        <html:p>The iMac lay dormant in my <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> room for the next few months while I figured out an answer to that question.</html:p>
                        <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiejjxl32uo7vfhgpkbkxuiww4vabuu745bhajcrleqi7uz4blqjay.gif" />

    <html:figcaption>My iMac sleeping peacefully in my office at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">Clare College</fr:link> Memorial Court, connected to a vintage A1048 keyboard and Apple Pro Mouse (as it should be!). Nearby is my iPod Classic, which I use for about an hour each day and charge once every 6-8 weeks.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AJ/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AJ</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AJ/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="With a little love, everything has a use">With a little love, <html:em>everything</html:em> has a use</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>Last week I finally realised that there is a lot I can still do with this machine. I turned it on when I had a bit of free time, and found that it remains very snappy—software opens instantly without hanging, and in fact the built-in programs are significantly less bug-ridden than they were in subsequent versions of Mac OS X and its (unworthy) successor macOS. To put this into perspective, the “outdated” iMac’s performance was far better than that of my last Intel iMac from 2020 with sixteen times the RAM and several times the processor cores.</html:p>
                        <html:p>It is well-known that hardware capabilities get better and better each year, but this did not translate into improved performance for users until after the Apple Silicon transition—when the hardware improvement was so great that it was able to outpace the deathmarch of inefficient software, for a time. Don’t worry, the “transition to AI” is going to destroy all those gains soon and we’ll be back where we started.</html:p>
                        <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiaaxhqvbslbd3sb6mafhlrxswbdbwipj4bzhuewlg7il73mhq7l7y.jpeg" />

    <html:figcaption>Mac OS X Tiger is still King—with the peak versions of Finder, Preview, and iTunes.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
                        <html:p>But I digress. Even if you can’t use the Web, there are many things that a 19 year old iMac running Mac OS X Tiger is better at than a more recently manufactured machine. For example, Tiger was the last version of Mac OS X in which Preview.app (the PDF and image viewer) had a working search interface; from the subsequent version (Leopard) all the way until the present day, searching is somehow both too fuzzy and not fuzzy enough, and there seems to be no combination of quotation marks that will lead to reasonable results appearing in the search pane. (Same with Mail.app, which has somehow got <html:em>even worse</html:em> in the past year; you can’t connect to email on such an old machine anyway, so the point is moot.)</html:p>
                        <html:p>Similarly, iTunes 7 was the functional peak for Apple’s music management and playback software (although iTunes 6 was visually superior), and people who have only used Apple’s current “Music” app will not be able to understand what they are missing. Likewise, the version of Finder shipped with Tiger was the most polished and least buggy version they ever produced; it is really amazing to switch back and forth between macOS 15.3 and Mac OS X 10.4, and find that most of the bugs or usability problems I have encountered on a daily basis for the past decade or so are actually <html:em>regressions</html:em>.</html:p>
                        <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                          <fr:frontmatter>
                            <fr:authors>
                              <fr:author>
                                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                              </fr:author>
                            </fr:authors>
                            <fr:date>
                              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                            </fr:date>
                            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AK/</fr:uri>
                            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AK</fr:display-uri>
                            <fr:route>/jms-01AK/</fr:route>
                            <fr:title text="The perfect music and PDF reading workstation">The perfect music and PDF reading workstation</fr:title>
                          </fr:frontmatter>
                          <fr:mainmatter>
                            <html:p>So I transferred my music and PDF libraries to the iMac—this was easy to do by creating a local WiFi network from the iMac, a functionality that has been removed in macOS(!). Indeed, modern macOS has replaced some (but not all) aspects of this functionality with what is called “Internet Sharing”, but this feature does not work reliably and in many cases the needful functionalities are unpredictably grayed out and disabled without any message explaining why. Death by a thousand papercuts... But I digress: I set up a local WiFi network with a file server easily using the old <html:em>System Preferences</html:em> application (don’t get me started on the bizarre redesign of System Settings introduced in macOS Ventura), and easily transferred everything I wanted to the iMac and then I was off to the races.</html:p>
                            <html:p>I listen to music and study papers on this machine, and it gives me so much joy to <html:em>use</html:em> this masterpiece of practical industrial design every day—I even write referee reports on it using an ancient version of <fr:link href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnioutliner/" type="external">OmniOutliner</fr:link>, a venerable piece of software that I have to say has not improved much in the past two decades. After installing a copy of <fr:link href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/scrivener" type="external">Scrivener 2.5</fr:link> (don’t worry, I own a license for <fr:link href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/" type="external">Scrivener 3.0</fr:link> and you should too!), I find myself creative writing in my free time like it’s 2006.</html:p>
                          </fr:mainmatter>
                        </fr:tree>
                        <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                          <fr:frontmatter>
                            <fr:authors>
                              <fr:author>
                                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                              </fr:author>
                            </fr:authors>
                            <fr:date>
                              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                            </fr:date>
                            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AL/</fr:uri>
                            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AL</fr:display-uri>
                            <fr:route>/jms-01AL/</fr:route>
                            <fr:title text="What about my iPod Classic?">What about my iPod Classic?</fr:title>
                          </fr:frontmatter>
                          <fr:mainmatter>
                            <html:p>Some of you may be aware that I use an iPod Classic every day. The thing is a godsend—the best mobile device I own. I bought it with a fresh battery and SSD, and the damn battery lasts for months before I have to recharge it. That is the kind of technology that was taken from us and replaced by resource-intensive devices governed by the logic of planned obsolescence. But I have it back—my world is not the same as your world, but it is a world I am glad to have returned to.</html:p>
                            <html:p>Naturally, the first thing I wanted to do was use the iMac as a hub for synchronising the iPod with iTunes. This will work, but what I did not anticipate is that one of my main uses of the iPod is to listen to podcasts, and podcasts cannot be downloaded on the iMac because of the vicious imposition of TLS on all parts of the web that didn’t need it (<fr:link href="https://letsencrypt.org/" type="external">Let’s Encrypt</fr:link> really ought to have been called <html:em>Let’s Kill The Open Web</html:em>). So I continue synchronising my iPod with my modern day MacBook Air—and it is a testament to Apple’s historical approach to backward compatibility that this is still possible (and even integrated with the otherwise terrible Podcasts app!).</html:p>
                          </fr:mainmatter>
                        </fr:tree>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AM/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AM</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AM/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Is retrocomputing sustainable?">Is retrocomputing sustainable?</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>I constantly feel a pang in the back of my throat when I think about retrocomputing over the long term. We are scrounging around for intact pieces of old technology, but there will come a time when these are too scarce, or when we have really lost the ability to repair them. It is like living in a post-apocalyptic film where a cataclysm has made all manufacturing impossible—but today the cataclysm is not a war or even a virus, but just the simple vicious logic of Capital and a technology industry that has hitched itself to the most ignorant and anti-human trends emanating from the most technologically ignorant people on Wall Street.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Retrocomputing is decidedly <html:em>not</html:em> sustainable, in the same sense that living on a stash of canned foods that can no longer be manufactured cannot be sustainable. But also unsustainable is the present day technological treadmill of consumer goods containing precious metals and dangerous chemicals being produced in the billions and sent directly almost directly to the landfill.</html:p>
                        <html:p>I think a better question to ask is whether retrocomputing is <html:em>progressive</html:em>. I think that retrocomputing can be progressive insofar as it is part of a practice of looking <html:em>forward</html:em>—how can we build sovereign technology that respects constrained resources as well as users of different abilities, and cannot be taken away or made useless by Capital and the irrational whims of the stock market. Such a project <html:em>must</html:em> have a significant design component, and this cannot be done amateurishly; looking to the iconic design languages of the past for inspiration and education is, then, deeply progressive in this environment.</html:p>
                        <html:p>The tragedy of Mac OS X is not that Apple took it away and replaced it with something inferior: the tragedy is that free software communities have never managed to produce something even remotely approaching its level of fit and finish. Volunteer projects do not deserve my ire, which I reserve for our economic system in which nearly <html:em>all</html:em> competent design work is confined to corporate environments, and then wiped away when the wind shifts.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AN/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AN</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AN/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Bring back the joy in computing!">Bring back the joy in computing!</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>Forget your troubles and find something that makes you smile, and reminds you of what is possible when a team brimming with talent comes together to build something beautiful.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Write to me with any joyful and quirky projects, hardware or software, that you would like to share.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>15</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AO/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AO</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AO/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Jem Lord at HoTT/UF in Genoa"><fr:link href="/jemlord/" title="Jem Lord" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jemlord/" display-uri="jemlord" type="local">Jem Lord</fr:link> at <fr:link href="/hott-uf-2025/" title="HoTT-UF ’25: Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory/ Univalent Foundations" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hott-uf-2025/" display-uri="hott-uf-2025" type="local">HoTT/UF</fr:link> in Genoa</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>My first-year PhD student <fr:link href="/jemlord/" title="Jem Lord" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jemlord/" display-uri="jemlord" type="local">Jem Lord</fr:link> presented <fr:link href="https://hott-uf.github.io/2025/abstracts/HoTTUF_2025_paper_21.pdf" type="external">their work on <html:em>Easy Parametricity</html:em></fr:link> at the <fr:link href="/hott-uf-2025/" title="HoTT-UF ’25: Workshop on Homotopy Type Theory/ Univalent Foundations" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hott-uf-2025/" display-uri="hott-uf-2025" type="local">HoTT/UF</fr:link> workshop in Genoa this week. Although I was not able to come in person, a little birdy told me that Jem gave a very good talk, so I’m proud of them for that. Congratulations, Jem!</html:p>
                    <html:p>Jem’s work concerns a very simple parametricity axiom for a universe <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math> in type theory: namely, that every <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-small type <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> be <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-null in the sense of <fr:link href="/rijke-shulman-spitters-2020/" title="Modalities in homotopy type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/rijke-shulman-spitters-2020/" display-uri="rijke-shulman-spitters-2020" type="local">Rijke, Shulman and Spitters</fr:link>. This is a mathematical way to say that small types “cannot see” their universe; another way to phrase it is that every function <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">→</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> for <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> is constant. One of Jem’s results, which has a startling proof(!), is that when <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">C</mml:mi></mml:math> is a category that is complete with respect to certain <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-small diagrams and <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mml:mi></mml:math> is locally <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">U</mml:mi></mml:math>-small category, any “unnatural” transformation between functors <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">F</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">,</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">G</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">:</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">C</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">→</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math> is automatically natural. Many similar results can be obtained in the same way.</html:p>
                    <html:p>There are a variety of models of these axioms. One example is the impredicative universe of modest types within a category of assemblies, which is the “standard” categorical model of both System F and the original calculus of constructions. The same principle will work within <fr:link href="/uemura-2019-types/" title="Cubical assemblies, a univalent and impredicative universe and a failure of propositional resizing" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/uemura-2019-types/" display-uri="uemura-2019-types" type="local">cubical assemblies</fr:link>.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>15</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AP/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AP</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AP/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Speaking at YaMCaTS 37 next week">Speaking at <fr:link href="/yamcats-37/" title="Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar 37" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/yamcats-37/" display-uri="yamcats-37" type="local">YaMCaTS 37</fr:link> next week</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I am traveling to Sheffield on Tuesday, to speak at the <fr:link href="/yamcats-37/" title="Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar 37" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/yamcats-37/" display-uri="yamcats-37" type="local">Yorkshire and Midlands Category Theory Seminar</fr:link> the following day. I haven’t prepared my talk yet, but I will be speaking about my <fr:link href="/pugh-sterling-2025/" title="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/pugh-sterling-2025/" display-uri="pugh-sterling-2025" type="local">joint work</fr:link> with <fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link> on the geometry of partial map classifiers, which <fr:link href="/jms-01A6/" title="Weeknotes 2025-W15 › Two papers to appear in LICS ’25 › With Leoni Pugh: When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A6/" display-uri="jms-01A6" type="local">I discussed in my previous weeknote</fr:link>. I’ll be returning to Cambridge on Thursday, in time to have a <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> lunch the following day with <fr:link href="/anilmadhavapeddy/" title="Anil Madhavapeddy" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/anilmadhavapeddy/" display-uri="anilmadhavapeddy" type="local">Anil</fr:link>’s student <fr:link href="/patrickferris/" title="Patrick Ferris" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/patrickferris/" display-uri="patrickferris" type="local">Patrick Ferris</fr:link>, who has been doing <fr:link href="https://patrick.sirref.org/weekly-2025-03-31/" type="external">very interesting things</fr:link> with <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/index/" title="Forester" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/index/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/index/" type="local">Forester</fr:link>.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>15</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>18</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AQ/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AQ</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AQ/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Reading corner: Children of Time"><fr:link href="/jms-01AY/" title="Reading corner" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AY/" display-uri="jms-01AY" type="local">Reading corner</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2015/" title="Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2015" type="local">Children of Time</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p><fr:link href="/mitchellriley/" title="Mitchell Riley" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/mitchellriley/" display-uri="mitchellriley" type="local">Mitchell Riley</fr:link> suggested I read <fr:link href="/tchaikovsky-2015/" title="Children of Time" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/tchaikovsky-2015/" display-uri="tchaikovsky-2015" type="local">Children of Time</fr:link> by Adrian Tchaikovsky next, a more recent science fiction novel than <fr:link href="/jms-019W/" title="Ventriloquy of the Mid-Century Man" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019W/" display-uri="jms-019W" type="local">what I have been reading lately</fr:link>. I’ve haven’t gotten very deep into it yet, but so far I am enjoying it with a few reservations. The quality of writing, in the literary sense, is somehow still lower than my usual expectations—and the development of human characters is as flimsy and hackneyed as I have come to expect in this genre, but I have to say that the approach to characterising both sentient and non-sentient spiders is actually creative and engaging.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Stay tuned for a future review in my <fr:link href="/jms-015X/" title="The Jon Sterling Review of Books" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-015X/" display-uri="jms-015X" type="local">culture blog</fr:link>!</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" numbered="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W15/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>2025-W15</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/2025-W15/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W15">Weeknotes 2025-W15</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>I have a lot to say this week, so strap in.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A0/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A0</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A0/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Forester 5.0 development: canonical URLs, atom feeds, and LSP"><fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" title="Forester 5.0" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link> development: canonical URLs, atom feeds, and LSP</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Work on <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" title="Forester 5.0" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link> proceeds apace, generously supported by <fr:link href="/jms-00XB/" title="Advanced Research + Invention Agency" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00XB/" display-uri="jms-00XB" type="local">ARIA</fr:link> who have engaged <fr:link href="/kentookura/" title="Kento Okura" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/kentookura/" display-uri="kentookura" type="local">Kento Okura</fr:link> and myself on a consulting basis to support their internal use of Forester. My recent goals have been to bring Forester closer in line with the architecture of the World Wide Web; to that end, I have made two big improvements.</html:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AA/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AA</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AA/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="First cut at canonical URLs">First cut at canonical URLs</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>Trees are addressed by “canonical URLs” that are meant to be the place where they will ultimately be published. See <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/JVIT/" title="Towards Forester 5.0 II: a design for canonical URLs" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/JVIT/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/JVIT/" type="local">my blog post</fr:link> on the design for more details. Canonical URLs are of the form <html:code>https://www.my-host.net/tree-name/</html:code>; the handling is a little fragile right now and you can expect bugs (but please write to me about them).</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AB/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AB</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AB/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="First cut at atom syndication">First cut at atom syndication</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>It is now possible to syndicate the children of a tree as an Atom feed. This is done currently by including the following directive in the tree you wish to syndicate:</html:p>
                        <html:pre><![CDATA[\syndicate-current-tree-as-atom-feed]]></html:pre>
                        <html:p>Then, if your tree is located at <html:code>https://www.my-host.net/tree-name/</html:code>, you will find that there is an atom feed at <html:code>https://www.my-host.net/tree-name/atom.xml</html:code>. There are many subtleties to this, and the atom support will continue to evolve and improve. One thing I need to deal with is the fact that Forester produces nested hyperlinks—which are not valid in HTML! I came up with a pretty slick way to <fr:link href="https://git.sr.ht/~jonsterling/forester-base-theme/commit/a251f9cf19b0ff42f4553d315df5181b985c79cb" type="external">handle this in XSLT</fr:link>, but that Atom renderer is intended to bypass that entirely.</html:p>
                        <html:p>As a side note, I am very happy to see that I am <fr:link href="https://patrick.sirref.org/weekly-2025-03-31/" type="external">not the only person</fr:link> using the new support for Atom feeds. Patrick’s fork of Forester is looking pretty cool, and I am excited to learn more from what he is doing. I’m also relieved that he was able to get rebased atop the ever-changing <html:code>forester-5.0-dev</html:code> branch.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AC/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01AC</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01AC/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Federation is still janky">Federation is still janky</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>One thing I want to start designing soon is how best to handle federated forests. Right now, Forester bundles all the imported material under a <html:code>foreign/my-friends-host/</html:code> directory and routes all links accordingly, but in many (but not all!) cases one would want to not bundle things at all and instead have links routed directly to the canonical URLs as published on the World Wide Web. I am not sure of the best design for this, so I welcome feedback. In the meanwhile, enjoy the janky prototype feel.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A9/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01A9</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01A9/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Language server; code completion via effects and handlers">Language server; code completion via effects and handlers</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p><fr:link href="/kentookura/" title="Kento Okura" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/kentookura/" display-uri="kentookura" type="local">Kento</fr:link> is hard at work hardening Forester’s language server. I am hoping that we will have something to show on the scale of a week.</html:p>
                        <html:p>There were some subtleties about how to provide completion information at a source location—which is at least as complex as the expander itself, since scope emerges from the expansion process. We had something fairly broken in place, which I have spent Thursday and Friday morning replacing with something cool using OCaml 5’s effects and handlers. The idea is to instrument the expander with an effect that notifies observes that it has entered a source range; this can be handled as a no-op, <html:em>or</html:em> by querying the scope’s available symbols when it enters the desired range and throwing away the continuation, and resuming the continuation otherwise to keep searching. This approach allows all the scope-handling code to be unified into a single routine, whose behaviour is controlled by effect handlers on the outside.</html:p>
                        <html:p>As a side note, I am looking forward to when the next version of <fr:link href="https://topiary.tweag.io/" type="external">Topiary</fr:link> is released, which should contain support for formatting OCaml’s effect handlers. Right now we don’t use the nice notation because we are stuck on Topiary 0.6.0.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A1/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A1</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A1/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Project Pterosaur: yes, I’m building a new proof assistant"><fr:link href="/jms-019E/" title="Project Pterosaur" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019E/" display-uri="jms-019E" type="local">Project Pterosaur</fr:link>: yes, I’m building a new proof assistant</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I swore after building <fr:link href="https://github.com/RedPRL/cooltt" type="external">cooltt</fr:link>, <fr:link href="https://github.com/RedPRL/redtt" type="external">redtt</fr:link>, and <fr:link href="https://github.com/RedPRL/sml-redprl" type="external">RedPRL</fr:link> that I would never build another proof assistant, as the experience burned around four years of my PhD and resulted (at least directly) in very little publishable work—but, to be fair, I probably would not have made the <fr:link href="/jms-0014/" title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-0014/" display-uri="jms-0014" type="local">key mathematical discovery</fr:link> of my <fr:link href="/sterling-2021-thesis/" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-2021-thesis/" display-uri="sterling-2021-thesis" type="local">PhD thesis</fr:link> if it were not for these engineering experiments. But I’m back on my bullshit, as the young people say, and hard at work building a new interactive proof assistant that I have code-named <fr:link href="/jms-019E/" title="Project Pterosaur" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019E/" display-uri="jms-019E" type="local">Project Pterosaur</fr:link>.</html:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A2/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01A2</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01A2/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Locales in dependent type theory?">Locales in dependent type theory?</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>The goal of Pterosaur is to explore the adaptation of <html:em>locales</html:em> from Isabelle to dependent type theory, as a lightweight but extremely expressive alternative to type classes. My colleague <fr:link href="/lawrencepaulson/" title="Lawrence Paulson" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lawrencepaulson/" display-uri="lawrencepaulson" type="local">Larry Paulson</fr:link> has written <fr:link href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/locales" type="external">some great blog posts about locales in Isabelle</fr:link>, and I strongly recommend reading Ballarin’s <fr:link href="https://www21.in.tum.de/~ballarin/publications/jar2019.pdf" type="external">Exploring the Structure of an Algebra Text with Locales</fr:link> to get a feel for what is possible. Here is what locales do:</html:p>
                        <html:ol><html:li>Locales appear to completely solve the pain involved when building up hierarchies of mathematical structures and notations, allowing you to effortlessly combine theories along a common core (e.g. defining rings in terms of a multiplicative monoid and an Abelian group sharing the same carrier).</html:li>
      <html:li>Locales allow you to <html:em>add new methods</html:em> to a theory after the fact, and they will magically be available on anything that extended that theory. You can also add new links in the theory graph, and both cycles and diamonds are allowed so long as they are coherent; this is useful if you want to silently regard (e.g.) the space of endomaps on a set as a monoid, etc.</html:li></html:ol>
                        <html:p>In comparison to modules and type classes, the strength of locales is that you don’t have to decide ahead of time whether you want to “bundle” fields with their carriers, etc. In contrast, a great deal of the difficult work of mathematical library design and maintainance in tools like Rocq, Agda, and <fr:link href="/jms-019G/" title="Lean" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019G/" display-uri="jms-019G" type="local">Lean</fr:link> is figuring out just what things to bundle, and fixing things when your choices inevitably lead to breakage, etc. Locales avoid these problems entirely.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Finally, a reasonably usable locale implementation can be obtained <html:em>without any higher-order unification whatsoever</html:em>. I have a feeling that will be extremely important, given how unreliable (and <fr:link href="https://github.com/agda/agda/issues/5837" type="external">incorrect</fr:link>!) most implementations of higher-order unification are; the situation is so bad that it is actually an open problem to define a correct higher-order unification algorithm in the presence of singleton types (such as the unit type). I do think that this can be solved (and may have already been solved by Andras Kovacs), but my point is that the prognosis for unification in dependent type theory is bad.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A3/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01A3</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01A3/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="Experimental implementation in Lean">Experimental implementation in <fr:link href="/jms-019G/" title="Lean" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019G/" display-uri="jms-019G" type="local">Lean</fr:link></fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>The other interesting thing about Pterosaur is that I am implementing it in <fr:link href="/jms-019G/" title="Lean" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019G/" display-uri="jms-019G" type="local">Lean</fr:link>; I am not verifying anything, and am making free use of Lean’s <html:code>partial</html:code> keyword (which hides potentially divergent code from definitional equality). Instead, I am thinking of Lean as a “better OCaml”: I can’t speak to the quality of the compiler and code generator, but I can absolutely say that from the perspective of day-to-day programming, Lean has a lot of affordances that make it extremely nice to use. On the other hand, Lean’s story for modularity is not so good; but I hope they don’t “fix” it any time soon, because I think that something like locales could be a good option for Lean itself in the future if I am able to demonstrate their potential in the context of Pterosaur’s clean-room implementation.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A4/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01A4</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01A4/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="A taste of code">A taste of code</fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>I will have more to say about Pterosaur in the future, but let me leave you with a bit of demo code.</html:p>
                        <html:pre><![CDATA[locale Magma { A =>
  car : Type,
  car.isSet : isSet A·car,
  cmp : (x y : A·car) → A·car
}

locale Magma.Hom { f =>
  dom : Magma,
  cod : Magma,
  car : (x : f·dom·car) → f·cod·car,
  cmp : (x y : f·dom·car) → Id f·cod·car (f·car (f·dom·cmp x y)) (f·cod·cmp (f·car x) (f·car y))
}

locale Semigroup { A =>
  splice magma : Magma,
  cmp.assoc : (x y z : A·car) → Id A·car (A·cmp (A·cmp x y) z) (A·cmp x (A·cmp y z))
}

locale Semigroup.Hom {f =>
  dom : Semigroup,
  cod : Semigroup,
  splice magma.hom : Magma.Hom / {dom := f·dom·magma, cod := f·cod·magma}
}

locale Monoid { A =>
  splice semigroup : Semigroup,
  unit : A·car,
  cmp.leftUnit : (x : A·car) → Id A·car (A·cmp A·unit x) x,
  cmp.rightUnit : (x : A·car) → Id A·car (A·cmp x A·unit) x
}

locale Monoid.Hom {f =>
  dom : Monoid,
  cod : Monoid,
  splice semigroup.hom : Semigroup.Hom / {dom := f·dom·semigroup, cod := f·cod·semigroup},
  unit : Id f·cod·car (f·car f·dom·unit) f·cod·unit
}

locale Group { G =>
  splice monoid : Monoid,
  inv : (x : G·car) → G·car,
  inv.inv : (x : G·car) → Id G·car (G·inv (G·inv x)) x
}

locale AbelianGroup { A =>
  splice group : Group,
  splice commutativeOperation : CommutativeOperation / {car := A·car, cmp := A·cmp}
}]]></html:pre>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A5/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A5</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A5/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Two papers to appear in LICS ’25">Two papers to appear in <fr:link href="/lics-2025/" title="LICS ’25: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lics-2025/" display-uri="lics-2025" type="local">LICS ’25</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>This week I have had two papers accepted at <fr:link href="/lics-2025/" title="LICS ’25: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lics-2025/" display-uri="lics-2025" type="local">LICS ’25</fr:link>; I’m excited about both of them.</html:p>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A6/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01A6</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01A6/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="With Leoni Pugh: When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?">With <fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/pugh-sterling-2025/" title="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/pugh-sterling-2025/" display-uri="pugh-sterling-2025" type="local">When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?</fr:link></fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p><fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link> is my old Part III student from 2023–2024, and this work builds on her Part III dissertation. The goal of our paper was to better understand the relationship between two approaches to partial functions in denotational semantics:</html:p>
                        <html:ol><html:li><html:strong>“Geometrical” partiality / “the Sierpiński cone”</html:strong>: freely add a lowest element to the space representing a given data type. This is useful for defining functions whose <html:em>inputs</html:em> are partially defined, because you can do a case-analysis on the definedness of the input.</html:li>
      <html:li><html:strong>“Logical” partiality / “the partial map classifier”</html:strong>: representing partially defined elements of a space <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">X</mml:mi></mml:math> by pairs 
  <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[(]]></mml:mo>
   <mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">p</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">,</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">x</mml:mi>
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[)]]></mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow></mml:math>
  where <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">p</mml:mi></mml:math> is a proposition and <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">x</mml:mi></mml:math> is a function from <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">isTrue</mml:mi>
  <mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[(]]></mml:mo>
   <mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">p</mml:mi>
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[)]]></mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
 </mml:mrow></mml:math> to <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">X</mml:mi></mml:math>. This is useful for defining functions whose <html:em>outputs</html:em> are partially defined.</html:li></html:ol>
                        <html:p>In traditional domain theory as developed by <fr:link href="/danascott/" title="Dana Scott" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/danascott/" display-uri="danascott" type="local">Scott</fr:link>, the two kinds of partiality coincide—<fr:link href="/sterling-2024-lifting/" title="Tensorial structure of the lifting doctrine in constructive domain theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-2024-lifting/" display-uri="sterling-2024-lifting" type="local">even constructively</fr:link>. I am, however, interested in <fr:link href="/hyland-1991/" title="First steps in synthetic domain theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hyland-1991/" display-uri="hyland-1991" type="local"><html:em>synthetic domain theory</html:em></fr:link> which abstracts away from continuity and limits and lets you just use sets and functions rather than cpos and continuous functions—provided that you avoid non-constructive principles like the Axiom of Choice or the Law of Excluded Middle. The starting point of our work is my observation that the two notions cannot coincide <html:em>absolutely</html:em> in synthetic domain theory, but that there may be restricted subuniverses in which they do coincide. The main result of our paper is to define such a subuniverse, made possible by my discovery of the <html:em>based Segal condition</html:em>—a strengthening of the usual Segal condition for higher categories.</html:p>
                        <html:p>A broader motivation of this work is to develop synthetic domain theory and synthetic higher category theory within the same framework. Whereas synthetic domain theory traditionally concerned itself with spaces that behaved like ω-complete partial orders (but where all functions are automatically monotone and continuous), the same ideas (if applied within <fr:link href="/hottbook/" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hottbook/" display-uri="hottbook" type="local">homotopy type theory</fr:link>) allow you to consider spaces that behave like <html:em>∞-categories</html:em> with colimits of ω-chains (but where all functions are automatically ∞-functorial and ω-continuous). I believe that unifying domain theory and higher category theory will prove useful for studying things like the denotational semantics of concurrency, which is inherently higher-dimensional.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                    <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                      <fr:frontmatter>
                        <fr:authors>
                          <fr:author>
                            <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                          </fr:author>
                        </fr:authors>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:date>
                          <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                          <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                          <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                        </fr:date>
                        <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A7/</fr:uri>
                        <fr:display-uri>jms-01A7</fr:display-uri>
                        <fr:route>/jms-01A7/</fr:route>
                        <fr:title text="With Andrew Slattery: Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories">With <fr:link href="/andrewslattery/" title="Andrew Slattery" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/andrewslattery/" display-uri="andrewslattery" type="local">Andrew Slattery</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/slattery-sterling-2025/" title="Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/slattery-sterling-2025/" display-uri="slattery-sterling-2025" type="local">Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories</fr:link></fr:title>
                      </fr:frontmatter>
                      <fr:mainmatter>
                        <html:p>This year, <fr:link href="/thomasstreicher/" title="Thomas Streicher" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/thomasstreicher/" display-uri="thomasstreicher" type="local">Thomas Streicher</fr:link> (born 1958) passed away from cancer. Thomas was one of the Greats of dependent type theory and he also wrote an <fr:link href="https://www.abebooks.co.uk/9789812701428/Domain-theoretic-Foundations-Functional-Programming-Streicher-9812701427/plp" type="external">excellent textbook on domain theory for denotational semantics</fr:link>, but much more importantly he was kind and curious and patient and always made time for young people. While I was still finding my place in the community, Thomas was very generous to me with his time and advice, and he sent me many papers to referee.</html:p>
                        <html:p>Although Thomas made many contributions to dependent type theory, domain theory, realisability theory, and category theory, he is most known to type theorists for two things—both in collaboration with the late <fr:link href="/martinhofmann/" title="Martin Hofmann" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/martinhofmann/" display-uri="martinhofmann" type="local">Martin Hofmann</fr:link>: the <fr:link href="/hofmann-streicher-1998/" title="The groupoid interpretation of type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hofmann-streicher-1998/" display-uri="hofmann-streicher-1998" type="local">groupoid interpretation of type theory</fr:link> and the eponymous  <fr:link href="/hofmann-streicher-1997/" title="Lifting Grothendieck universes" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hofmann-streicher-1997/" display-uri="hofmann-streicher-1997" type="local">Hofmann–Streicher universe lifting construction</fr:link>. Andrew and my paper pertains to the latter.</html:p>
                        <html:p>The idea of Hofmann–Streicher lifting has to do with universes, which are “types of types” (typically defined in such a way as to avoid paradoxes). Martin-Löf type theory usually includes universes in order to be able to quantify over (small enough) types; in the simplest models of Martin-Löf type theory, types are interpreted as sets and so Martin-Löf’s universes are interpreted as certain sets of sets, such as <fr:link href="/sga-4/" title="Théorie des topos et cohomologie étale des schémas (SGA 4)" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sga-4/" display-uri="sga-4" type="local">Grothendieck universes</fr:link>. But it is important to be able to interpret the language of type theory in more sophisticated worlds than set theory: for example, in <html:em>presheaves</html:em> (which are functors from a fixed category <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">C</mml:mi></mml:math> into <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Set</mml:mi></mml:math>).  What <fr:link href="/hofmann-streicher-1997/" title="Lifting Grothendieck universes" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hofmann-streicher-1997/" display-uri="hofmann-streicher-1997" type="local">Hofmann and Streicher</fr:link> did is show how to transform any universe of sets into a universe of presheaves!</html:p>
                        <html:p>Although Hofmann and Streicher’s construction worked well and had good properties, they did not find a <html:em>universal property</html:em> for it—which is an abstract description of the object that determines it uniquely up to isomorphism, usually in terms of how it relates to other objects. Recently <fr:link href="/awodey-2024-universes/" title="On Hofmann–Streicher universes" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/awodey-2024-universes/" display-uri="awodey-2024-universes" type="local">Awodey</fr:link> found a 1-dimensional universal property, which was the starting point of our work. What Andrew and I wanted to do is generalise Awodey’s analysis in two directions:</html:p>
                        <html:ol><html:li>We wanted a <html:em>2-dimensional</html:em> version, which is useful because it captures more about the universe than can be said in just one dimension: for example, with a 2-dimensional version, you can see immediately (by “abstract nonsense”) that Hofmann–Streicher lifting preserves structures like monads, adjunctions, etc. that might be used for modelling computational effects, etc.</html:li>
      <html:li>We wanted a <html:em>relative</html:em> version, which would make it easier to iterate the Hofmann–Streicher lifting construction: the purpose of this is to be able to define presheaf models of type theory <html:em>internal</html:em> to other presheaf models. These kind of situations actually happen in practice! For example, the model of <fr:link href="/bbcgsv-2019/" title="Guarded cubical type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/bbcgsv-2019/" display-uri="bbcgsv-2019" type="local">guarded cubical type theory</fr:link> that combines step-indexing with univalence ought to be an example of this.</html:li></html:ol>
                        <html:p>To develop this two-fold generalisation of Hofmann–Streicher lifting, we resituated the theory in terms of another of Thomas’s favourite topics: the theory of <html:em>fibrations</html:em>, on which Thomas had written <fr:link href="/streicher-fcjb/" title="Fibred categories à la Jean Bénabou" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/streicher-fcjb/" display-uri="streicher-fcjb" type="local">the most wonderful lecture notes</fr:link>.</html:p>
                        <html:p>We dedicated our paper to Thomas’s memory. May he rest in peace.</html:p>
                      </fr:mainmatter>
                    </fr:tree>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A8/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A8</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A8/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Reading corner: The Fountains of Paradise"><fr:link href="/jms-01AY/" title="Reading corner" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AY/" display-uri="jms-01AY" type="local">Reading corner</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/clarke-1979/" title="The Fountains of Paradise" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/clarke-1979/" display-uri="clarke-1979" type="local">The Fountains of Paradise</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I recently read Arthur C. Clarke’s <fr:link href="/clarke-1979/" title="The Fountains of Paradise" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/clarke-1979/" display-uri="clarke-1979" type="local">The Fountains of Paradise</fr:link>; although it was a pretty good read, I found that like many science fiction books of that era, one has to look past a lot in order to enjoy it. I wrote some commentary in my post entitled <fr:link href="/jms-019W/" title="Ventriloquy of the Mid-Century Man" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019W/" display-uri="jms-019W" type="local">Ventriloquy of the Mid-Century Man</fr:link> on my culture blog <fr:link href="/jms-015X/" title="The Jon Sterling Review of Books" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-015X/" display-uri="jms-015X" type="local">The Jon Sterling Review of Books</fr:link>.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AH</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-01AH/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work">Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>Over the Christmas holiday, I bought an iMac off eBay for £50. Why was it so cheap? Because it is a 2006 model firing on a single gigabyte of RAM with an Intel Core 2 Duo processor, running Mac OS X Tiger. When I was a kid, I dreamed of having a computer like this—for me, the white plastic era will always be peak Apple design, and Tiger’s version of Aqua was the most polished and refined form of the design language that they ever managed to produce. My first Macintosh was a white polycarbonate unibody MacBook running Leopard—and at the time I greatly regretted having just missed the Tiger era for the gaudy and overly darkened feel of Leopard with its sinister-coloured window controls. I did not know at the time how much worse things would get…</html:p>
            <html:p>My excuse for purchasing this machine was that I “needed” to run Mac OS X Tiger as “research” for my experimental project <fr:link href="https://github.com/jonsterling/aquaui" type="external">AquaUI</fr:link>, which imagines how the Aqua design language could have evolved if it had been allowed to. But really, I wanted to relive my rare trips to Apple retailers as a kid, where I would spend minutes doing nothing but just moving the scrollbar while watching its stationary “wave” texture, or highlighting buttons to see them burst with blue radiance.</html:p>
            <html:p>(I spoke about many of the topics covered in this post in my appearance on the <fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/" type="external">Kodsnack podcast</fr:link> hosted by Fredrik Björeman: <html:em><fr:link href="https://kodsnack.se/international/626/" type="external">Episode 626, “The great flattening of everything”</fr:link></html:em>.)</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AI/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AI</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AI/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?">Day One: what can you do 19 year old iMac?</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>When the delivery came, I took the machine gingerly out of its battered and taped over original packaging and turned it on to a feeling of great excitement, which quickly gave way to loss and melancholy: so much of what computers are “for” involves the World Wide Web, and the forced transition to HTTPS/TLS has stolen access to the Web from users of many working computers of access to the Web (unless they gut the machine by downgrading to a modern but severely less polished operating system, like Linux). The old Intel Macs are a prime example of this loss—although some <fr:link href="https://tenfourfox.blogspot.com/" type="external">volunteer projects exist</fr:link> to enable safe access to the Web for PowerPC machines, older Intel Macintoshes have received comparatively less attention. Capitalist forced obsolescence comes to all, however, and there will no doubt come a time when the “necessary” “security” routines will simply not be executable with the kinds of hardware resources that could be mustered in 2006, no matter the system architecture. After playing around and finding much of the functionality crippled due to being barred from the Internet, I had to ask myself, <html:strong>What should I even do with this thing?</html:strong></html:p>
                <html:p>The iMac lay dormant in my <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">College</fr:link> room for the next few months while I figured out an answer to that question.</html:p>
                <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiejjxl32uo7vfhgpkbkxuiww4vabuu745bhajcrleqi7uz4blqjay.gif" />

    <html:figcaption>My iMac sleeping peacefully in my office at <fr:link href="/jms-00GP/" title="Clare College" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00GP/" display-uri="jms-00GP" type="local">Clare College</fr:link> Memorial Court, connected to a vintage A1048 keyboard and Apple Pro Mouse (as it should be!). Nearby is my iPod Classic, which I use for about an hour each day and charge once every 6-8 weeks.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AJ/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AJ</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AJ/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="With a little love, everything has a use">With a little love, <html:em>everything</html:em> has a use</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Last week I finally realised that there is a lot I can still do with this machine. I turned it on when I had a bit of free time, and found that it remains very snappy—software opens instantly without hanging, and in fact the built-in programs are significantly less bug-ridden than they were in subsequent versions of Mac OS X and its (unworthy) successor macOS. To put this into perspective, the “outdated” iMac’s performance was far better than that of my last Intel iMac from 2020 with sixteen times the RAM and several times the processor cores.</html:p>
                <html:p>It is well-known that hardware capabilities get better and better each year, but this did not translate into improved performance for users until after the Apple Silicon transition—when the hardware improvement was so great that it was able to outpace the deathmarch of inefficient software, for a time. Don’t worry, the “transition to AI” is going to destroy all those gains soon and we’ll be back where we started.</html:p>
                <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiaaxhqvbslbd3sb6mafhlrxswbdbwipj4bzhuewlg7il73mhq7l7y.jpeg" />

    <html:figcaption>Mac OS X Tiger is still King—with the peak versions of Finder, Preview, and iTunes.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
                <html:p>But I digress. Even if you can’t use the Web, there are many things that a 19 year old iMac running Mac OS X Tiger is better at than a more recently manufactured machine. For example, Tiger was the last version of Mac OS X in which Preview.app (the PDF and image viewer) had a working search interface; from the subsequent version (Leopard) all the way until the present day, searching is somehow both too fuzzy and not fuzzy enough, and there seems to be no combination of quotation marks that will lead to reasonable results appearing in the search pane. (Same with Mail.app, which has somehow got <html:em>even worse</html:em> in the past year; you can’t connect to email on such an old machine anyway, so the point is moot.)</html:p>
                <html:p>Similarly, iTunes 7 was the functional peak for Apple’s music management and playback software (although iTunes 6 was visually superior), and people who have only used Apple’s current “Music” app will not be able to understand what they are missing. Likewise, the version of Finder shipped with Tiger was the most polished and least buggy version they ever produced; it is really amazing to switch back and forth between macOS 15.3 and Mac OS X 10.4, and find that most of the bugs or usability problems I have encountered on a daily basis for the past decade or so are actually <html:em>regressions</html:em>.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AK/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AK</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AK/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="The perfect music and PDF reading workstation">The perfect music and PDF reading workstation</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>So I transferred my music and PDF libraries to the iMac—this was easy to do by creating a local WiFi network from the iMac, a functionality that has been removed in macOS(!). Indeed, modern macOS has replaced some (but not all) aspects of this functionality with what is called “Internet Sharing”, but this feature does not work reliably and in many cases the needful functionalities are unpredictably grayed out and disabled without any message explaining why. Death by a thousand papercuts... But I digress: I set up a local WiFi network with a file server easily using the old <html:em>System Preferences</html:em> application (don’t get me started on the bizarre redesign of System Settings introduced in macOS Ventura), and easily transferred everything I wanted to the iMac and then I was off to the races.</html:p>
                    <html:p>I listen to music and study papers on this machine, and it gives me so much joy to <html:em>use</html:em> this masterpiece of practical industrial design every day—I even write referee reports on it using an ancient version of <fr:link href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnioutliner/" type="external">OmniOutliner</fr:link>, a venerable piece of software that I have to say has not improved much in the past two decades. After installing a copy of <fr:link href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/scrivener" type="external">Scrivener 2.5</fr:link> (don’t worry, I own a license for <fr:link href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/" type="external">Scrivener 3.0</fr:link> and you should too!), I find myself creative writing in my free time like it’s 2006.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AL/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AL</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AL/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="What about my iPod Classic?">What about my iPod Classic?</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Some of you may be aware that I use an iPod Classic every day. The thing is a godsend—the best mobile device I own. I bought it with a fresh battery and SSD, and the damn battery lasts for months before I have to recharge it. That is the kind of technology that was taken from us and replaced by resource-intensive devices governed by the logic of planned obsolescence. But I have it back—my world is not the same as your world, but it is a world I am glad to have returned to.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Naturally, the first thing I wanted to do was use the iMac as a hub for synchronising the iPod with iTunes. This will work, but what I did not anticipate is that one of my main uses of the iPod is to listen to podcasts, and podcasts cannot be downloaded on the iMac because of the vicious imposition of TLS on all parts of the web that didn’t need it (<fr:link href="https://letsencrypt.org/" type="external">Let’s Encrypt</fr:link> really ought to have been called <html:em>Let’s Kill The Open Web</html:em>). So I continue synchronising my iPod with my modern day MacBook Air—and it is a testament to Apple’s historical approach to backward compatibility that this is still possible (and even integrated with the otherwise terrible Podcasts app!).</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AM/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AM</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AM/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Is retrocomputing sustainable?">Is retrocomputing sustainable?</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>I constantly feel a pang in the back of my throat when I think about retrocomputing over the long term. We are scrounging around for intact pieces of old technology, but there will come a time when these are too scarce, or when we have really lost the ability to repair them. It is like living in a post-apocalyptic film where a cataclysm has made all manufacturing impossible—but today the cataclysm is not a war or even a virus, but just the simple vicious logic of Capital and a technology industry that has hitched itself to the most ignorant and anti-human trends emanating from the most technologically ignorant people on Wall Street.</html:p>
                <html:p>Retrocomputing is decidedly <html:em>not</html:em> sustainable, in the same sense that living on a stash of canned foods that can no longer be manufactured cannot be sustainable. But also unsustainable is the present day technological treadmill of consumer goods containing precious metals and dangerous chemicals being produced in the billions and sent directly almost directly to the landfill.</html:p>
                <html:p>I think a better question to ask is whether retrocomputing is <html:em>progressive</html:em>. I think that retrocomputing can be progressive insofar as it is part of a practice of looking <html:em>forward</html:em>—how can we build sovereign technology that respects constrained resources as well as users of different abilities, and cannot be taken away or made useless by Capital and the irrational whims of the stock market. Such a project <html:em>must</html:em> have a significant design component, and this cannot be done amateurishly; looking to the iconic design languages of the past for inspiration and education is, then, deeply progressive in this environment.</html:p>
                <html:p>The tragedy of Mac OS X is not that Apple took it away and replaced it with something inferior: the tragedy is that free software communities have never managed to produce something even remotely approaching its level of fit and finish. Volunteer projects do not deserve my ire, which I reserve for our economic system in which nearly <html:em>all</html:em> competent design work is confined to corporate environments, and then wiped away when the wind shifts.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AN/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AN</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AN/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Bring back the joy in computing!">Bring back the joy in computing!</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Forget your troubles and find something that makes you smile, and reminds you of what is possible when a team brimming with talent comes together to build something beautiful.</html:p>
                <html:p>Write to me with any joyful and quirky projects, hardware or software, that you would like to share.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>9</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>11</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/2025-W15/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>2025-W15</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/2025-W15/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Weeknotes 2025-W15">Weeknotes 2025-W15</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>I have a lot to say this week, so strap in.</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A0/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01A0</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01A0/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Forester 5.0 development: canonical URLs, atom feeds, and LSP"><fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" title="Forester 5.0" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link> development: canonical URLs, atom feeds, and LSP</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Work on <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" title="Forester 5.0" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/jms-011P/" type="local">Forester 5.0</fr:link> proceeds apace, generously supported by <fr:link href="/jms-00XB/" title="Advanced Research + Invention Agency" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-00XB/" display-uri="jms-00XB" type="local">ARIA</fr:link> who have engaged <fr:link href="/kentookura/" title="Kento Okura" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/kentookura/" display-uri="kentookura" type="local">Kento Okura</fr:link> and myself on a consulting basis to support their internal use of Forester. My recent goals have been to bring Forester closer in line with the architecture of the World Wide Web; to that end, I have made two big improvements.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AA/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AA</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AA/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="First cut at canonical URLs">First cut at canonical URLs</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>Trees are addressed by “canonical URLs” that are meant to be the place where they will ultimately be published. See <fr:link href="https://www.forester-notes.org/JVIT/" title="Towards Forester 5.0 II: a design for canonical URLs" uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/JVIT/" display-uri="https://www.forester-notes.org/JVIT/" type="local">my blog post</fr:link> on the design for more details. Canonical URLs are of the form <html:code>https://www.my-host.net/tree-name/</html:code>; the handling is a little fragile right now and you can expect bugs (but please write to me about them).</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AB/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AB</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AB/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="First cut at atom syndication">First cut at atom syndication</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>It is now possible to syndicate the children of a tree as an Atom feed. This is done currently by including the following directive in the tree you wish to syndicate:</html:p>
                    <html:pre><![CDATA[\syndicate-current-tree-as-atom-feed]]></html:pre>
                    <html:p>Then, if your tree is located at <html:code>https://www.my-host.net/tree-name/</html:code>, you will find that there is an atom feed at <html:code>https://www.my-host.net/tree-name/atom.xml</html:code>. There are many subtleties to this, and the atom support will continue to evolve and improve. One thing I need to deal with is the fact that Forester produces nested hyperlinks—which are not valid in HTML! I came up with a pretty slick way to <fr:link href="https://git.sr.ht/~jonsterling/forester-base-theme/commit/a251f9cf19b0ff42f4553d315df5181b985c79cb" type="external">handle this in XSLT</fr:link>, but that Atom renderer is intended to bypass that entirely.</html:p>
                    <html:p>As a side note, I am very happy to see that I am <fr:link href="https://patrick.sirref.org/weekly-2025-03-31/" type="external">not the only person</fr:link> using the new support for Atom feeds. Patrick’s fork of Forester is looking pretty cool, and I am excited to learn more from what he is doing. I’m also relieved that he was able to get rebased atop the ever-changing <html:code>forester-5.0-dev</html:code> branch.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AC/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AC</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01AC/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Federation is still janky">Federation is still janky</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>One thing I want to start designing soon is how best to handle federated forests. Right now, Forester bundles all the imported material under a <html:code>foreign/my-friends-host/</html:code> directory and routes all links accordingly, but in many (but not all!) cases one would want to not bundle things at all and instead have links routed directly to the canonical URLs as published on the World Wide Web. I am not sure of the best design for this, so I welcome feedback. In the meanwhile, enjoy the janky prototype feel.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A9/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A9</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A9/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Language server; code completion via effects and handlers">Language server; code completion via effects and handlers</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p><fr:link href="/kentookura/" title="Kento Okura" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/kentookura/" display-uri="kentookura" type="local">Kento</fr:link> is hard at work hardening Forester’s language server. I am hoping that we will have something to show on the scale of a week.</html:p>
                    <html:p>There were some subtleties about how to provide completion information at a source location—which is at least as complex as the expander itself, since scope emerges from the expansion process. We had something fairly broken in place, which I have spent Thursday and Friday morning replacing with something cool using OCaml 5’s effects and handlers. The idea is to instrument the expander with an effect that notifies observes that it has entered a source range; this can be handled as a no-op, <html:em>or</html:em> by querying the scope’s available symbols when it enters the desired range and throwing away the continuation, and resuming the continuation otherwise to keep searching. This approach allows all the scope-handling code to be unified into a single routine, whose behaviour is controlled by effect handlers on the outside.</html:p>
                    <html:p>As a side note, I am looking forward to when the next version of <fr:link href="https://topiary.tweag.io/" type="external">Topiary</fr:link> is released, which should contain support for formatting OCaml’s effect handlers. Right now we don’t use the nice notation because we are stuck on Topiary 0.6.0.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A1/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01A1</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01A1/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Project Pterosaur: yes, I’m building a new proof assistant"><fr:link href="/jms-019E/" title="Project Pterosaur" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019E/" display-uri="jms-019E" type="local">Project Pterosaur</fr:link>: yes, I’m building a new proof assistant</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>I swore after building <fr:link href="https://github.com/RedPRL/cooltt" type="external">cooltt</fr:link>, <fr:link href="https://github.com/RedPRL/redtt" type="external">redtt</fr:link>, and <fr:link href="https://github.com/RedPRL/sml-redprl" type="external">RedPRL</fr:link> that I would never build another proof assistant, as the experience burned around four years of my PhD and resulted (at least directly) in very little publishable work—but, to be fair, I probably would not have made the <fr:link href="/jms-0014/" title="Chapter 7: normalization for cubical type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-0014/" display-uri="jms-0014" type="local">key mathematical discovery</fr:link> of my <fr:link href="/sterling-2021-thesis/" title="First steps in synthetic Tait computability: the objective metatheory of cubical type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-2021-thesis/" display-uri="sterling-2021-thesis" type="local">PhD thesis</fr:link> if it were not for these engineering experiments. But I’m back on my bullshit, as the young people say, and hard at work building a new interactive proof assistant that I have code-named <fr:link href="/jms-019E/" title="Project Pterosaur" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019E/" display-uri="jms-019E" type="local">Project Pterosaur</fr:link>.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A2/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A2</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A2/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Locales in dependent type theory?">Locales in dependent type theory?</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>The goal of Pterosaur is to explore the adaptation of <html:em>locales</html:em> from Isabelle to dependent type theory, as a lightweight but extremely expressive alternative to type classes. My colleague <fr:link href="/lawrencepaulson/" title="Lawrence Paulson" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lawrencepaulson/" display-uri="lawrencepaulson" type="local">Larry Paulson</fr:link> has written <fr:link href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io/tag/locales" type="external">some great blog posts about locales in Isabelle</fr:link>, and I strongly recommend reading Ballarin’s <fr:link href="https://www21.in.tum.de/~ballarin/publications/jar2019.pdf" type="external">Exploring the Structure of an Algebra Text with Locales</fr:link> to get a feel for what is possible. Here is what locales do:</html:p>
                    <html:ol><html:li>Locales appear to completely solve the pain involved when building up hierarchies of mathematical structures and notations, allowing you to effortlessly combine theories along a common core (e.g. defining rings in terms of a multiplicative monoid and an Abelian group sharing the same carrier).</html:li>
      <html:li>Locales allow you to <html:em>add new methods</html:em> to a theory after the fact, and they will magically be available on anything that extended that theory. You can also add new links in the theory graph, and both cycles and diamonds are allowed so long as they are coherent; this is useful if you want to silently regard (e.g.) the space of endomaps on a set as a monoid, etc.</html:li></html:ol>
                    <html:p>In comparison to modules and type classes, the strength of locales is that you don’t have to decide ahead of time whether you want to “bundle” fields with their carriers, etc. In contrast, a great deal of the difficult work of mathematical library design and maintainance in tools like Rocq, Agda, and <fr:link href="/jms-019G/" title="Lean" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019G/" display-uri="jms-019G" type="local">Lean</fr:link> is figuring out just what things to bundle, and fixing things when your choices inevitably lead to breakage, etc. Locales avoid these problems entirely.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Finally, a reasonably usable locale implementation can be obtained <html:em>without any higher-order unification whatsoever</html:em>. I have a feeling that will be extremely important, given how unreliable (and <fr:link href="https://github.com/agda/agda/issues/5837" type="external">incorrect</fr:link>!) most implementations of higher-order unification are; the situation is so bad that it is actually an open problem to define a correct higher-order unification algorithm in the presence of singleton types (such as the unit type). I do think that this can be solved (and may have already been solved by Andras Kovacs), but my point is that the prognosis for unification in dependent type theory is bad.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A3/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A3</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A3/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="Experimental implementation in Lean">Experimental implementation in <fr:link href="/jms-019G/" title="Lean" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019G/" display-uri="jms-019G" type="local">Lean</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>The other interesting thing about Pterosaur is that I am implementing it in <fr:link href="/jms-019G/" title="Lean" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019G/" display-uri="jms-019G" type="local">Lean</fr:link>; I am not verifying anything, and am making free use of Lean’s <html:code>partial</html:code> keyword (which hides potentially divergent code from definitional equality). Instead, I am thinking of Lean as a “better OCaml”: I can’t speak to the quality of the compiler and code generator, but I can absolutely say that from the perspective of day-to-day programming, Lean has a lot of affordances that make it extremely nice to use. On the other hand, Lean’s story for modularity is not so good; but I hope they don’t “fix” it any time soon, because I think that something like locales could be a good option for Lean itself in the future if I am able to demonstrate their potential in the context of Pterosaur’s clean-room implementation.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A4/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A4</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A4/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="A taste of code">A taste of code</fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>I will have more to say about Pterosaur in the future, but let me leave you with a bit of demo code.</html:p>
                    <html:pre><![CDATA[locale Magma { A =>
  car : Type,
  car.isSet : isSet A·car,
  cmp : (x y : A·car) → A·car
}

locale Magma.Hom { f =>
  dom : Magma,
  cod : Magma,
  car : (x : f·dom·car) → f·cod·car,
  cmp : (x y : f·dom·car) → Id f·cod·car (f·car (f·dom·cmp x y)) (f·cod·cmp (f·car x) (f·car y))
}

locale Semigroup { A =>
  splice magma : Magma,
  cmp.assoc : (x y z : A·car) → Id A·car (A·cmp (A·cmp x y) z) (A·cmp x (A·cmp y z))
}

locale Semigroup.Hom {f =>
  dom : Semigroup,
  cod : Semigroup,
  splice magma.hom : Magma.Hom / {dom := f·dom·magma, cod := f·cod·magma}
}

locale Monoid { A =>
  splice semigroup : Semigroup,
  unit : A·car,
  cmp.leftUnit : (x : A·car) → Id A·car (A·cmp A·unit x) x,
  cmp.rightUnit : (x : A·car) → Id A·car (A·cmp x A·unit) x
}

locale Monoid.Hom {f =>
  dom : Monoid,
  cod : Monoid,
  splice semigroup.hom : Semigroup.Hom / {dom := f·dom·semigroup, cod := f·cod·semigroup},
  unit : Id f·cod·car (f·car f·dom·unit) f·cod·unit
}

locale Group { G =>
  splice monoid : Monoid,
  inv : (x : G·car) → G·car,
  inv.inv : (x : G·car) → Id G·car (G·inv (G·inv x)) x
}

locale AbelianGroup { A =>
  splice group : Group,
  splice commutativeOperation : CommutativeOperation / {car := A·car, cmp := A·cmp}
}]]></html:pre>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A5/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01A5</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01A5/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Two papers to appear in LICS ’25">Two papers to appear in <fr:link href="/lics-2025/" title="LICS ’25: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lics-2025/" display-uri="lics-2025" type="local">LICS ’25</fr:link></fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>This week I have had two papers accepted at <fr:link href="/lics-2025/" title="LICS ’25: 40th Annual ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/lics-2025/" display-uri="lics-2025" type="local">LICS ’25</fr:link>; I’m excited about both of them.</html:p>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A6/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A6</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A6/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="With Leoni Pugh: When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?">With <fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/pugh-sterling-2025/" title="When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/pugh-sterling-2025/" display-uri="pugh-sterling-2025" type="local">When is the partial map classifier a Sierpiński cone?</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p><fr:link href="/leonipugh/" title="Leoni Pugh" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/leonipugh/" display-uri="leonipugh" type="local">Leoni Pugh</fr:link> is my old Part III student from 2023–2024, and this work builds on her Part III dissertation. The goal of our paper was to better understand the relationship between two approaches to partial functions in denotational semantics:</html:p>
                    <html:ol><html:li><html:strong>“Geometrical” partiality / “the Sierpiński cone”</html:strong>: freely add a lowest element to the space representing a given data type. This is useful for defining functions whose <html:em>inputs</html:em> are partially defined, because you can do a case-analysis on the definedness of the input.</html:li>
      <html:li><html:strong>“Logical” partiality / “the partial map classifier”</html:strong>: representing partially defined elements of a space <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">X</mml:mi></mml:math> by pairs 
  <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[(]]></mml:mo>
   <mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">p</mml:mi><mml:mo xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">,</mml:mo><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">x</mml:mi>
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[)]]></mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow></mml:math>
  where <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">p</mml:mi></mml:math> is a proposition and <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">x</mml:mi></mml:math> is a function from <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">isTrue</mml:mi>
  <mml:mrow xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[(]]></mml:mo>
   <mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">p</mml:mi>
   <mml:mo fence="true" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><![CDATA[)]]></mml:mo>
  </mml:mrow>
 </mml:mrow></mml:math> to <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">X</mml:mi></mml:math>. This is useful for defining functions whose <html:em>outputs</html:em> are partially defined.</html:li></html:ol>
                    <html:p>In traditional domain theory as developed by <fr:link href="/danascott/" title="Dana Scott" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/danascott/" display-uri="danascott" type="local">Scott</fr:link>, the two kinds of partiality coincide—<fr:link href="/sterling-2024-lifting/" title="Tensorial structure of the lifting doctrine in constructive domain theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sterling-2024-lifting/" display-uri="sterling-2024-lifting" type="local">even constructively</fr:link>. I am, however, interested in <fr:link href="/hyland-1991/" title="First steps in synthetic domain theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hyland-1991/" display-uri="hyland-1991" type="local"><html:em>synthetic domain theory</html:em></fr:link> which abstracts away from continuity and limits and lets you just use sets and functions rather than cpos and continuous functions—provided that you avoid non-constructive principles like the Axiom of Choice or the Law of Excluded Middle. The starting point of our work is my observation that the two notions cannot coincide <html:em>absolutely</html:em> in synthetic domain theory, but that there may be restricted subuniverses in which they do coincide. The main result of our paper is to define such a subuniverse, made possible by my discovery of the <html:em>based Segal condition</html:em>—a strengthening of the usual Segal condition for higher categories.</html:p>
                    <html:p>A broader motivation of this work is to develop synthetic domain theory and synthetic higher category theory within the same framework. Whereas synthetic domain theory traditionally concerned itself with spaces that behaved like ω-complete partial orders (but where all functions are automatically monotone and continuous), the same ideas (if applied within <fr:link href="/hottbook/" title="Homotopy Type Theory: univalent foundations of mathematics" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hottbook/" display-uri="hottbook" type="local">homotopy type theory</fr:link>) allow you to consider spaces that behave like <html:em>∞-categories</html:em> with colimits of ω-chains (but where all functions are automatically ∞-functorial and ω-continuous). I believe that unifying domain theory and higher category theory will prove useful for studying things like the denotational semantics of concurrency, which is inherently higher-dimensional.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
                <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
                  <fr:frontmatter>
                    <fr:authors>
                      <fr:author>
                        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                      </fr:author>
                    </fr:authors>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:date>
                      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                      <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                    </fr:date>
                    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A7/</fr:uri>
                    <fr:display-uri>jms-01A7</fr:display-uri>
                    <fr:route>/jms-01A7/</fr:route>
                    <fr:title text="With Andrew Slattery: Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories">With <fr:link href="/andrewslattery/" title="Andrew Slattery" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/andrewslattery/" display-uri="andrewslattery" type="local">Andrew Slattery</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/slattery-sterling-2025/" title="Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/slattery-sterling-2025/" display-uri="slattery-sterling-2025" type="local">Hofmann–Streicher lifting of fibred categories</fr:link></fr:title>
                  </fr:frontmatter>
                  <fr:mainmatter>
                    <html:p>This year, <fr:link href="/thomasstreicher/" title="Thomas Streicher" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/thomasstreicher/" display-uri="thomasstreicher" type="local">Thomas Streicher</fr:link> (born 1958) passed away from cancer. Thomas was one of the Greats of dependent type theory and he also wrote an <fr:link href="https://www.abebooks.co.uk/9789812701428/Domain-theoretic-Foundations-Functional-Programming-Streicher-9812701427/plp" type="external">excellent textbook on domain theory for denotational semantics</fr:link>, but much more importantly he was kind and curious and patient and always made time for young people. While I was still finding my place in the community, Thomas was very generous to me with his time and advice, and he sent me many papers to referee.</html:p>
                    <html:p>Although Thomas made many contributions to dependent type theory, domain theory, realisability theory, and category theory, he is most known to type theorists for two things—both in collaboration with the late <fr:link href="/martinhofmann/" title="Martin Hofmann" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/martinhofmann/" display-uri="martinhofmann" type="local">Martin Hofmann</fr:link>: the <fr:link href="/hofmann-streicher-1998/" title="The groupoid interpretation of type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hofmann-streicher-1998/" display-uri="hofmann-streicher-1998" type="local">groupoid interpretation of type theory</fr:link> and the eponymous  <fr:link href="/hofmann-streicher-1997/" title="Lifting Grothendieck universes" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hofmann-streicher-1997/" display-uri="hofmann-streicher-1997" type="local">Hofmann–Streicher universe lifting construction</fr:link>. Andrew and my paper pertains to the latter.</html:p>
                    <html:p>The idea of Hofmann–Streicher lifting has to do with universes, which are “types of types” (typically defined in such a way as to avoid paradoxes). Martin-Löf type theory usually includes universes in order to be able to quantify over (small enough) types; in the simplest models of Martin-Löf type theory, types are interpreted as sets and so Martin-Löf’s universes are interpreted as certain sets of sets, such as <fr:link href="/sga-4/" title="Théorie des topos et cohomologie étale des schémas (SGA 4)" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/sga-4/" display-uri="sga-4" type="local">Grothendieck universes</fr:link>. But it is important to be able to interpret the language of type theory in more sophisticated worlds than set theory: for example, in <html:em>presheaves</html:em> (which are functors from a fixed category <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">C</mml:mi></mml:math> into <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Set</mml:mi></mml:math>).  What <fr:link href="/hofmann-streicher-1997/" title="Lifting Grothendieck universes" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/hofmann-streicher-1997/" display-uri="hofmann-streicher-1997" type="local">Hofmann and Streicher</fr:link> did is show how to transform any universe of sets into a universe of presheaves!</html:p>
                    <html:p>Although Hofmann and Streicher’s construction worked well and had good properties, they did not find a <html:em>universal property</html:em> for it—which is an abstract description of the object that determines it uniquely up to isomorphism, usually in terms of how it relates to other objects. Recently <fr:link href="/awodey-2024-universes/" title="On Hofmann–Streicher universes" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/awodey-2024-universes/" display-uri="awodey-2024-universes" type="local">Awodey</fr:link> found a 1-dimensional universal property, which was the starting point of our work. What Andrew and I wanted to do is generalise Awodey’s analysis in two directions:</html:p>
                    <html:ol><html:li>We wanted a <html:em>2-dimensional</html:em> version, which is useful because it captures more about the universe than can be said in just one dimension: for example, with a 2-dimensional version, you can see immediately (by “abstract nonsense”) that Hofmann–Streicher lifting preserves structures like monads, adjunctions, etc. that might be used for modelling computational effects, etc.</html:li>
      <html:li>We wanted a <html:em>relative</html:em> version, which would make it easier to iterate the Hofmann–Streicher lifting construction: the purpose of this is to be able to define presheaf models of type theory <html:em>internal</html:em> to other presheaf models. These kind of situations actually happen in practice! For example, the model of <fr:link href="/bbcgsv-2019/" title="Guarded cubical type theory" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/bbcgsv-2019/" display-uri="bbcgsv-2019" type="local">guarded cubical type theory</fr:link> that combines step-indexing with univalence ought to be an example of this.</html:li></html:ol>
                    <html:p>To develop this two-fold generalisation of Hofmann–Streicher lifting, we resituated the theory in terms of another of Thomas’s favourite topics: the theory of <html:em>fibrations</html:em>, on which Thomas had written <fr:link href="/streicher-fcjb/" title="Fibred categories à la Jean Bénabou" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/streicher-fcjb/" display-uri="streicher-fcjb" type="local">the most wonderful lecture notes</fr:link>.</html:p>
                    <html:p>We dedicated our paper to Thomas’s memory. May he rest in peace.</html:p>
                  </fr:mainmatter>
                </fr:tree>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>9</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>11</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01A8/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01A8</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01A8/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Reading corner: The Fountains of Paradise"><fr:link href="/jms-01AY/" title="Reading corner" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AY/" display-uri="jms-01AY" type="local">Reading corner</fr:link>: <fr:link href="/clarke-1979/" title="The Fountains of Paradise" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/clarke-1979/" display-uri="clarke-1979" type="local">The Fountains of Paradise</fr:link></fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>I recently read Arthur C. Clarke’s <fr:link href="/clarke-1979/" title="The Fountains of Paradise" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/clarke-1979/" display-uri="clarke-1979" type="local">The Fountains of Paradise</fr:link>; although it was a pretty good read, I found that like many science fiction books of that era, one has to look past a lot in order to enjoy it. I wrote some commentary in my post entitled <fr:link href="/jms-019W/" title="Ventriloquy of the Mid-Century Man" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-019W/" display-uri="jms-019W" type="local">Ventriloquy of the Mid-Century Man</fr:link> on my culture blog <fr:link href="/jms-015X/" title="The Jon Sterling Review of Books" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-015X/" display-uri="jms-015X" type="local">The Jon Sterling Review of Books</fr:link>.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
