<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
      <fr:month>4</fr:month>
      <fr:day>17</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AL/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>jms-01AL</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/jms-01AL/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work › With a little love, everything has a use › What about my iPod Classic?"><fr:link href="/jms-01AJ/" title="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work › With a little love, everything has a use" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AJ/" display-uri="jms-01AJ" type="local"><fr:link href="/jms-01AH/" title="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/" display-uri="jms-01AH" type="local">Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work</fr:link> › With a little love, <html:em>everything</html:em> has a use</fr:link> › What about my iPod Classic?</fr:title>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <html:p>Some of you may be aware that I use an iPod Classic every day. The thing is a godsend—the best mobile device I own. I bought it with a fresh battery and SSD, and the damn battery lasts for months before I have to recharge it. That is the kind of technology that was taken from us and replaced by resource-intensive devices governed by the logic of planned obsolescence. But I have it back—my world is not the same as your world, but it is a world I am glad to have returned to.</html:p>
    <html:p>Naturally, the first thing I wanted to do was use the iMac as a hub for synchronising the iPod with iTunes. This will work, but what I did not anticipate is that one of my main uses of the iPod is to listen to podcasts, and podcasts cannot be downloaded on the iMac because of the vicious imposition of TLS on all parts of the web that didn’t need it (<fr:link href="https://letsencrypt.org/" type="external">Let’s Encrypt</fr:link> really ought to have been called <html:em>Let’s Kill The Open Web</html:em>). So I continue synchronising my iPod with my modern day MacBook Air—and it is a testament to Apple’s historical approach to backward compatibility that this is still possible (and even integrated with the otherwise terrible Podcasts app!).</html:p>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
              <fr:month>4</fr:month>
              <fr:day>17</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AJ/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>jms-01AJ</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/jms-01AJ/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work › With a little love, everything has a use"><fr:link href="/jms-01AH/" title="Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AH/" display-uri="jms-01AH" type="local">Putting Mac OS X Tiger back to work</fr:link> › With a little love, <html:em>everything</html:em> has a use</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>Last week I finally realised that there is a lot I can still do with this machine. I turned it on when I had a bit of free time, and found that it remains very snappy—software opens instantly without hanging, and in fact the built-in programs are significantly less bug-ridden than they were in subsequent versions of Mac OS X and its (unworthy) successor macOS. To put this into perspective, the “outdated” iMac’s performance was far better than that of my last Intel iMac from 2020 with sixteen times the RAM and several times the processor cores.</html:p>
            <html:p>It is well-known that hardware capabilities get better and better each year, but this did not translate into improved performance for users until after the Apple Silicon transition—when the hardware improvement was so great that it was able to outpace the deathmarch of inefficient software, for a time. Don’t worry, the “transition to AI” is going to destroy all those gains soon and we’ll be back where we started.</html:p>
            <html:figure><html:img width="300px" src="/bafkrmiaaxhqvbslbd3sb6mafhlrxswbdbwipj4bzhuewlg7il73mhq7l7y.jpeg" />

    <html:figcaption>Mac OS X Tiger is still King—with the peak versions of Finder, Preview, and iTunes.</html:figcaption></html:figure>
            <html:p>But I digress. Even if you can’t use the Web, there are many things that a 19 year old iMac running Mac OS X Tiger is better at than a more recently manufactured machine. For example, Tiger was the last version of Mac OS X in which Preview.app (the PDF and image viewer) had a working search interface; from the subsequent version (Leopard) all the way until the present day, searching is somehow both too fuzzy and not fuzzy enough, and there seems to be no combination of quotation marks that will lead to reasonable results appearing in the search pane. (Same with Mail.app, which has somehow got <html:em>even worse</html:em> in the past year; you can’t connect to email on such an old machine anyway, so the point is moot.)</html:p>
            <html:p>Similarly, iTunes 7 was the functional peak for Apple’s music management and playback software (although iTunes 6 was visually superior), and people who have only used Apple’s current “Music” app will not be able to understand what they are missing. Likewise, the version of Finder shipped with Tiger was the most polished and least buggy version they ever produced; it is really amazing to switch back and forth between macOS 15.3 and Mac OS X 10.4, and find that most of the bugs or usability problems I have encountered on a daily basis for the past decade or so are actually <html:em>regressions</html:em>.</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AK/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AK</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AK/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="The perfect music and PDF reading workstation">The perfect music and PDF reading workstation</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>So I transferred my music and PDF libraries to the iMac—this was easy to do by creating a local WiFi network from the iMac, a functionality that has been removed in macOS(!). Indeed, modern macOS has replaced some (but not all) aspects of this functionality with what is called “Internet Sharing”, but this feature does not work reliably and in many cases the needful functionalities are unpredictably grayed out and disabled without any message explaining why. Death by a thousand papercuts... But I digress: I set up a local WiFi network with a file server easily using the old <html:em>System Preferences</html:em> application (don’t get me started on the bizarre redesign of System Settings introduced in macOS Ventura), and easily transferred everything I wanted to the iMac and then I was off to the races.</html:p>
                <html:p>I listen to music and study papers on this machine, and it gives me so much joy to <html:em>use</html:em> this masterpiece of practical industrial design every day—I even write referee reports on it using an ancient version of <fr:link href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnioutliner/" type="external">OmniOutliner</fr:link>, a venerable piece of software that I have to say has not improved much in the past two decades. After installing a copy of <fr:link href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/scrivener" type="external">Scrivener 2.5</fr:link> (don’t worry, I own a license for <fr:link href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/" type="external">Scrivener 3.0</fr:link> and you should too!), I find myself creative writing in my free time like it’s 2006.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/jonmsterling/" title="Jon Sterling" uri="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jonmsterling/" display-uri="jonmsterling" type="local">Jon Sterling</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2025</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>4</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>17</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-01AL/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>jms-01AL</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/jms-01AL/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="What about my iPod Classic?">What about my iPod Classic?</fr:title>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Some of you may be aware that I use an iPod Classic every day. The thing is a godsend—the best mobile device I own. I bought it with a fresh battery and SSD, and the damn battery lasts for months before I have to recharge it. That is the kind of technology that was taken from us and replaced by resource-intensive devices governed by the logic of planned obsolescence. But I have it back—my world is not the same as your world, but it is a world I am glad to have returned to.</html:p>
                <html:p>Naturally, the first thing I wanted to do was use the iMac as a hub for synchronising the iPod with iTunes. This will work, but what I did not anticipate is that one of my main uses of the iPod is to listen to podcasts, and podcasts cannot be downloaded on the iMac because of the vicious imposition of TLS on all parts of the web that didn’t need it (<fr:link href="https://letsencrypt.org/" type="external">Let’s Encrypt</fr:link> really ought to have been called <html:em>Let’s Kill The Open Web</html:em>). So I continue synchronising my iPod with my modern day MacBook Air—and it is a testament to Apple’s historical approach to backward compatibility that this is still possible (and even integrated with the otherwise terrible Podcasts app!).</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
